Preface

"The author arrived in the East as a missionary towards the end of 1839, and was stationed at Malacca for between three and four years. Before leaving England, he had enjoyed the benefit of a few months' instruction in Chinese from the late Professor Kidd at University College, London, and was able in the beginning of 1840 to commence the study of the first of the works in the present publication. It seemed to him then—and the experience of one and twenty years gives its sanction to the correctness of the judgment—that he should not be able to consider himself qualified for the duties of his position, until he had thoroughly mastered the classical books of the Chinese, and had investigated for himself the whole field of thought through which the sages of China had ranged, and in which were to be found the foundations of the moral, social, and political life of the people. Under this conviction he addressed himself eagerly to the reading of the Confucian Analects, and proceeded from the to the other works. Circumstances occurred in the mission at Malacca to throw various engagements upon him which left him little time to spend at his books, and he consequently sought about for all the assistance which he could find from the labours of men who had gone before.

"In this respect he was favourably situated, the charge of the Anglo-Chinese College having devolved upon him, so that he had free access to all the treasures in its library. He had translations and dictionaries in abundance, and they facilitated his progress. Yet he desiderated some some work upon the classics, more critical, more full and exact, than any which he had the opportunity of consulting, and he sketched to himself the plan of its execution. This was distinctly before him in 1841, and for several years he hoped to hear that some experienced Chinese scholar was preparing to give to the public something of the kind. As time went on, and he began to feel assured as to his own progress in the language, it occurred to him that hi might venture on such an undertaking himself. He studies, wrote out translations, and made notes, with the project in his mind. He hopes he can say that it did not divert him from the usual active labours of a missionary in preaching and teaching, but it did not allow him to rest satisfied in any operations of the time then being.

"In 1856 he first talked with some of his friends about his purpose, and among them was the Rev. Josiah Cox, of the Wesleyan Missionary Society. The question of the expense of publication came up. The author's idea was that by-and-by he would be able to digest his materials in readiness for the press, and that then he would be likely, on application, to meet with such encouragement from the British and other foreign merchants in China, as would enable him to go forward with his plan. Mr. Cox, soon after, without the slightest intimation of his intention, mentioned the whole matter to his friend, Mr. Joseph Jardine. In consequence of what he reported of Mr. Jardine's sentiments, the author had an interview with that gentleman, when he very generously undertook to bear the expense of carrying the work through the press. His lamented death leaves the author at liberty to speak more freely on this point than he would otherwise have done. Mr. Jardine expressed himself favourably of the plan, and said, 'I know the liberality of the merchants in China, and that many of them would readily give their help to such an undertaking, but you need not have the trouble of canvassing the community. If you are prepared for the toil of the publication, I will bear the expense of it. We make our money in China, and we should be glad to assist in whatever promises to be of benefit to it.'

"The author could not but but grateful to Mr. Jardine for his proffer, nor did he hesitate to accept it. The interruption of missionary labours, consequent on the breaking out of hostilities in the end of 1856, was favourable to retired and literary work, and he immediately set about preparing some of his materials for the press. A necessary visit to England in 1857, which kept him absent from the colony for eighteen months, proved a serious interruption, but the first-fruits of his labours are now in a state to be presented to the public."

The preface to the former edition of this volumn, when it was published at Hong Kong in 1861, commenced with the preceding paragraphs. The author has thought it desirable to reproduce them, as giving an account of the first conception in his mind of his labour on the Chinese classics, and of the circumstances under which his earlier volumes were published.

Though Mr. Jardine died before the publication of the first volume, the assistance given by him was continued with equal generosity by his brother, now Sir Robert Jardine, Baronet, until the second and third volumes had been published, and also during the preparation of the fourth and fifth volumes.

Soon after the publication of the fifth volume, which contained, besides the translation of the Confucian text, a version of all the notes and additions to it in the voluminous work of Tso Chʽiu-ming, the author was obliged to return to his country in 1873; but since he was appointed to his present position in the University here, translation of the Hsiao-ching, the Yi-ching, and the Li Chi, have been contributed by him to the series of The Sacred Books of the East, which has been issued from the Clarendon Press since 1879. He has thus done for the Confucian classics more than he contemplated in 1861. He then undertook to produce versions of what are called "The Four Books" and "The Five Ching," and added that "if life and health were spared" he would like to give a supplementary volume or two, so as to embrace all the books in the collection of "The Thirteen Ching," which began to appear under the Tʽang dynasty in our seventh century. He has translated ten of those books, including the extensive work of Tso Chʽiu-ming mentioned above. Other scholars have also done their mart. M. Edouard Biot, the younger, indeed, had published at Paris in 1851 his translation of Le Cheou Li, the Rites, or the Official Book, of the dynasty of Chou, under which Confucius lived; and in the present year Professor C. de Harlez, of Louvain, has given to the world a version of the other great ritual work, the Yi Li.

Thus all the "Thirteen Ching" of China have been made accessible to scholars of the west, excepting the Êrh Ya, which has been named The Literary Expositor, a lexical work, the precursor of the dictionaries which Chinese literature possesses in abundance.

To return to the volume of which a revised edition is now submitted to the public, the author would state that 1200 copies of it were printed in 1861. These were exhausted several years ago, and many calls for a new edition have come to him from China, to which only other engagements have prevented his responding sooner. So far as typographical execution is concerned, this edition ought to excel the former very much. Other improvements will also be discovered. The author has carefully gone over the text of the translation and notes. He is glad to have found occasion but rarely for correction and alteration of the former. He thought indeed at one time of recasting the whole version in a terser and more pretentious style. He determined, however, on refection to let it stand as it first occurred to him, his object having always been faithfulness to the original Chinese rather than grace of composition. Not that he is indifferent to the value of an elegant and idiomatic rendering in the language of the translation, and he hopes that he was able to combine in a considerable degree correctness of interpretation and acceptableness of style. He has to thank many friends whose Chinese scholarship is widely acknowledged for assuring him of this.

He has seen it objected to his translations that they were modelled on the views of the great critic and philosopher of the Sung dynasty, the well-known Chu Hsi. He can only say that he commenced and has carried on his labours with the endeavour to search out the meaning for himself, independent of all commentators. He soon became aware, however, of the beauty and strength of Chu's style, the correctness of his analysis, and the comprehension and depth of his thought. That his own views of passages generally coincide with those of The Old Man of the Cloudy Valley should be accepted, he submits, as complimentary to him rather than the reverse.

While this volume now reappears with few alterations of translation, it will be found that the alterations in the representation of proper names and names of Chinese characters generally are very many. The method adopted in it for the transliteration of their sounds may be considered as a compromise between that proposed by Sir Thomas F. Wade in his Hsin Ching Lu and that with which the author has become familiar through his work in connection with The Sacred Books of the East. The principal differences in the two transliterations are ǎ for ê, ǎu for ou, z for j, ze for zǔ, r for urh, and w for u.[1369] He has also given up attempting to reproduce in the notes and in the seventh appendix the names and tones of the southern Mandarin dialect, and has endeavoured to confine himself to the tones as given in the Hsin Ching lu.

J.L.

Oxford,

December, 1890.

III[864]

Tzǔ-lu said, "The ruler of Wei has been waiting for you, in order with you to administer the government. What will you consider the first thing to be done?"[865]

The Master replied, "What is necessary is to rectify names."[866]

"So, indeed!" said Tzǔ-lu. "You are wide of the mark! Why must there be such rectification?"

The Master said, "How uncultivated you are, Yu! A superior man, in regard to what he does not know, shows a cautious reserve.[867]

"If names be not correct, language is not in accordance with the truth of things. If language be not in accordance with the truth of things, affairs cannot be carried on to success.

"When affairs cannot be carried on to success, proprieties and music will not flourish. When proprieties and music do not flourish, punishments will not be properly awarded. When punishments are not properly awarded, the people do not know how to move hand or foot.[868]

"Therefore a superior man considers it necessary that the names he uses may be spoken appropriately, and also that what he speaks may be carried out appropriately. What the superior man requires, is just that in his words there may be nothing incorrect."

I[1145]

The head of the Chi family was going to attack Chuan-yü.[1146]

Jan Yu and Chi-lu had an interview with Confucius, and said, "Our chief, Chi, is going to commence operations against Chuan-yü."[1147]

Confucius said, "Chʽiu, is it not you who are in fault here?[1148]

"Now, in regard to Chuan-yü, long ago, a former king appointed its ruler to preside over the sacrifices to the eastern Mêng; moreover, it is in the midst of the territory of our state; and its ruler is a minister in direct connexion with the sovereign:—What has your chief to do with attacking it?"[1149]

Jan Yu said, "Our master wishes the thing; neither of us two ministers wishes it."[1150]

Confucius said, "Chʽiu, there are the words of Chou Jên,—'When he can put forth his ability, he takes his place in the ranks of office; when he finds himself unable to do so, he retires from it. How can he be used as a guide to a blind man, who does not support him when tottering, nor raise him up when fallen?'[1151]

"And further, you speak wrongly. When a tiger or rhinoceros escapes from his cage; when a tortoise or piece of jade is injured in its repository:—whose is the fault?"[1152]

Jan Yu said, "But at present, Chuan-yü is strong and near to Pi; if our chief do not now take it, it will hereafter be a sorrow to his descendants."

Confucius said. "Chʽiu, the superior man hates that declining to say—'I want such and such a thing,' and framing explanations for the conduct.[1153]

"I have heard that rulers of states and chiefs of families are not troubled lest their people should be few, but are troubled lest they should not keep their several places; that they are not troubled with fears of poverty, but are troubled with fears of a want of contented repose among the people in their several places. For when the people keep their several places, there will be no poverty; when harmony prevails, there will be no scarcity of people; and when there is such a contented repose, there will be no rebellious upsettings.[1154]

"So it is.—Therefore, if remoter people are not submissive, all the influences of civil culture and virtue are to be cultivated to attract them to be so; and when they have been so attracted, they must be made contented and tranquil.[1155]

"Now, here are you, Yu and Chʽiu, assisting your chief. Remoter people are not submissive, and, with your help, he cannot attract them to him. In his own territory there are divisions and downfalls, leavings and separations, and, with your help, he cannot preserve it.[1156]

"And yet he is planning these hostile movements within the state.—I am afraid that the sorrow of the Chi-sun family will not be on account of Chuan-yü, but will be found within the screen of their own court."[1157]

XXI[1248]

Tsai Wo asked about the three years" mourning for parents, saying that one year was long enough.[1249]

"If the superior man," said he, "abstains for three years from the observances of propriety, those observances will be quite lost. If for three years he abstains from music, music will be ruined.[1250]

"Within a year the old grain is exhausted, and the new grain has sprung up, and, in procuring fire by friction, we go through all the changes of wood for that purpose. After a complete year, the mourning may stop."[1251]

The Master said, "If you were, after a year, to eat good rice, and wear embroidered clothes, would you feel at ease?" "I should," replied Wo.[1252]

The Master said, "If you can feel at ease, do it. But a superior man, during the whole period of mourning, does not enjoy pleasant food which he may eat, nor derive pleasure from music which he may hear. He also does not feel at ease, if he is comfortably lodged. Therefore he does not do what you propose. But now you feel at ease and may do it."

Tsai Wo then went out, and the Master said, "This shows Yü's want of virtue. It is not till a child is three years old that it is allowed to leave the arms of its parents. And the three years" mourning is universally observed throughout the empire. Did Yü enjoy the three years" love of his parents?"[1253]

VII[1281]

Tzǔ-lu, following the Master, happened to fall behind, when he met an old man, carrying across his shoulder on a staff a basket for weeds. Tzǔ-lu said to him, "Have you seen my master, sir!" The old man replied, "Your four limbs are unaccustomed to toil; you cannot distinguish the five kinds of grain:—who is your master?" With this, he planted his staff in the ground, and proceeded to weed.[1282]

Tzǔ-lu joined his hands across his breast, and stood before him.[1283]

The old man kept Tzǔ-lu to pass the night in his house, killed a fowl, prepared millet, and feasted him. He also introduced to him his two sons.[1284]

Next day, Tzǔ-lu went on his way, and reported his adventure. The Master said, "He is a recluse," and sent Tzǔ-lu back to see him again, but when he got to the place, the old man was gone.

Tzǔ-lu then said to the family, "Not to take office is not righteous. If the relations between old and young may not be neglected, how is it that he sets aside the duties that should be observed between sovereign and minister? Wishing to maintain his personal purity, he allows that great relation to come to confusion. A superior man takes office, and performs the righteous duties belonging to it. As to the failure of right principles to make progress, he is aware of that."[1285]

I[1356]

Yao said, "Oh! you, Shun, the Heaven-determined order of succession now rests in your person. Sincerely hold fast the due mean. If there shall be distress and want within the four seas, the heavenly revenue will come to a perpetual end."[1357]

Shun also used the same language in giving charge to Yü.

Tʽang said, "I the child Lü, presume to use a dark-coloured victim, and presume to announce to Thee, O most great and sovereign God, that the sinner I dare not pardon, and thy ministers, O God, I do not keep in obscurity. The examination of them is by thy mind, O God. If, in my person, I commit offences, they are not to be attributed to you, the people of the myriad regions. If you in the myriad regions commit offences, these offences must rest on my person."[1358]

Chou conferred great gifts, and the good were enriched.[1359]

"Although he has his near relatives, they are not equal to my virtuous men. The people are throwing blame upon me, the one man."[1360]

He carefully attended to the weights and measures, examined the body of the laws, restored the discarded officers, and the good government of the kingdom took its course.

He revived states that had been extinguished, restored families whose line of succession had been broken, and called to office those who had retired into obscurity, so that throughout the kingdom the hearts of the people turned towards him.

What he attached chief importance to, were the food of the people, the duties of mourning, and sacrifices.

By his generosity, he won all. By his sincerity, he made the people repose trust in him. By his earnest activity, his achievements were great. By his justice, all were delighted.

He did not dislike to have his rice finely cleaned, nor to have his minced meat cut quite small.

He did not eat rice which had been injured by heat or damp and turned sour, nor fish or flesh which was gone. He did not eat what was discoloured, or what was of a bad flavour, nor anything which was ill-cooked, or was not in season.

He did not eat meat which was not cut properly, nor what was served without its proper sauce.

Though there might be a large quantity of meat, he would not allow what he took to exceed the due proportion for the rice. It was only in wine that he laid down no limit for himself, but he did not allow himself to be confused by it.

He did not partake of wine and dried meat bought in the market.

He was never without ginger when he ate.

He did not eat much.

When he had been assisting at the prince's sacrifice, he did not keep the flesh which he received overnight. The flesh of his family sacrifice he did not keep over three days. If kept over three days, people could not eat it.

When eating, he did not converse. When in bed, he did not speak.

Although his food might be coarse rice and vegetable soup, he would offer a little of it in sacrifice with a grave, respectful air.

Section II

The Authority of the Chinese Classics.

This subject will be discussed in connection with each separate work, and it is only designed here to exhibit generally the evidence on which the Chinese classics claim to be received as genuine productions of the time to which they are referred.

In the memoirs of the Former Han dynasty (BC 202–AD 24), we have one chapter which we may call the History of Literature. [1393] It commences thus: "After the death of Confucius,[1394] there was an end of his exquisite words; and when his seventy disciples had passed away, violence began to be done to their meaning. It came about that there were five different editions of the Chʽun Chʽiu, four of the Shih, and several of the Yi. Amid the disorder and collisions of the warring states (481–220), truth and falsehood were still more in a state of warfare, and a sad confusion marked the words of the various scholars. Then came the calamity inflicted under the Chʽin dynasty (BC 220–205), when the literary monuments were destroyed by fire, in order to keep the people in ignorance. But, by and by, there arose the Han dynasty, which set itself to remedy the evil wrong by the Chʽin. Great efforts were made to collect slips and tablets,[1395] and the way was thrown wide open for the bringing in of books. In the time of the emperor Hsiao-wu[1396] (BC 140–85), portions of the books being wanting and tablets lost, so that ceremonies and music were suffering great damage, he was moved to sorry, and said, 'I am very sad for this.' He therefore formed the plan of repositories, in which the books might be stored, and appointed officers to transcribe books on an extensive scale, embracing the works of the various scholars, that they might all be placed in the repositories. The emperor Chʽêng[1397] (BC 32–5), finding that a portion of the book still continued dispersed or missing, commissioned Chʽên Nung, the Superintendent of Guests,[1398] to search for undiscovered books throughout the empire, and by special edict ordered the chief of the banqueting house, Liu Hsiang,[1399], to examine the classical works, along with the commentaries on them, the writings of the scholars, and all poetical productions; the Master-controller of Infantry,Jên Hung,[1400] to examine the books on the art of war; the GRand Historiographer, Yin Hsien,[1401] to examine the books treating of the art of numbers (i.e. divination); and the Imperial Physician, Li Chu-kuo,[1402] to examine the books on medicine. Whenever any book was done with, Hsing forthwith arranged it, indexed it, and made a digest of it, which was presented to the emperor. While this work was in progress, Hsing died, and the emperor Ai (BC 6–AD 1) appointed his son, Hsin,[1403], as Master of the Imperial Carriages, to complete his father's work. On this, Hsin collected all the books, and presented a report of them, under seven divisions."

The first of these divisions seems to have been a general catalogue[1404] containing perhaps only the titles of the works included in the other six. The second embraced the classical works.[1405] From the abstract of it, which is preserved in the chapter referred to, we find that there were 294 collections of the Yi-ching from thirteen different individuals or editors;[1406] 412 collections of the Shu-ching, from nine different individuals; 416 volumes of the Shih-ching, from six different individuals;[1407] of the Books of Rites, 555 collections, from thirteen different individuals; of the Books on Music, 165 collections, from six different editors; 948 collections of History, under the heading of the Chʽun Chʽiu, from twenty-three different individuals; 229 collections of the Lun Yü, including the Analects and kindred fragments, from twelve different individuals; of the Hsiao-ching, embracing also the Ërh Ya, and some other portions of the ancient literature, 59 collections, from eleven different individuals; and finally of the lesser Learning, being works on the form of the characters, 45 collections, from eleven different individuals. The works of Mencius were included in the second division,[1408] among the writings of what were deemed orthodox scholars,[1409] of which there were 836 collections, from fifty-three different individuals.

The above important document is sufficient to show how the emperors of the Han dynasty, as soon as they had made good their possession of the empire, turned their attention to recover the ancient literature of the nation, the classical books engaging their first care, and how earnestly and effectively the scholars of the time responded to the wishes of their rulers. In addition to the time responded to the wishes of their rulers. In addition to the facts specified in the preface to it, I may relate that the ordinance of the Chʽin dynasty against possessing the classical books (with the exception, as it will appear in its proper place, of the Yi-ching) was repealed by the second sovereign of the Han, the emperor Hsiao Hui,[1410] in the fourth year of his reign BC 191, and that a large portion of the Shu-ching was recovered in the time of the third emperor, BC 179–157, while in the year BC 136 a special board was constituted, consisting of literati, who were put in charge of the five Ching.[1411]

The collections reported on by Liu Hsin suffered damage in the troubles which began AD 8, and continued till the rise of the second or eastern Han dynasty in the year 25. The founder of it (AD 25–57) zealously promoted the undertaking of his predecessors, and additional repositories were required for the books which were collected. His successors, the emperors Hsiao-ming/[1412] (58–75), Hsiao-chang[1413] (76–88), and Hsiao-huo[1414] (89–105), took a part themselves in the studies and discussions of the literary tribunal, and the emperor Hsiao-ling,[1415] between the years 172–178, had the text of the five Ching, as it had been fixed, cut in slabs of stone, and set up in the capital outside the gate of the Grand College. Some old accounts say that the characters were in three different forms, but they were only in one form;—see the 287th book of Chu Yi-Tsun's great work.

Since the Han, the successive dynasties have considered the literary monuments of the country to be an object of their special care. Many of them have issued editions of the classics, embodying the commentaries of preceding generations. No dynasty has distinguished itself more in this line than the present Manchu possessors of the empire. In fine, the evidence is complete that the classical books of China have come down from at least a century before our Christian era, substantially the same as we have them at present.

But it still remains to inquire in what condition we may suppose the books were, when the scholars of the Han dynasty commenced their labours upon them. They acknowledged that the tablets—we cannot here speak of manuscripts—were mutilated and in disorder. Was the injury which they had received of such an extent that all the care and study put forth on the small remains would be of little use? This question can be answered satisfactorily, only by an examination of the evidence which is adduced for the text of each particular classic; but it can be made apparent that there is nothing, in the nature of the case, to interfere with our believing that the materials were sufficient to enable the scholars to execute the work entrusted to them.

The burning of the ancient books by order of the founder of the Chʽin dynasty is always referred to as the greatest disaster which they sustained, and ith this is coupled the slaughter of many of the literati by the same monarch.

The account which we have of these transactions in the Historical Records is the following:[1416]

"In his 34th year (the 34th year, that is, after he had ascended the throne of Chʽin. It was only the 9th after he had been acknowledged sovereign of the empire, coinciding with BC 213), the emperor, returning from a visit to the south, which had extended as far as Yüeh, gave a feast in his palace at Xianyang, when the great scholars, amounting to seventy men, appeared and wished him long life.[1417] One of the principal ministers, Chou Chʽing-chʽên,[1418] came forward and said, 'Formerly, the state of Chʽin was only 1000 li in extent, but your majesty, by your spirit-like efficacy and intelligent wisdom, has tranquillised and settled the whole empire, and driven away all barbarous tribes, so that, wherever the sun and moon shine, all rulers appear before you as guests acknowledged subjection. You have formed the states of the various princes into provinces and districts, where the people enjoy a happy tranquillity, suffering no more from the calamities of war and contention. This condition of things will be transmitted for 10,000 generations. From the highest antiquity there has been no one in awful virtue like your majesty.'

"The emperor was pleased with this flattery, when Chʽun-yü Yüeh,[1419] one of the great scholars, a native of Chʽi, advanced and said, 'The sovereigns of Yin and Chou, for more than a thousand years, invested their sons and younger brothers, and meritorious ministers, with domains and rule, and could thus depend upon them for support and aid;—that I have heard. But now your majesty is in possession of all within the seas, and your sons and younger brothers are nothing but private individuals. The issue will be that someone will arise to play the part of Tʽien Chʽêng,[1420] or of the six nobles of Tsin. Without the support of your own family, where will you find the aid which you may require? That a state of things not modelled from the lessons of antiquity can long continue;—that is what I have not heard. Chʽing is now showing himself to be a flatterer, who increases the errors of your majesty, and not a loyal minister.'

"The emperor requested the opinions of others on this representation, and the premier, Li Ssǔ,[1421] said, 'The five emperors were not one the double of the other, nor did the three dynasties accept one another's ways. Each had a peculiar system of government, not for the sake of the contrariety, but as being required by the changed times. Now, your majesty has laid the foundations of imperial sway, so that it will last for 10,000 generations. This is indeed beyond what a stupid scholar can understand. And, moreover, Yüeh only talks of things belonging to the three dynasties, which are not fit to be models to you. At other times, when the princes were all striving together, they endeavoured to gather the wandering scholars about them; but now, the empire is in a stable condition, and laws and ordinances issue from one supreme authority. Let those of the people who abide in their homes give their strength to the toils of husbandry, while those who become scholars should study the various laws and prohibitions. Instead of doing this, however, the scholars do not learn what belongs to the present day, but study antiquity. They go on to condemn the present time, leading the masses of the people astray, and to disorder.

"'At the risk of my life, I, the prime minister, say: Formerly, when the nation was disunited and disturbed, there was no one who could give unity to it. The princes therefore stood up together; constant references were made to antiquity to the injury of the present state; baseless statements were dressed up to confound what was real, and men made a boast of their own peculiar learning to condemn what their rulers appointed. And now, when your majesty has consolidated the empire, and, distinguishing black from white, has constituted it a stable unity, they still honour their peculiar learning, and combine together; they teach men what is contrary to your laws. When they hear that an ordinance has been issued, everyone sets to discussing it with his learning. In the court, they are dissatisfied in heart; out of it, they keep talking in the streets. WHile they make a pretence of vaunting their master, they consider it fine to have extraordinary views of their own. And so they lead on the people to be guilty of murmuring and evil speaking. If these things are not prohibited, your majesty's authority will decline, and parties will be formed. The best way is to prohibit them. I pray that all the records in charge of the historiographers be burned, excepting those of Chʽin; that with the exception of those officers belonging to the Board of Great Scholars, all throughout the empire who presume to keep copies of the Shih-ching, or the books of the hundred schools, be required to go with them to the officers in charge of the several districts, and burn them;[1422] that all who may dare to speak together ab out the Shih and the Chu be put to death, and their bodies exposed in the marketplace; that those who make mention of the past, so as to blame the present, but put to death along with their relatives; that officers who shall know of the violation of those rules and not inform against the offenders, be held equally guilty with them; and that whoever shall not have burned their books within thirty days after the issuing of the ordinance, be branded and sent to labour on the wall for four years. The only books which should be spared are those on medicine, divination, and husbandry. WHoever wants to learn the laws may go to the magistrates and learn of them.'

"The imperial decision was—'Approved.'"

The destruction of the scholars is related more briefly. In the year after the burning of the books, the resentment of the emperor was excited by the remarks and flight of two scholars who had been favourites with him, and he determined to institute a strict inquiry about all of their class in Xianyang, to find out whether they had been making ominous speeches about him, and disturbing the minds of the people. The investigation was committed to the censors,[1423] and it being discovered that upwards of 460 scholars had violated the prohibitions, they were all buried alive in pits,[1424] for a warning to the empire, while degradation and banishment were employed more strictly than before against all who fell under suspicion. The emperor's eldest son, Fu-su, remonstrated with him, saying that such measures against those who repeated the words of Confucius and sought to imitate him, would alienate all the people from their infant dynasty, but his interference offended his father so much that he was sent off from court, to be with the general who was superintending the building of the great wall.

No attempts have been made by Chinese critics and historians to discredit the record of these events, though some have questioned the extent of the injury inflicted by them on the monuments of their ancient literature. [1425] It is important to observe that the edict against the books did not extent to the Yi-ching, which was exempted as being a work on divination, nor did it extend to the other classics which were in charge of the Board of Great Scholars. There ought to have been no difficulty in finding copies when the Han dynasty superseded that of Chʽin, and probably there would have been none but for the sack of the capital in BC 206 by Hsiang Yü, the formidable opponent of the founder of the House of Han. Then, we are told, the fired blazed for three months among the palaces and public buildings, and must have proved as destructive to the copies of the great scholars as the edict of the tyrant had been to the copies among the people.

It is to be noted also that the life of Shih Huang Ti lasted only three years after the promulgation of his edict. He died in BC 210, and the reign of his second son who succeeded him lasted only other three years. A brief period of disorder and struggling for the supreme authority between different chiefs ensued; but the reign of the founder of the Han dynasty dates from BC 202. Thus, eleven years were all which intervened between the order for the burning of the books and the rise of that family, which signalized itself by the care which it bestowed for their recovery; signalized itself by the care which it bestowed for their recovery; and from the edict of the tyrant of Chʽin against private individuals having copies in their keeping, to its express abrogation by the emperor Hsiao Hui, there were only twenty-two years. We may believe, indeed, that vigorous efforts to carry the edict into effect would not be continued longer than the life of its author,—that is, not for more than about three years. The calamity inflicted on the ancient books of China by the house of Chʽin could not have approached to anything like a complete destruction of them. There would be no occasion for the scholars of the Han dynasty, in regard to the bulk of their ancient literature, to undertake more than the work of recension and editing.

The idea of forgery by them on a large scale is out of the question. TRhe catalogues of Liang Hsin enumerated more than 13,000 volumes of a larger or smaller size, the productions of nearly 600 different writers, and arranged in thirty-eight subdivisions of subjects.[1426] In the third catalogue, the first subdivision contained the orthodox writers,[1427] to the number of fifty-three, with 836 works or portions of their works. Between Mencius and Kʽung Chi, the grandson of Confucius, eight different authors have place. The second subdivision contained the works of the Taoist school,[1428] amounting to 993 collections, from thirty-seven different authors. The sixth subdivision contained the Mohist writers,[1429] to the number of six, with their productions in 86 collections. I specify these two subdivisions, because they embrace the works of scholars or sects antagonistic to that of Confucius, and some of them still hold a place in Chinese literature, and contain many references to the five classics, and to Confucius and his disciples.

The inquiry pursued in the above paragraphs conducts us to the conclusion that the materials from which the classics, as they have come down to us, were compiled and edited in the two centuries preceding our Christian era, were genuine remains, going back to a still more remote period. The injury which they sustained from the dynasty of Chʽin was, I believe, the same in character as that to which they were exposed during all the time of "the warring states." It may have been more intense in degree, but the constant warfare which prevailed for some centuries among the different states which composed the kingdom was eminently unfavourable to the cultivation of literature. Mencius tells us how the princes had made away with many of the records of antiquity, from which their own usurpations and innovations might have been condemned.[1430] Still the times were not unfruitful, either in scholars or statesmen, to whom the ways and monuments of antiquity were dear, and the space from the rise of the Chʽin dynasty to the death of Confucius was not very great. It only amounted to 258 years. Between these two periods Mencius stands as a connecting link. Born probably in the year BC 371, he reached, by the intervention of Kʽung Chi, back to the sage himself, and as his death happened BC 288, we are brought down to within nearly half a century of the Chʽin dynasty. From all these considerations we may proceed with confidence to consider each separate work, believing that we have in these classics and books what the great sage of China and his disciples gave to their country more than 2000 years ago.

Section I

Formation of the Text of the Analects by the Scholars of the Han Dynasty.

When the work of collecting and editing the remains of the classical books was undertaken by the scholars of Han, there appeared two different copies of the Analects, one of Lu the native state of Confucius, and the other from Chʽi, the state adjoining. Between these there were considerable differences. The former consisted of twenty books or chapters, the same as those into which the classic is now divided. The latter contained two books in addition, and in the twenty books, which they had in common, the chapters and sentences were somewhat more numerous than in the Lu exemplar.

The names of several individuals are given, who devoted themselves to the study of those two copies of the Classic. Among the patrons of the Lu copy are mentioned the names of Hsia-hou Shêng, grand-tutor of the heir-apparent, who died at the age of 90, and in the reign of the emperor Hsüan (BC 73–49);[1431] Hsiao Wang-chih,[1432] a general-officer, who died in the reign of the emperor Yüan (BC 48–33); Wei Hsien, who was premier of the empire from BC 70–66; and his son Hsüan-chʽêng.[1433] As patrons of the Chʽi copy, we have Wang Chʽing, who was a censor in the year BC 99;[1434] Yung Shêng;[1435] and Wang Chi,[1436] a statesman who died in the beginning of the reign of the emperor Yüan.

But a third copy of the Analects was discovered about BC 150. One of the sons of emperor Ching was appointed king of Lu[1437] in the year BC 154, and sometime after, wishing to enlarge his palace, he proceeded to pull down the house of the Kʽung family, known as that where Confucius himself had lived. While doing so, there were found in the wall copies of the Shu-ching, the Chʽun Chʽiu, the Hsiao-ching, and the Lun Yü or Analects, which had been deposited there, when the edict for the burning of the books was issued. They were all written, however, in the most ancient form of the Chinese character,[1438] which had fallen into disuse, and the king returned them to the Kʽung family, the head of which, Kʽung An-kuo,[1439] gave himself to the study of them, and finally, in obedience to an imperial order, published a work called The Lun Yü, with Explanations of the Characters, and Exhibition of the Meaning.[1440]

The recovery of this copy will be seen to be a most important circumstance in the history of the text of the Analects. It is referred by Chinese writers, as "The old Lun Yü." In the historical narrative which we have of the affair, a circumstance is added which may appear to some minds to throw suspicion on the whole account. The king was finally arrested, we are told, in his purpose to destroy the house, by hearing the sounds of bells, musical stones, lutes, and citherns, as he was ascending the steps that led to the ancestral hall or temple. This incident was contrived, we may suppose, by the Kʽung family, to preserve the house, or it may have been devised by the historian to glorify the sage, but we may not, on account of it, discredit the funding of the ancient copies of the books. We have Kʽung An-kuo's own account of their being committed to him, and of the ways which he took to decipher them. The work upon the Analects, mentioned above, has not indeed come down to us, but his labours on the Shu-ching still remain.

It has been already stated, that the Lun Yü of Chʽi contained two books more than that of Lu. In this respect, the old Lun Yü agreed with the Lu exemplar. Those two books were wanting in it as well. The last book of the Lu Lun was divided in it, however, into two, the chapter beginning, "Yao said," forming a whole book by itself, and the remaining two chapters formed another book beginning "Tzǔ-chang." With this trifling difference, the old and the Lu copies appear to have agreed together.

Chang Yü, prince of An-chʽang,[1441] who died BC 4, after having sustained several of the highest offices of the empire, instituted a comparison between the exemplars of Lu and Chʽi, with a view to determine the true text. The result of his labours appeared in twenty-one books, which are mentioned in Liu Hsin's catalogue. They were known as the Lun of prince Chang,[1442] and commanded general approbation. To Chang Yü is commonly ascribed the ejecting from the classic the two additional books which the Chʽi exemplar contained, but Ma Tuan-lin prefers to rest that circumstance on the authority of the old Lun, which we have seen was without them.[1443] If we had the two books, we might find sufficient reason from their contents to discredit the. That may have been sufficient for Chang Yü to condemn them as he did, but we can hardly suppose that he did not have before him the old Lun, which had come to light about a century before he published his work.

In the course of the second century, a new edition of the Analects, with a commentary, was published by one of the greatest scholars which China has ever produced, Chêng Hsüan, known also as Chêng Kʽang-chʽêng.[1444] He died in the reign of the emperor Hsien (AD 190–220)[1445] at the age of 74, and the amount of his labours on the ancient classical literature is almost incredible. While he adopted the Lu Lun as the received text of his time, he compared it minutely with those of Chʽi and the old exemplar. In the last section of this chapter will be found a list of the readings in his commentary different from hose which are now acknowledged in deference to the authority of Chu Hsi, of the Sung dynasty. They are not many, and their importance is but trifling.

On the whole, the above statements will satisfy the reader of the care with which the text of the Lun Yü was fixed during the dynasty of Han.

Section II

At What Time, and by Whom, the Analects Were Written; Their Plan; and Authenticity.

At the commencement of the notes upon the first book, under the heading, "The Title of the Work," I have given the received account of its authorship, which preceded the catalogue of Liu Hsin. According to that, the Analects were compiled by the disciples of Confucius coming together after his death, and digesting the memorials of his discourses and conversations which they had severally preserved. But this cannot be true. We may believe, indeed, that many of the disciples put on record conversations which they had had with their master, and notes about his manners and incidents of his life, and that these have been incorporated with the work which we have, but that work must have taken its present form at a period somewhat later.

In Book VIII, chapters

iii

and

iv

, we have some notices of the last days of Tsêng Shên, and are told that he was visited on his deathbed by the officer Mêng Ching. Now Ching was the posthumous title of Chung-sun Chieh,[1446] and we find him alive (Li Chi II Pt. ii 2) after the death of duke Tao of Lu,\[1447] which took place BC 431, about fifty years after the death of Confucius.

Again,

Book XIX is all occupied with the sayings of the disciples. Confucius personally does not appear in it. Parts of it, as chapters

iii

,

xii

, and

xviii

, carry us down to a time when the disciples had schools and followers of their own, and were accustomed to sustain their teachings by referring to the lessons which they had heard from the sage.

Thirdly, there is the

second chapter

of Book XI, the second paragraph of which is evidently a note by the compilers of the work, enumerating ten of the principal disciples, and classifying them according to their distinguishing characteristics. We can hardly suppose it to have been written while any of the ten were alive. But there is among them the name of Tzǔ-hsia, who lived to the age of about a hundred. We find him, BC 407, three-quarters of a century after the death of Confucius, at the court of Wei, to the prince of which he is reported to have presented some of the classical books.[1448]

We cannot therefore accept the above account of the origin of the Analects,—that they were compiled by the disciples of COnfucius. Much more likely is the view that we owe the work to their disciples. In the note on

I ii 1

, a peculiarity is pointed out in the use of the surnames of Yu Jo and Tsêng Shên, which has made some Chines critics attribute the compilation to their followers. But this conclusion does not stand investigation. Others have assigned different portions to different schools. Thus

Book V

is given to the disciples of Tzǔ-king;

Book XI

, to those of Min Tzǔ-chien;

Book XIV

, to Yüan Hsien; and

Book XVI

has been supposed to be interpolated from the Analects of Chʽi. Even if we were to acquiesce in these decisions, we should have accounted only for a small part of the work. It is best to rest in the general conclusion, that it was compiled by the disciples of the disciples of the sage, making free use of the written memorials concerning him which they had received, and the oral statements which they had heard, from their several masters. And we shall not be far wrong, if we determine its date as about the end of the fourth, or the beginning of the fifth century before Christ.

In the critical work on the Four Books, called Record of Remarks in the Village of Jung,[1449] it is observe. "The Analects, in my opinion, were made by the disciples, just like this records of remarks. There they were recorded, and afterwards came a first-rate hand, who gave them the beautiful literary finish which we now witness, so that there is not a character which does not have its own indispensable place."[1450] We have seen that the first of these statements contains only a small amount of truth with regard to the materials of the Analects, nor can we receive the second. If one hand or one mind had digested the materials provided by many, the arrangement and the style of the work would have been different. We should not have had the same remark appearing in several books, with little variation, and sometimes with none at all. Nor can we account on this supposition for such fragments as the last chapters of the

ninth

,

tenth

, and

sixteenth

Books, and many others. No definite plan has been kept in view throughout. A degree of unity appears to belong to some Books more than others, and in general to the first ten more than to those which follows, but there is no progress of thought or illustration of subject from book to book. And even in those where the chapters have a common subject, they are thrown together at random more than on any plan.

We cannot tell when the work was first called the Lun Yü.[1451] The evidence in the preceding section is sufficient to prove that when the Han scholars were engaged in collecting the ancient books, it came before them, not in broken tablets, but complete, and arranged in books, or sections, as we now have it. The old copy was found deposited in the wall of the house which Confucius had occupied, and must have been placed there not later than BC 211, distant from the date which I have assigned to the compilation, not much more than a century and a half. That copy, written in the most ancient characters, was, possibly, the autograph of the compilers.

We have the writings, or portions of the writings, of several authors of the third and fourth centuries before Christ. Of these, in addition to The Great Learning, The Doctrines of the Mean, and The Works of Mencius, I have looked over the Works Hsün Chʽing[1452] of the orthodox school, of the philosophers Chuang and Lieh of the Taoist school,[1453] and the heresiarch Mo.[1454]

In the Great Learning, Commentary, chapter iv, we have the words of

Ana. XII xiii

. In the Doctrines of the Mean, ch. iii, we have

Ana. VII xxvii

; and in ch. xxviii 5, we have substantially

Ana. III ix

. In Mencius, II Pt. I ii 19, we have

Ana. VII xxxiii

, and in vii 2,

Ana. IV xxvii

; in III Pr. I iv 11,

Ana. VIII xviii

,

xix

; in IV Pt. I xiv 1,

Ana. XI xvi2

; in V Pt. II vii 9,

Ana. X xiii 4

; and in VII Pt. II xxxvii 1, 2, 8,

Ana. V xxi

,

XIII xxi

, and

XVIII xiii

. These quotations, however, are introduced by "The master said," or "Confucius said," no mention being made of any book called the Lun Yü, or Analects. In the Great Learning, Commentary, x 15, we have the words of

Ana. IV iii

, and in Mencius, III Pt. II vii 3, those of

Ana. XVII i

, but without any notice of quotation.

In the writings of Hsün Chʽing, Book I page 2, we find something like the words of

Ana. XV xxx

; and on p. 6, part of

XIV xxv

. But in these instances there is no mark of quotation.

In the writings of Chuang, I have noted only one passage where the words of the Analects are reproduced.

Ana. XVIII v

is found, but with large additions, and no reference of quotation, in his treatise on "Man in the world, associated with other man."[1455] In all those works, as well as in those of Lieh and Mo, the references to Confucius and his disciples, and to many circumstances of his life, are numerous.[1456] The quotations of sayings of his not found in the Analects are likewise many, especially in the Doctrine of the Mean, in Mencius, and in the works of Chuang. Those in the latter are mostly burlesque, but hose by the orthodox writers have more or less classical authority. Some of them may be found in the Chia Yü,[1457] or Narratives of the School, and in parts of the Li Chi, while others are only known to us by their occurrence in these writers. Altogether, they do not supply the evidence, for which I am in quest, of the existence of the Analects as a distinct work, bearing the name of the Lun Yü, prior to the Chʽin dynasty. They leave the presumption, however, in favour of those conclusions, which arises from the facts stated in the first section, undisturbed. They confirm it rather. They show that there was abundance of materials at hand to the scholars of Han, to compile a much larger work with the same title, if they had felt it their duty to do the business of compilation, and not that of editing.

Section III

Of Commentaries Open the Analects

It would be a vast and unprofitable labour to attempt to give a list of the commentaries which have been published on this work. My object is merely to point out how zealously the business of interpretation was undertaken, as soon as the text had been recovered by the scholars of the Han dynasty, and with what industry it has been preserved in down to the present times.

Mention has been made, in section I 6, of the Lun of prince Chang, published in the half century before our era. Pao Hsien,[1458] a distinguished scholar and officer, of the reign of Kuang-wu,[1459] the first emperor of the Eastern Han dynasty, AD 25–57, and another scholar of the surname Chou,[1460] less known but of the same time, published works, containing arrangements of this in chapters and sentences, with explanatory notes. The critical work of Kʽung An-kuo on the old Lun Yü has been referred to. That was lost in consequence of suspicious under which An-kuo fell towards the close of the reign of the emperor Wu, but in the time of the emperor Shun, AD 126–144, another scholar, Ma Jung,[1461] undertook the exposition of the characters in the old Lun, giving at the same time his views of the general meaning. The labours of Chêng Hsüan in the second century have been mentioned. Not long after his death, there ensued there ensued a period of anarchy, when the empire was divided into three governments, well known from the celebrated historical romance, called The Three Kingdoms. The strongest of them, the house of Wei, patronized literature, and three of its high officers and scholars, Chʽên Chʽün, Wang Su, and Chou Shêng-lieh,[1462] in the first half, and probably the second quarter, of the third century, all gave to the world their notes on the Analects.

Very shortly after, five of the great ministers of the government of Wei, Sun Yung, Chêng Chʽung, Tsʽao Hsi, Hsün Kʽai, and Ho Yen,[1463] united in the production of one great work, entitled, A Collection of Explanations of the Lun Yü.[1464] It embodied the labours of all the writers which have been mentioned, and, having been frequently reprinted by succeeding dynasties, it still remains. The preface of the five compilers, in the form of a memorial to the emperor, so called, of the house of Wei, is published with it, and has been of much assistance to me in writing these sections. Ho Yen was the leader among them, and the work is commonly quoted as if it were the production of him alone.

From Ho Yen downwards, there had hardly been a dynasty which has not contributed it labourers to the illustration of the Analects. In the Liang, which occupied the throne a good part of the sixth century, there appeared the Comments of Huang Kʽan,[1465] who to the seven authorities cited by Ho Yen added other thirteen, being scholars who had deserved well of the classic during the intermediate time. Passing over other dynasties, we come to the Sung, AD 960–1279. An edition of the classics was published by imperial authority, about the beginning of the eleventh century, with the title of The Correct Meaning. The principle scholar engaged in the undertaking was Hsing Pʽing.[1466] The portion of it on the Analects[1467] is commonly reprinted in "The Thirteen Classics," after Ho Yen's explanations. But the names of the Sung dynasty are all thrown into the shade by that of Chu Hsi, than whom China has not produced a greater scholar. He composed, or his disciples compiled, in the twelfth century, three works on the Analects:—the first called Collected Meanings;[1468] the second Collected Comments;[1469] and the third, Queries.[1470] Nothing could exceed the grace and clearness of his style, and the influence which he has exerted on the literature of China has been almost despotic.

The scholars of the present dynasty, however, seem inclined to question the correctness of his views and interpretations of the classics, and the chief place among them is due to Mao Chʽi-ling,[1471] known by the local name of Hsi-ho.[1472] His writings, under the name of The Collected Works of Hsi-ho,[1473] have been published in eighty volumes, containing between three and four hundred books or sections. He has nine treatises on the Four Books, or parts of them, and deserves to take rank with Chêng Hsüan and Chu Hsi at the head of Chinese scholars, though he is a vehement opponent of the latter. Most of his writings are to be found also in the great work called A Collection of Works on the Classics, under the Imperial Dynasty of Chʽing,[1474] which contains 1400 sections, and is a noble contribution by the scholars of the present dynasty to the illustration of its ancient literature.

Section I

Life of Confucius

"And have you foreigners surnames as well?" This question has often been put to me by Chinese. It marks the ignorance which belongs to the people of all that is external to themselves, and the pride of antiquity which enters largely as an element into their character. If such a pride could in any case be justified, we might allow it to the family of the Kʽung, the descendants of Confucius. In the reign of Kʽang-hsi, twenty-one centuries and a half after the death of the sage, they amounted to eleven thousand males. But their ancestry is carried back through a period of equal extent, and genealogical tables are common, in which the descent of Confucius is traced down from Huang-ti, in whose resign the cycle was invented, BC 2627.[1475]

The more moderate writers, however, content themselves with exhibiting his ancestry back to the commencement of the Chou dynasty, BC 121. Among the relatives of the tyrant Chou, the last emperor of the Yin dynasty, was an elder brother, by a concubine, named Chʽi,[1476] who is celebrated by Confucius,

Ana. XVIII i

, under the title of the viscount of Wei. Foreseeing the impending ruin of their family, Chʽi withdrew from the court; and subsequently he was invested by the emperor Chʽêng, the second of the house of Chou, with the principality of Sung, which embraced the eastern portion of the present province of Henan, that he might there continue the sacrifices to the sovereigns of Yin. Chʽi was followed as duke of Sung by a younger brother, in whose line the succession continued. His great-grandson, the the duke Min,[1477] was followed, BC 908, by a younger brother, leaving, however, two sons, Fu-fu Ho[1478] and Fu-ssǔ.[1479] Fu Ho[1480] resigned his right to the dukedom in favour of Fang-ssǔ, who put his uncle to death in BC 893, and became master of the state. He is known as the duke Li,[1481] and to his elder brother belongs the honour of having the sage among his descendants.

Three descents from Fu Ho, we find Chêng Kʽao-fu,[1482] who was a distinguished officer under the dukes Tai, Wu, and Hsüan (BC 799–728).[1483] He is still celebrated for his humility, and for his literary tastes. We have accounts of him as being in communication with the grand-historiographer of the kingdom, and engaged in researches about its ancient poetry, thus setting an example of one of the works to which Confucius gave himself.[1484] Kʽao gave birth to Kʽung-fu Chia,[1485] from whom the surname of Kʽung took its rise. Five generations had now elapsed since the dukedom was held in the direct line of his ancestry, and it was according to the rule in such cases that the branch should cease its connection with the ducal stem, and merge among the people under a new surname. Kʽung Chia was Master of the Horse in Sung, and an officer of well-known loyalty and probity. Unfortunately for himself, he had a wife of surpassing beauty, of whom the chief minister of the state, by the name Hua Tu,[1486] happened on one occasion to get a glimpse. Determined to possess her, he commenced a series of intrigues, which ended, BC 710, in the murder of Chia and of the ruling duke Shang.[1487] At the same time, Tu secured the person of the lady, and hastened to his palace with the prize, but on the way she had strangled herself with her girdle.

An enmity was thus commenced between the two families of Kʽung and Hua which the lapse of time did not obliterate, and the latter being the more powerful of the two, Chia's great-grandson withdrew into the state of Lu to avoid their persecution. There he was appointed commandant of the city of Fang,[1488] and is known in history by the name of Fang-shu.[1489] Fang-shu gave birth to Po-hsia,[1490] and from him came Shu-liang Ho,[1491] the father of Confucius. Ho appears in the history of the times as a soldier of great prowess and daring bravery. In the year of BC 562, when serving at the siege of a place called Fu-yang,[1492] a party of the assailants made their way in at a gate which had purposely been left open, and no sooner were they inside than the portcullis was dropped. Ho was just entering; and catching the massive structure with both his hands, he gradually by dint of main strength raised it and held it up, till his friends had made their escape.

Thus much on the ancestry of the sage. Doubtless he could trace his descent in the way which has been indicated up to the imperial house of Yin, nor was there one among his ancestors during the rule of Chou to whom he could not refer with satisfaction. They had been ministers and soldiers of Sung and Lu, all men of worth and in Chêng Kʽao, both for his humility and literary researches, Confucius might have special complacency.

Confucius was the child of Shu-liang Ho's old age. The soldier had married in early life, but his wife brought him only daughters,—to the number of nine, and no son. By a concubine he had a son, named Mêng-pʽi, and also Po-ni,[1493] who proved a cripple, sothat, when he was over seventy years, Ho sought a second wife in the Yen family,[1494] from which came subsequently Yen Hui, the favourite disciple of his son. There were three daughters in the family, the youngest being named Chêng-tsai.[1495] Their father said to them, "Here is the commandant of Tsou. His father and grandfather were only scholars, but his ancestors before them were descendants of the sage sovereigns. He is a man ten feet high,[1496] and of extraordinary prowess, and I am very desirous of his alliance. Though he is old and austere, you need have no misgivings about him. Which of you three will be his wife?" The two elder daughters were silent, but Chêng-tsai said "Why do you ask us, father? It is for you to determine." "Very well," said her father in reply, "you will do." Chêng-tsai, accordingly, became Ho's wife, and in due time gave birth to Confucius, who received the name of Chʽiu, and was subsequently styled Chung-ni.[1497] The event happened on the twenty-first day of the tenth month of the twenty-first year of the duke Hsiang, of Lu, being the twentieth year of the emperor Ling, BC 552.[1498] The birth-place was in the district of Tsou,[1499] of which Ho was the governor. It was somewhere within the limits of the present department of Yanzhou in Shandong, but the honour of being the exact spot is claimed for two places in two different districts of the department.

The notices which we have of Confucius's early years are very scanty. When he was in his third year his father died. It is related of him, that as a boy he used to play at the arrangement of sacrificial vessels, and at postures of ceremony. Of his schooling we have no reliable account. There is a legend, indeed, that at seven he went to school to Yen Pʽing-chung,[1500] but it must be rejected as Pʽing-chung belonged to the state of Chʽi. He tells us himself that at fifteen he bent his mind to learning;[1501] but the condition of the family was one of poverty. At a subsequent period, when people were astonished at the variety of his knowledge, he explained it by saying, "When I was young, my condition was low, and therefore I acquired my ability in many things; but they were mean matters."[1502]

When he was nineteen, he married a lady from the state of Sung, of the Chien-kuan family,[1503] and in the following year his son Li was born. On the occasion of this event, the duke Chao sent him a present of a couple of carp. It was to signify his sense of his prince's favour, that he called his son Li (the carp), and afterwards gave him the designation of Po-yü[1504] (fish primus). No mention is made of the birth of any other children, though we know, from

Ana. V i

, that he had at least one daughter. We know also, from an inscription on her grave, that he had one other daughter, who died when he was quite young. The fact of the duke of Lu's sending him a gift on the occasion of Li's birth, shows that he was not unknown, but was already commanding public attention and the respect of the great.

It was about this time, probably in the year after his marriage, that Confucius took his first public employment, as keeper of the stores of grain,[1505] and in the following year he was put in charge of the public fields and lands.[1506] Mencius adduces these employments in illustration of his doctrine that the superior man say at times take office on account of his poverty, but must confine himself in such a case to places of small emolument, and aim at nothing but the discharge of their humble duties. According to him, Confucius, as keeper of stores, said, "My calculations must all be right:—that is all I have to care about;" and when in charge of the public fields, he said, "The oxen and sheep must be fat and strong and superior:—that is all I have to care about."[1507] It does not appear whether these offices were held by Confucius in the direct employment of the state, or as a dependent of the Chi family in whose jurisdiction he lived. The present of the carp from the duke may incline us to suppose the former.

In his twenty-second year, Confucius commenced his labours as a public teacher, and his house became a resort for young and inquiring spirits, who wished to learn the doctrines of antiquity. However small the fee his pupils were able to afford, he never refused his instructions.[1508] All that he required, was an ardent desire for improvement, and some degree of capacity. "I do not open up the truth," he said, "to one who is not eager to get knowledge, nor help out anyone who is not anxious to explain himself. When I have presented one corner of a subject to anyone, and he cannot from it learn the other three, I do not repeat my lesson."[1509]

His mother died in the year BC 527, and he resolved that her body should lie in the same grave with that of his father, and that their common resting-place should be in Fang, the first home of the Kʽung in Lu. But here a difficulty presented itself. His father's coffin had been for twenty years where it had first been deposited, off the road of The Five Fathers, in the vicinity of Tsou:—would it be right in him to move it? He was relieved from this perplexity by an old woman of the neighbourhood, who told him that the coffin had only just been put into the ground, as a temporary arrangement, and not regularly buried. On learning this, he carried his purpose into execution. Both coffins were conveyed to Fang, and put in the ground together, with no intervening space between them, as was the custom in some states. And now came a new perplexity. He said to himself, "In old times, they had graves, but raised no tumulus over them. But I am a man, who belongs equally to the north and the south, the east and the west. I must have something by which I can remember the place." Accordingly he raised a mound, four feet high, over the grave, and returned home, leaving party of his disciples to see everything properly completed. In the meantime there came on a heavy storm of rain, and it was a considerable time before the disciples joined him. "What makes you so late?" he asked. "The grave in Fang fell down," they said. He made no reply, and they repeated their answer three times, when he burst into tears, and said, "Ah! they did not make their grave so in antiquity."[1510]

Confucius mourned for his mother the regular period of three years,—three years nominally, but in fact only twenty-seven months. Five days after the mourning was expired, he played on his lute, but could not sing. It required other five days before he could accompany an instrument with his voice.[1511]

Some writers have represented Confucius as teaching his disciples important lessons from the manner in which he buried his mother, and having a design to correct irregularities in the ordinary funeral ceremonies of the time. These things are altogether "without book." We simply have a dutiful son paying the last tribute of affection to a good parent. In one point he departs from the ancient practice, raising a mound over the grave, and when the fresh earth gives way from a sudden rain, he is moved to tears, and seems to regret his innovation. This sets Confucius vividly before us,—a man of the past as much as of the present, whose own natural feelings were liable to be hampered in their development by the traditions of antiquity which he considered sacred. It is important, however, to observe the reason which he gave for rearing the mound. He had in it a presentiment of much of his future course. He was "a man of the north, the south, the east, and the west." He might not confine himself to any one state. He would travel, and his way might be directed to some "wise ruler," whom his counsels would conduct to a benevolent sway that would break forth on every side till it transformed the empire.

When the mourning for his mother was over, Confucius remained in Lu, but in what special capacity we do not know. Probably he continued to encourage the resort of inquirers to whom he communicated instruction, and pursued his own researches into the history, literature, and institutions of the empire. In the year BC 525, the chief of the small state of Tʽan,[1512] made his appearance at the court of Lu, and discoursed in a wonderful manner, at a feast given to him by the duke, about the names which the most ancient sovereigns, from Huang-ti downwards, gave to their ministers. The sacrifices to the emperor Shao-hao, the next in descent from Huang-ti, were maintained in Tʽan, so that the chief fancied that he knew all about the abstruse subject on which he discoursed. Confucius, hearing about the matter, waited on the visitor, and learned from him all that he had to communicate.[1513]

To the year BC 525, when Confucius was twenty-nine years old, is referred his studying music under a famous master of the name of Hsiang.[1514] He was approaching his thirtieth year when, as he tells us, "he stood"[1515] firm, that is, in his convictions on the subjects of learning to which he had bent his mind fifteen years before. Five years more, however, were still to pass by, before the anticipation mentioned in the conclusion of the last paragraph began to receive its fulfilment,[1516] though we may conclude from the way in which it was brought about that he was growing all the time in the estimation of the thinking minds in his native state.

In the twenty-fourth year of duke Chao, BC 518, one of the principal ministers of Lu, known by the name of Mêng Hsi, died. Seventeen years before, he had painfully felt his ignorance of ceremonial observances, and had made it his subsequent business to make himself acquainted with them. On his deathbed, he addressed his chief officer, saying, "A knowledge of propriety is the stem of a man. Without it he has no means of standing firm. I have heard that there is one Kʽung Chʽiu, who is thoroughly versed in it. He is descendant of sages, and though the line of his family was extinguished in Sung, among his ancestors there were Fu-fu Ho, who resigned the state to his brother, and Chang Kʽao-fu, who was distinguished for his humility. Tsang Ho has observed that if sage men of intelligent virtue do not attain to eminence, distinguished men are sure to appear among their posterity. His words are now to be verified I think, in Kʽung Chʽiu. After my death, you must tell Ho-chi to go and study proprieties under him."[1517] In consequence of this charge, Ho-chi,[1518] Mêng Hsi's son, who appears in the Analects under the name of Mêng Yi,[1519] and a brother, or perhaps only a near relative, named Nan-kung Chêng-shu,[1520] became disciples of Confucius. Their wealth and standing in the state gave him a position which he had not had before, and he told Chêng-shu of a wish which he had to visit the court of Chou, and especially to confer on the subject of ceremonies and music with Lao Tan. Chêng-shu represented the matter to the Chʽao, who put a carriage and a pair of horses at Confucius's disposal for the expedition.[1521]

At this time the court of Chou was in the city Lo,[1522] in the present department of Henan of the province of the same name. The reigning sovereign is known by the title of Ching,[1523] but the sovereignty was little more than nominal. The state of China was then analogous to that one of the European kingdoms during the prevalence of the feudal system. At the commencement of the dynasty, the various states of the kingdom had been assigned to the relatives and adherents of the reigning family. There were thirteen principalities of greater note, and a large number of smaller dependencies. During the vigorous youth of the dynasty, the sovereign lord paramount exercised an effective control over the various chiefs, but with the lapse of time there came weakness and decay. The chiefs—corresponding somewhat to European dukes, earls, marquises, barons, etc.—quarrelled and warred among themselves, and the stronger among them barely acknowledged their subjection to the sovereign. A similar condition of things prevailed in each particular state. There there were hereditary ministerial families, who were continually encroaching on the authority of their rulers, and the heads of those families again were frequently hard pressed by their inferior officers. Such was the state of China in Confusius's time. The read must have it clearly before him, if he would understand the position of the sage, and the reforms which, we shall find, it was subsequently his object to introduce.

Arrived at Chou, he had no intercourse with the court or any of the principal ministers. He was there not as a politicians, but as an inquirer about the ceremonies and maxims of the founders of the existing dynasty. Lao Tan,[1524] whom he had wished to see, generally acknowledged as the founder of the Taoists, or rationalistic sect (so called), which has maintained its ground in opposition to the followers of Confucius, was then a curator of the royal library. They met and freely interchanged their views, but no reliable account of their conversations has been preserved. In the fifth book of the Li Chi, which is headed "The philosopher Tsêng asked," Confucius refers four times to the views of Laozi on certain points of funeral ceremonies, and in the Narratives of the School, book XXIV, he tells Chi Kʽang what he had heard from him about, "The Five Tis," but we may hope their conversation turned also on more important subjects. Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, favourable to Laozi, makes hi lecture his visitor in the following style:—"Those whom you talk about are dead, and their bones are mouldered to dust; only their words remain. When the superior man gets his time, he mounts aloft; but when the time is against him, he moves as if his feet were entangled. I have heard that a good merchant, though he has rich treasures deeply stored, appears as if he were poor, and that the superior man whose virtue is complete, is yet to outward seeming stupid. Put away your proud air and many desires, your insinuating habit and wild will.[1525] These are of no advantage to you. This is all which I have to tell you." On the other hand, Confucius is made to say to his disciples, "I know how birds can fly, how fishes can swim, and how animals can run. But the runner may be snarled, the swimmer may be hooked, and the flyer may be shot by the arrow. But there is the dragon. I cannot tell how he mounts on the wind through the clouds, and rises to heaven. Today I have seen Laozi, and can only compare him to the dragon."[1526]

While at Lo, Confucius walked over the grounds set apart for the great sacrifices to heaven and earth; inspected the pattern of the Hall of Light, built to give audience in to the princes of the kingdom; and examined all the arrangements of the ancestral temple and the court. From the whole he received a profound impression. "Now," said he with a sigh, "I know the sage wisdom of the duke of Chou, and how the house of Chou attained to the royal sway."[1527] On the walls of the Hall of Light were paintings of the ancient sovereigns from Yao and Shun downwards, their characters appearing in the representations of them, and words of praise or warning being appended. There was also a picture of the duke of Chou sitting with his infant nephew, the king Ching, upon his knees, to give audience to all the princes. Confucius surveyed the scene with silent delight, and then said to his followers, "Here you see how Chou became so great. As we use a glass to examine the forms of things, so must we study antiquity in order to understand the present time."[1528] In the hall of the ancestral temple, there was a metal statue of a man with three clasps upon his mouth, and his back covered over with an enjoyable homily on the duty of keeping a watch upon the lips. Confucius turned to his disciples and said, "Observe it, my children. These words are true, and commend themselves to our feelings."[1529]

About music he made inquiries at Chêng Hung, to whom the following remarks are attributed:—"I have observed about Chung-ni many marks of a sage. He has river eyes and a dragon forehead,—the very characteristics of Huang-ti. His arms are long, his back is like a tortoise, and he is nine feet six inches in height,—the very semblance of Tʽang the Completer. When he speaks, he praises the ancient kings. He moves along the path of humility and courtesy. He has heard of every subject, and retains with a strong memory. His knowledge of things seems inexhaustible.—Have we not in him the rising of a sage?"[1530]

I have given these notices of Confucius at the court of Chou, more as being the only ones I could find, than because I put much faith in them. He did not remain there long, but returned the same year to Lu, and continued his work of teaching. His fame was greatly increased; disciples. Came to him from different parts, till their number amounted to three thousand. Several of those who have come down to us as the most distinguished among his followers, however, were yet unborn, and the statement just given may be considered as an exaggeration. We are not to conceive of the disciples as forming a community, and living together. Parties of them may have done so. We shall find Confucius hereafter always moving amid a company of admiring pupils; but the greater number must have had their proper avocations and ways of living, and would only resort to the master, when they wished specially to ask his counsel or to learn of him.

In the year succeeding the return to Lu, that state fell into great confusion. There were three families in it, all connected irregularly with the ducal house, which had long kept the rulers in a condition of dependency. They appear frequently in the Analects as the Chi clan, the Shu, and the Mêng; and while Confucius freely spoke of their usurpations,[1531] he was a sort of dependent of the Chi family, and appears in frequent communication with members of all the three. In the year BC 517, the duke Chao came to open hostilities with them, and being worsted, fled into Chʽi, the state adjoining Lu on the north. Thither Confucius also repaired, that he might avoid the prevailing disorder of his native state. Chʽi was then under the government of a ruler (in rank a marquis, but historically called duke), afterwards styled Ching,[1532] who "had a thousand teams, each of four horses, but on the day of his death the people did not praise him for a single virtue."[1533] His chief minister, however, was Yen Ying,[1534] a man of considerable ability and worth. At his court the music of the ancient sage-emperor, Shun, originally brought to Chʽi from the state of Chʽên,[1535] was still preserved.

According to the Narratives of the School, in incident occurred on the way Chʽi, which I may transfer to these pages as a good specimen of the way in which Confucius turned occurring matters to account, in his intercourse with his disciples. As he was passing by the side of the Tai mountain, there was a woman weeping and wailing by a grave. Confucius bent forward in his carriage, and after listening to her for some time, sent Tzǔ-lu to ask the cause of her grief. "You weep, as if you had experienced sorrow open sorrow," said Tzǔ-lu. The woman replied, "It is so. My husband's father was killed here by a tiger, and my husband also; and now my son has met the same fate." Confucius asked her why she did not remove from the place, and on her answering, "There is here no oppressive government," he turned to his disciples, and said, "My children, remember this. Oppressive government is fiercer than a tiger."[1536]

As soon as he crossed the border from Lu, we are told he discovered from the gait and manner of a boy, whom he saw carrying a pitcher, the influence of the sages' music, and told the driver of his carriage to hurry on to the capital.[1537] Arrived there, he heard the strain, and was so ravished with it, that for three months he did not know the taste of flesh. "I did not think," he said, "that music could have been made so excellent as this."[1538] The duke Ching was pleased with the conferences which he had with him,[1539] and proposed to assign to him the town of Lin-chʽiu, from the revenues of which he might derive a sufficient support; but Confucius refused the gift, and said to his disciples, "A superior man will only receive reward for services which he has done. I have given advice to the duke Ching, but he has not yet obeyed it, and now he would endow me with this place! Very far is he from understanding me!"/[1540]

On one occasion the duke asked about government, and received the characteristic reply, "There is government when the ruler is ruler, and the minister is minister; when the father is father, and the son is son."[1541] I say that the reply is characteristic. Once, when Tzǔ-lu asked him what he would consider the first thing to be done if entrusted with the government of a state, Confucius answered, "What is necessary is to rectify names."[1542] The disciple thought the reply wide of the mark, but it was substantially the same with what he said to the marquis Ching. There is sufficient foundation in nature for government in the several relations of society, and if those be maintained and developed according to their relative significancy, it is sure to obtain. This was a first principle in the political ethics of Confucius.

Another day the duke got to a similar inquiry the reply that the art of government lay in an economical use of the revenues; and being pleased, he resumed his purpose of retaining the philosopher in his state, and proposed to assign to him the fields of Ni-chi. His chief minister Yen Ying dissuaded him from the purpose saying, "Those scholars are impracticable, and cannot be imitated. They are haughty and conceited of their own views, so that they will not be content in inferior positions. They set a high value on all funeral ceremonies, give way to their grief, and will waste their property on great burials, so that they would only be injurious to the common manners. This Mr. Kʽung has a thousand peculiarities. It would take generations to exhaust all that he knows about the ceremonies of going up and going down. This is not the time to examine into his rules propriety. If you, prince, wish to employ him to change the customs of Chʽi, you will not be making the people your primary consideration."[1543]

I had rather believe that these were not the words of Yen Ying, but they must represent pretty correctly the sentiments of many of the statesmen of the time about Confucius. The duke of Chʽi got tired ere long of having such a monitor about him, and observed, "I cannot treat him as I would the chief of the Chi family. I will treat him in a way between that accorded to the chief of the Chi, and that given to the chief of the Mêng family." Finally he said, "I am old; I cannot use his doctrines."[1544] These observations were made directly to Confucius, or came to his hearing.[1545] It was not consistent with his self-respect to remain longer in Chʽi, and he returned to Lu.[1546]

Returned to Lu, he remained for the long period of about fifteen years without being engaged in any official employment. It was a time, indeed, of great disorder. The duke Chao continued a refugee in Chʽi, the government being in the hands of the great families, up to his death in BC 510, on which event the rightful heir was set aside, and another member of the ducal house, known to us by the title of Ting,[1547] substituted in his place. The ruling authority of the principality became thus still more enfeebled than it had been before, and, on the other hand, the chiefs of the Chi, the Shu, and the Mêng, could hardly keep their ground against their own officers. Of those latter, the two most conspicuous were Yang Hu,[1548] called also Yang Huo,[1549]and Kung-shan Fu-jao.[1550] At one time Chi Huan, the most powerful of the chiefs, was kept a prisoner by Yang Hu, and was obliged to make terms with him in order to obtain his liberation. Confucius would give his countenance to none, as he disapproved of all, and he studiously kept aloof from them. Of how he comported himself among them we have a specimen in the incident related in the

Analects, XVIII i

—"Yang Huo wished to see Confucius, but Confucius would not go see him. On this, he sent a present of a pig to Confucius, who, having chosen a time when Huo was not at home, went to pay his respects for the gift. He met him, however, on the way. 'Come, let me speak with you,' said the officer. 'Can he be called benevolent, who keeps his jewel in his bosom, and leaves his country to confusion?' Confucius replied, 'No.' 'Can he be called wise, who is anxious to be engaged in public employment, and yet is constantly losing the opportunity of being so?' Confucius against said, 'No.' The other added, 'The days and months are passing away; the years do not wait for us.' Confucius said, 'Right; I will go into office.'" Chinese writers are eloquent in their praises of the sage for the combination of propriety, complaisance and firmness, which they see in his behaviour in this matter. To myself there seems nothing remarkable in it but a somewhat questionable dexterity. But it was well for the fame of Confucius that his time was not occupied during those years with official services. He turned them to better account, prosecuting his researches into the poetry, history, ceremonies, and music of the nation. Many disciples continued to resort to him, and the legendary writers tell us how he employed their services in digesting the results of his studies. I must repeat, however, that several of them, whose names are most famous, such as Tsêng Shên, were as yet children, and Min Sun[1551] was not born till BC 500.

To this period we must refer the almost single instance which we have of the manner of COnfucius's intercourse with his son Li. "Have you heard any lessons from your father different from what we have all heard?" asked one of the disciples once of Li. "No," said Li. "He was standing along once, when I was passing through the court below with hasty steps, and said to me, 'Have you learned the odes?' On my replying, 'Not yet,' he added, 'If you do not learn the odes, you will not be fit to converse with.' Another day, in the same place and the same way, he said to me, 'Have you read the rules of propriety?' On my replying, 'Not yet,' he added, 'If you do not learn the rules of propriety, your character cannot be established.' I have heard only these two things from him." The disciple was delighted and observed, "I asked one thing, and I have got three things. I have heard about the odes. I have heard about the rules of propriety. I have heard about the odes. I have heard about the rules of propriety. I have also heard that the superior man maintains a distant reserve towards his son."[1552]

I can easily believe that this distant reserve was the rule which Confucius followed generally in his treatment of his son. A stern dignity is the quality which a father has to maintain upon his system. It is not to be without the element of kindness, but that must never go beyond the line of propriety. There is too little room left for the play and development of natural affection.

The divorce of his wife must also have taken place during these years, if it ever took place at all, which is a disputed point. The curious reader will find the question discussed in the notes on the second book of the Li Chi. The evidence inclines, I think, against the supposition that Confucius did put his wife away. When she died, at a period subsequent to the present, Li kept on weeping aloud for her after the period for such a demonstration of grief had expired, when Confucius sent a message to him that his sorry must be subdued, and the obedient son dried his tears.[1553] We are glad to know that on one occasion—the death of his favourite disciple, Yen Hui—the tears of Confucius himself would flow over and above the measure of propriety.[1554]

We come to the short period of Confucius's official life. In the year BC 501, things had come to a head between the chiefs of the three families and their ministers, and had resulted in the defeat of the latter. In that year the resources of Yang Huo were exhausted, and he fled into Chʽi, so that the state was delivered from its greatest troubler, and the way was made more clear for Confucius to go into office, should an opportunity occur. It soon presented itself. Towards the end of that year he was made chief magistrate of the town of Chung-tu.[1555]

Just before he received this appointment, a circumstances occurred of which we do not well know what to make. When Yang-huo fled into Chʽi, King-shan Fu-jao, who had been confederate with him, continued to maintain a attitude of rebellion, and held the city of Pi against the Chi family. Thence he sent a message to Confucius inviting him to join him, and the sage seemed so inclined to go that his disciple Tzǔ-lu remonstrated with him, saying, "Indeed you cannot go! why must you think of going to see Kung-shan?" Confucius replied, "Can it be without some reason that he had invited me? If anyone employ me, may I not make an eastern Chou?"[1556] The upshot, however, was that he did not go, and I cannot suppose that he had ever any serious intention of doing so. Amid the general gravity of his intercourse with his followers, there gleam out a few instances of quiet pleasantry, when he amused himself by playing with their notions about him. This was probably one of them.

As magistrate of Chung-tu he produced a marvellous reformation of the manners of the people in a short time. According to the Narratives of the School, he enacted rules for the nourishing of the living and all observances to the dead. Different food was assigned to the old and the young, and different burdens to the strong and the weak. Males and females kept apart from each other in the streets. A thing dropped on the road was not picked up. There was no fraudulent carving of vessels. Inner coffins were made four inches thick, and the outer ones five. Graves were made on the high grounds, no mounds being raised over them, and no trees planted about them. Within twelve months, the princes of the other states all wished to imitate his style of administration.[1557]

The duke Ting, surprised at what he saw, asked whether his rules could be employed to govern a whole state, and Confucius told him that they might be applied to the whole kingdom. On this the duke appointed him assistant-superintendent of works,[1558] in which capacity he surveyed the lands of the state, and made many improvements in agriculture. From this he was quickly made minister of crime,[1559] and the appointed was enough to put an end to crime. There was no necessity to put the penal laws in execution. No offenders showed themselves.[1560]

These indiscriminating eulogies are of little value. One incident, related in the annotations of Tso-shih on the Chʽun-Chʽiu, commends itself at once to our belief, as in harmony with Confucius's character. The chief of the Chi, pursuing with his enmity the duke Chao, even after his death, had placed his grave apart from the graves of his predecessors; and Confucius surrounded the ducal cemetery with a ditch so as to include the solitary resting-place, boldly telling the chief that he did it to hide his disloyalty.[1561] But he signalised himself most of all in BC 500, by his behaviour at an interview between the dukes of Lu and Chʽi, at a place called Shih-chi,[1562] and Chia-ku,[1563] in the present district of Lai-wu, in the department of Tʽai-an.[1564] Confucius was present as master of ceremonies on the part of Lu, and the meeting was professedly pacific. The two princes were to form a covenant of alliance. The principal officer on the part of Chʽi, however, despising Confucius as "a man of ceremonies, without courage," had advised his sovereign to make the duke of Lu a prisoner, and for this purpose a band of the half-savage original inhabitants of the place advanced with weapons to the stage where the two dukes were met. Confucius understood the scheme, and siad to the opposite party, "Our two princes are met for a pacific object. For you to bring a band of savage vassals to disturb the meeting with their weapons, is not the way in which Chʽi can expect to give law to the princes of the kingdom. These barbarians have nothing to do with our great flowery land. Such vassals may not interfere with our covenant. Weapons are out of place at such a meeting. As before the spirits, such conduct is unpropitious. In point of virtue, it is contrary to right. As between man and man, it is not polite." The duke of Chʽi ordered the disturbers off, but Confucius withdrew, carrying the duke of Lu with him. The business proceeded, notwithstanding, and when the words of the alliance were being read on the part of Chʽi,—"So be it to Lu, if it contribute not 300 chariots of war to the help of Chʽi, when its army goes across its borders," a messenger from Confucius added,—"And so be it to us, if we obey your orders, unless you return to us the fields on the south of the Wên." At the conclusion of the ceremonies, the prince of Chʽi wanted to give a grand entertainment, but Confucius demonstrated that such a thing would be contrary to the established rules of propriety, his real object being to keep his sovereign out of danger. In this way the two parties separated, they of Chʽi filled with shame at being foiled and disgraced by "the man of ceremonies;" and the result was that the lands of Lu which had been appropriated by Chʽi were restored.[1565]

For two years more Confucius held the office of minister of crime. Some have supposed that he was further raised to the dignity of chief minister of the state,[1566] but that was not the case. One instance of the manner in which he executed his functions is worth recording. When any matter came before him, he took the opinion of different individuals upon it, and in giving judgment would say, "I decide according to the view of so and so." There was an approach to our jury system in the plan, Confucius's object being to enlist general sympathy, and carry the public judgment with him in his administration of justice. A father having brought some charge against his son, Confucius kept them both in prison for three months, without making any difference in favour of the father, and then wished to dismiss them both. The head of the Chi was dissatisfied, and said, "You are playing with me, sir minister of crime. Formerly you told me that in a state or a family filial duty was the first thing to be insisted on. What hinders you now from putting to death this unfilial son as an example to all the people?" Confucius with a sigh replied, "When superiors fail in their futy, and yet go to put their inferiors to death, it is not right. This father has not taught his son to be filial;—to listen to his charge would be to slay the guiltless. The manners of the age have been long in a sad condition; we cannot expect the people not to be transgressing the laws."[1567]

At this time two of his disciples, Tzǔ-lu and Tzǔ-yu, entered the employment of the Chi family, and lent their influence, the former especially, to forward the plans of their master. One great cause of disorder in the state was the fortified cities held by the three chiefs, in which they could defy the supreme authority, and were in turn defied themselves by their officers. Those cities were like the castles of the barons of England in the time of the Norman kings. Confucius had their destruction very much at heart, and partly by the influence of persuasion, and partly by the assisting counsels of Tzǔ-lu, he accomplished his object in regard to Pi,[1568] the chief city of the Chi, and Hau,[1569] the chief city of the Shu.

It does not appear that he succeeded in the same way in dismantling Chʽêng,[1570] the chief city of the Mêng;[1571] but his authority in the state greatly increased. "He strengthened the ducal house and weakened the private families. He exalted the sovereign, and depressed the ministers. A transforming government went abroad. Dishonesty and dissoluteness were ashamed and hid their heads. Loyalty and good faith became the characteristics of the men, and chastity and docility those of the women. Strangers came in crowds from other states."[1572] Confucius became the idol of the people, and flew in songs through their mouths.[1573]

But this sky of bright promise was soon overcast. As the fame of the reformations in Lu went abroad, the neighbouring princes began to be afraid. The duke of Chi said, "With Confucius at the head of its government, Lu will become supreme among the states, and Chi which is nearest to it will be the first swallowed up. Let us propitiate it by a surrender of territory." One of his ministers proposed that they should first try to separate between the sage and his sovereign, and to effect this, they hit upon the following scheme. Eighty beautiful girls, with musical and dancing accomplishments, and a hundred and twenty of the finest horses that could be found, were selected, and sent as present to duke Ting. They were put up at first outside the city, and Chi Huan having gone in disguise to see them, forgot the lessons of Confucius, and took the duke to look at the bait. They were both captivated. The women were received, and the sage was neglected. For three days the duke gave no audience to his ministers. "Master," said Tzǔ-lu to Confucius, "it is time for you to be going." But Confucius was very unwilling to leave. The spring was coming on, when the sacrifice to heaven would be offered, and he determined to wait and see whether the solemnization of that would bring the duke back to his right mind. No such result followed. The ceremony was hurried through, and portions of the offerings were not sent round to the various ministers, according to the established custom. Confucius regretfully took his departure, going away slowly and by easy stages.[1574] He would have welcomed a message of recall. But the duke continued in his abandonment, and the sage went forth to thirteen weary years of homeless wandering.

On leaving Lu, Confucius first bent his steps westward to the state of Wei, situate about where the present provinces of Jilin and Henan adjoin. He was now in his fifty-sixth year, and felt depressed and melancholy. As he went along, he gave expression to his feelings in verse:—

"Fain would I still look towards Lu,
But this Kuai hill cuts off my view.
With an axe, I'd hew the thickets through:—
Vain thought! ’gainst the hill I nought can do;"

and again.—

"Through the valley howls the blast,
Drizzling rain falls thick and fast.
Homeward goes the youthful bride,
O'er the wild, crowds by her side.
How is it, O azure Heaven,
From my home I thus am driven,
Through the land my way to trace,
With no certain dwelling-place?
Dark, dark, the minds of men!
Worth in vain comes to their ken.
Hastens on my term of years;
Old age, desolate, appears."[1575]

A number of his disciples accompanied him, and his sadness infected them. When they arrived at the borders of Wei, at a place called Yi, the warden sought an interview, and on coming out from the sage, he tried to comfort the disciples, saying, "My friends, why are you distressed at your master's loss of office? The world has been long without the principles of truth and right; heaven is going to use your master as a bell with its wooden tongue."[1576] Such was the thought of this friendly stranger. The bell did indeed sound, but few had ears to hear.

Confucius's fame, however, had gone before him, and he was in little danger of having to suffer from want. On arriving at the capital of Wei, he lodged at first with a worthy officer, named Yen Chʽou-yu.[1577] The reigning duke, known to use by the epithet Ling,[1578] was a worthless, dissipated man, but he could not neglect a visitor of such eminence, and soon assigned to Confucius a revenue of 60,000 measures of grain.[1579] Here he remained for ten months, and then for some reason left it to go to Chʽên.[1580] On the way he had to pass by Kʽuang,[1581] a place probably in the present department of Kaifeng in Henan, which had formerly suffered suffered from Yang-huo. It so happened that Confucius resembled Huo, and the attention of the people being called to him by the movements of his carriage-driver, they thought it was their old enemy, and made an attack upon him. His followers were alarmed, but he was calm, and tried to assure them by declaring his belief that he had a divine mission. He said to them, "After the death of king Wên, was not the cause of truth lodged here in me? If heaven had wished to let this cause of truth perish, that I, a future mortal, should not have got such a relation to that cause. While heaven does not let the cause of truth perish, what can the people of Kʽuang do to me?"[1582] Having escaped from the hands of his assailants, he does not seem to have carried out his purpose of going to Chʽên, but returned to Wei.

On the way, he passed a house where he had formerly lodged, and finding that the master was dead, and the funeral ceremonies going on, he went in to condole and weep. When he came out, he told Tzǔ-kung to take the outside horses from his carriage, and give them as a contribution to express of the occasion. "You never did such a thing," Tzǔ-kung remonstrated, "at the funeral of any of your disciples; is it not too great a gift on this occasion of the death of an old host?" "When I went in," replied Confucius, "my presence brought a burst of grief from the chief mourner, and I joined him with my tears. I dislike the though of my tears not being followed by anything. Do it, my child."[1583]

On reaching Wei, he lodged with Chü Po-yü, an officer of whom honourable mention is made in the Analects.[1584] But this time he did not remain long in the state. The duke was married to a lady of the house of Sung, known by the name of Nan-tzǔ, notorious for her intrigues and wickedness. She sought an interview with the sage, which he was obliged unwillingly to accord. [1585] No doubt he was innocent of thought or act of evil, but it gave great dissatisfaction to Tzǔ-lu that his master should have been in company with such a woman, and Confucius, to assure him, swore an oath, saying, "Wherein I have done improperly, may heaven reject me! May heaven reject me!"[1586] He could not well abide, however, about such a court. One day the duke rode out through the streets of his capital in the same carriage with Nan-tzǔ, and made Confucius follow them in another. Perhaps he intended to honour the philosopher, but the people saw the incongruity, and cried out, "Lust in the front; virtue behind!" Confucius was ashamed, and made the observation, "I have not seen one who loves virtue as he loves beauty."[1587] Wei was no place for him. He left it, and took his way towards Chʽên.

Chʽên, which formed part of the present province of Henan, lay south from Wei. After passing the small state of Tsʽao,[1588] he approached the borders of Sung, occupying the present prefecture of Kuei-tê, and had some intentions of entering it, when an incident occurred, which it is not easy to understand from the meagre style in which it is related, but which gave occasion to a remarkable saying. Confucius was practising ceremonies with his disciples, we are told, under the shade of a large tree. Huan Tʽui, an ill-minded officer of Sung, heard of it, and sent a band of men to pull down the tree, and kill the philosopher, if they could get hold of him. The disciples were much alarmed, but Confucius observed, "Heaven has produced the virtue that is in me;—what can Huan Tʽui do to me?"[1589] They all made their escape, but seem to have been driven westwards to the state of Chêng,[1590] on arriving at the gate conducting into which from the east, Confucius found himself separated from his followers. Tzǔ-kung had arrived before him, and was told by a native of Chêng that there was a man standing by the east gate, with a forehead like Yao, a neck like Kao-yao, his shoulders on a level with those of Tzǔ-chʽên, but wanting, below the waist, three inches of the height of Yü, and altogether having the disconsolate appearance of a stray dog." Tzǔ-kung knew it was the master, hastened to him, and repeated to his great amusement the description which the man had given. "The bodily appearance," said Confucius, "is but a small matter, but to say I was like a stray dog,—capital! capital!"[1591] The stay they made at Chêng was short, and by the end of BC 495, Confucius was in Chʽên.

All the next year he remained there, lodging with the warder of the city wall, an officer of worth, of the name of Chêng,[1592] and we have no accounts of him which deserve to be related here.[1593]

In BC 494, Chʽên was much disturbed by attacks from Wu,[1594] a large state, the capital of which was in the present department of Suzhou, and Confucius determined to retrace his steps to Wei. On the way he was laid hold of at a place called Pʽu,[1595] which was held by a rebellious officer against Wei, and before he could get away, he was obliged to engage that he would not proceed thither. Thither, notwithstanding, he continued his route, and when Tzǔ-kung asked him whether it was right to violate the oath he had taken, he replied, "It was a forced oath. The spirits do not hear such."[1596] The duke Ling received him with distinction, but paid no more attention to his lessons than before, and Confucius is said then to have uttered his complaint, "If there were any of the princes who would employ me, in the course of twelve months I should have done something considerable. In three years the government would be perfected."[1597]

A circumstance occurred to direct his attention to the state of Tsin,[1598] which occupied the southern part of the present Shanxi, and extended over the Yellow river into Henan. An invitation came to Confucius, like that which he had formerly received from Kung-shan Fu-jao. Pi Hsi, an officer of Tsin, who was holding the town Chung-mou against his chief, invited him to visit him, and Confucius was inclined to go. Tzǔ-lu was always the mentor on such occasions. He said to him, "Master, I have heard you say, that when a man in his own person is guilty of doing evil, a superior man will not associate with him. Pi Hsi is in rebellion; if you go to him, what shall be said?" Confucius replied, "Yes, I did use those words. But is it not said that if a thing be really hard, it may be ground without being made thin; and if it be really white, it may be steeped in a dark fluid without being made black? Am I a bitter gourd? Am I to be hung up out of the way of being eaten?"[1599]

These sentiments sound strangely from his lips. After all, he did not go to Pi Hsi; and having travelled as far as the Yellow river that he might see one of the principal ministers of Tsin, he heard of the violent death of two men of worth, and returned to Wei, lamenting the fate which prevented him from crossing the stream, and trying to solace himself with poetry as he had done on leaving Lu. Again did he communicate with the duke, but as ineffectually, and disgusted at being questioned by him about military tactics, he left and went back to Chʽên.

He resided in Chʽên all the next year, BC 491, without anything occurring there which is worthy of note.[1600] Events had transpired in Lu, however, which were to issue in his return to his native state. The duke Ting had deceased BC 494, and Chi Huan, the chief of the Chi family, died in this year. On this deathbed, he felt remorse for his conduct to Confucius, and charged his successor, known to us in the Analects as Chi Kʽang, to recall the sage; but the charge was not immediately fulfilled. Chi Kʽang, by the advice of one of his officers, sent to Chʽên for the disciple Yen Chʽiu instead. Confucius willingly sent him off, and would gladly have accompanied him. "Let me return!" he said, "Let me return!"[1601] But that was not to be for several years yet.

In BC 490, accompanied, as usual, by several of his disciples, he went from Chʽên to Tsʽai, a small dependency of the great fief of Chʽu, which occupied a large part of the present provinces of Hunan and Hubei. On the way, between Chʽên and Tsʽai, their provisions became exhausted, and they were cut off somehow from obtaining a fresh supply. The disciples were quite overcome with want, and Tzǔ-lu said to the master, "Has the superior man indeed to endure in this way?" Confucius answered him, "The superior man may indeed have to endure want; but the mean man, when he is in want, gives way to unbridled license."[1602] According to the Narratives of the School, the distress continued seven days, during which time Confucius retained his equanimity, and was even cheerful, playing on his lute and singing.[1603] He retained, however, a strong impression of the perils of the season, and we find him afterwards recurring to it, and lamenting that of the friends that were with him in Chʽên and Tsʽai, there were none remaining to enter his door.[1604]

Escaped from this strait, he remained in Tsʽai over BC 489, and in the following year we find him in Shê, according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, he returned to Tsʽai, and having to cross a river, he sent Tzǔ-lu to inquire for the ford of two men who were at work in a neighbouring field. They were recluses,—men who had withdrawn from public life in disgust at the waywardness of the times. One of them was called Chʽêng-tsü, and instead of giving Tzǔ-lu the information he wanted, he asked him, "Who is it that holds the reins in the carriage there?" "It is Kʽung Chʽiu." "Kʽung Chʽiu of Lu?" "Yes," was the reply, and then the man rejoined, "He knows the ford."

Tzǔ-lu applied to the other, who was called Chieh-ni, but got for answer the question, "Who are you, Sir?" He replied, "I am Chung Yu." "Chung Yu, who is the disciple of Kʽung Chʽiu of Lu?" "Yes," again replied Tzǔ-lu, and Chieh-ni said to him, "Disorder, like a swelling flood, spreads over the whole kingdom, and who is he that will chage it for you? Than follow one who merely withdraws from this one and that one, had you not better follow those who withdraw from the world altogether?" With this he fell to covering up the seed, and gave no more heed to the stranger. Tzǔ-lu went back and reported what they had said, when Confucius vindicated his own course, saying, "It is impossible to associate with birds and beasts as if they were the same with us. If I associate not with these people,—with mankind,—with whom shall I associate? If right principles prevailed through the kingdom, there would be no need for me to change its state."[1605]

About the same time he had an encounter with another recluse, who was known as "The madman of Chʽu." He passed by the carriage of Confucius, singing out, "O phoenix, O phoenix, how is your virtue degenerated! As to the past, reproof is useless, but the future may be provided against. Give up, give up your vain pursuit." Confucius alighted and wished to enter into conversation with him, but the man hastened away. [1606]

But now the attention of the ruler Chʽu—king, as he styled himself—was directed to the illustrious stranger who was in his dominions, and he met Confucius and conducted him to his capital, which was in the present district of Yicheng, in the department of Xiangyang,[1607] in Hubei. After a time, he proposed endowing the philosopher with a considerable territory, but was dissuaded by his prime minister, who said to him, "Has your majesty any officer who could discharge the duties of an ambassador like Tzǔ-kung? or anyone so qualified for a premier as Yen Hui? or anyone to compare as a general with Tzǔ-lu? The kings Wên and Wu, from their hereditary dominions of a hundred li, rose to the sovereignty of the kingdom. If Kʽung Chʽiu, with such disciples to be his ministers, get the possession of any territory, it will not be to the prosperity of Chʽu?[1608] On this remonstrance the king gave up his purpose; and, when he died in the same year, Confucius left the state, and went back again to Wei.

The duke Ling had died four years before, soon after Confucius had last parted from him, and the reigning duke, known to us by the title of Chʽu,[1609] was his grandson, and was holding the principality against his own father. The relations between them were rather complicated. The father had been driven out in consequence of an attempt which he had instigated on the life of his step-mother, the notorious Nan-tzǔ, and the succession was given to his son. Subsequently, the father wanted to reclaim what he deemed his right, and an unseemly struggle ensued. The duke Chʽu was conscious how much his cause would be strengthened by the support of Confucius, and hence when he got to Wei, Tzǔ-lu could say to him, "The prince of Wei has been waiting for you, in order with you to administer the government;—what will you consider the first thing to be done?"[1610] The opinion of the philosopher, however, was against the propriety of the duke's course,[1611] and he declined taking office with him, though he remained in Wei for between five and six years. During all that time there is a blank in his history. In the very year of his return, according to the Annals of the Empire, his most beloved disciple, Yen Hui, died, on which occasion he exclaimed, "Alas! Heaven is destroying me! Heaven is destroying me!"[1612] The death of his wife is assigned to BC 484, but nothing else is related which we can connect with this long period.

His return to Lu was brought about by the disciple Jan Yu, who, we have seen, went into the service of Chi Kʽang, in BC 491. In the year BC 483, Yu had the conduct of some military operations against Chʽi, and being successful, Chi Kʽang asked him how he had obtained his military skill;—was it from nature, or by learning? He replied that he had learned it from Confucius, and entered into a flowing eulogy of the philosopher. The chief declared that he would bring Confucius home again to Lu. "If you do so," said the disciple, "see that you do not let mean men come between you and him." On this Kʽang sent three officers with appropriate presents to Wei, to invite the wanderer home, and he returned with them accordingly.[1613]

This event took place in the eleventh year of the duke Ai,[1614] who succeeded to Ting, and according to Kʽung Fu, Confucius's descendant, the invitation proceeded from him.[1615] We may suppose that while Chi Kʽang was the move and director of the proceeding, it was with the authority and approval of the duke. It is represented in the chronicle of Tso Chʽiu-ming as having occurred at a very opportune time. The philosopher had been consulted a little before by Kʽung Wên,[1616] an officer of Wei, about how he should conduct a feud with another officer, and disgusted at being referred to on such a subject, had ordered his carriage and prepared to leave the state, exclaiming, "The bird choose its tree. The tree does not choose the bird." Kʽung Wên endeavoured to excuse himself, and to prevail on Confucius to remain in Wei, and just at this juncture the messengers from Lu arrived.[1617]

Confucius was now in his sixty-ninth year. The world had not dealt kindly with him. In every state which he had visited he had met with disappointment and sorrow. Only five more years remained to him, nor were they of a brighter character than the past. He had, indeed, attained to that state, he tells us, in which "he could not follow what his heart desired without transgressing what was right,"[1618] but other people were not more inclined than they had been to abide by his counsels. The duke Ai and Chi Kʽang often conversed with him, but he no longer had weight in the guidance of state affairs, and wisely addressed himself to the completion of his literary labours. He wrote a preface, according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, to the Shu-ching; carefully digested the rites and ceremonies determined by the wisdom of the more ancient sages and kings; collected and arranged the ancient poetry; and undertook the reform of music.[1619] He has told us himself, "I returned from Wei to Lu, and then the music was reformed, and the pieces in the Songs of the Kingdom and Praise Songs found all their proper places."[1620] To the Yi-ching he devoted much study, and Ssǔ-ma Chʽien says that the leather thongs by which the tablets of his copy were bound together were thrice worn out. "If some years were added to my life," he said, "I would give fifty to the study of the Yi, and then I might come to be without great faults."[1621] During this time also, we may suppose that he supplied Tsêng Shên with the materials of the Classic of Filial Piety. The same year that he returned, Chi Kʽang sent Jan Yu to ask his opinion about an additional impost which he wished to lay upon the people, but Confucius refused to give any reply, telling the disciple privately his disapproval of the proposed measure. It was carried out, however, in the following year, by the agency of Jan, on which occasion, I suppose, it was that Confucius said to the other disciples, "He is no disciple of mine; my little children, beat the drum and assail him."[1622] The year BC 483 was marked by the death of his son Li, which he seems to have borne with more equanimity than he did that of his disciple Yen Hui, which some writers assign to the following year, though I have already mentioned it under the year BC 489.

In the spring of BC 481, a servant of Chi Kʽang caught a chʽi-lin on a hunting excursion of the duke in the present district of Jiaxiang.[1623] No person could tell what strange animal it was, and Confucius was called to look at it. He at once knew it to be a lin, and the legend-writers say that it bore on one of its horns the piece of ribbon, which his mother had attached to the one that appeared to her before his birth. According to the chronicle of Kung-yang, he was profoundly affected. He cried out, "For whom have you come? For whom have you come?" His tears flowed freely, and he added, "The course of my doctrines is run."[1624]

Notwithstanding the appearance of the lin, the life of Confucius was still protracted for two years longer, though he took occasion to terminate with that event his history of the Chʽun Chʽiu. This work, according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, was altogether the production of this year, but we need not suppose that it was so. In it, from the standpoint of Lu, he briefly indicates the principal events occurring throughout the country, every term being expressive, it is said, of the true character of the actors and events described. Confucius said himself, "It is the Spring and Autumn which will make men know me, and it is the Spring and Autumn will make men condemn me."[1625] Mencius makes the composition of it to have been an achievement as great as Yü's regulation of the waters of the deluge:—"Confucius completed the Spring and Autumn, and rebellious ministers and villainous sons were struck with terror."[1626]

Towards the end of this year, word came to Lu that the duke of Chʽi had been murdered by one of his officers. Confucius was moved with indignation. Such an outrage, he felt, called for his solemn interference. He bathed, went to court, and represented the matter to the duke, saying, "Chʽên Hêng has slain his sovereign, I beg that you will undertake to punish him." The duke pleaded his incapacity, urging that Lu was weak compared with Chʽi, but Confucius replied, "One half the people of Chʽi are not consenting to the deed. If you add to the people of Lu one half the people of Chʽi, you are sure to overcome." But he could not infuse his spirit into the duke, who told him to go and lay the matter before the chiefs of the three families. Sorely against his sense of propriety, he did so, but they would not act,m and he withdrew with the remark, "Following in the rear of the great officers, I did not dare not to represent such a matter."[1627]

In the year BC 479, Confucius had to mourn the death of another of his disciples, one of those who had been longest with him,—the well-known Tzǔ-lu. He stands out a sort of Peter in the Confucian school, a man of impulse, prompt to speak and prompt to act. He gets many a check from the master, but there is evidently a strong sympathy between them. Tzǔ-lu uses a freedom with him on which none of the other disciples dares to venture, and there is not one among them all, for whom, if I may speak from my own feeling, the foreign student comes to form such a liking. A pleasant picture is presented to us in one passage of the Analects. It is said, "The disciple Min was standing by his side, looking bland and precise; Tzǔ-lu (named Yu), looking bold and soldierly; Jan Yu and Tzǔ-kung, with a free and straightforward manner. The master was pleased, but he observed, 'Yu there!—he will not die a natural death.'"[1628]

This prediction was verified. When Confucius returned to Lu from Wei, he left Tzǔ-lu Tzǔ-kao[1629] engaged there in official service. Troubles arose. News came to Lu, BC 479, that a revolution was in progress in Wei, and when Confucius heard it, he said, "Chʽai will come here, but Yu will die."[1630] So it turned out. When Tzǔ-kao saw that matters were desperate he made his escape, but Tzǔ-lu would not forsake the chief who had treated him well. He threw himself into the melee, and was slain. Confucius wept sore for him, but his own death was not far off. It took place on the eleventh day of the fourth month in the same year, BC 479. [1631]

Early one morning, we are told, he got up, and with his hands behind his back, dragging his staff, he moved about by his door, crooning over,—

"The great mountain must crumble;
The strong beam must break;
And the wise man wither away like a plan."

After a little, he entered the house and sat down opposite the door. Tzǔ-kung had heard his words, and said to himself, "If the great mountain crumble, to what shall I look up? If the strong beam break, and the wise man wither away, on whom shall I lean? The master, I fear, is going to be ill." With this he hastened into the house. Confucius said to him, "Tzʽǔ, what makes you so late? According to the statues of Hsia, the corpse was dressed and coffined at the top of the eastern steps, treating the dead as if he were still the host. Under the Yin, the ceremony was performed between the two pillars, as if the dead were both host and guest. The rule of Chou is to perform it at the top of the western steps, treating the dead as if he were a guest. I am man of Yin, and last night I dreamt that I was sitting with offerings before me between the two pillars. No intelligent monarch arises; there is not one in the kingdom that will make me his master. My time has come to die." So it was. He went to his couch, and after seven days expired.[1632]

Such is the account which we have of the last hours of the great philosopher of China. His end was not unimpressive, but it was melancholy. He sank behind a cloud. Disappointed hopes made his soul bitter. The great ones of the kingdom had not received his teachings. No wife nor child was by to do the kindly offices of affection for him. Nor were the expectations of another life present with him as he passed through the dark valley. He uttered no prayer, and he betrayed no apprehensions. Deep-treasured in his own heart may have been the thought that he had endeavoured to serve his generation by the will of God, but he gave no sign. "The mountain falling came to nought, and the rock was removed out of his place. So death prevailed against him and he passed; his countenance was changed, and he was sent away."

I flatter myself that the preceding paragraphs contain a more correct narrative of the principal incidents in the life of Confucius than has yet been given in any European language. They might easily have been expanded into a volume, but I did not wish to exhaust the subject, but only to furnish a sketch, which, while it might satisfy the general reader, would be of special assistance to the careful student of the classical books. I had taken many notes of the manifest errors in regard to chronology and other matters in Narratives of the School, and the chapter of Ssǔ-ma Chʽien on the Kʽung family, when the digest of Chiang Yung, to which I have made frequent reference, attracted my attention. Conclusions to which I had come were confirmed, and a clue was furnished to difficulties which I was seeking to disentangle. I take the opportunity to acknowledge here my obligations to it. With a few notices of Confucius's habits and manners, I shall conclude this section.

Very little can be gathered from reliable sources on the personal appearance of the sage. The height of his father is stated, as I have noted, to have been ten feet, and though Confucius came short of this by four inches, he was often called "the tall man." It is allowed that the ancient foot or cubit was shorter than the modern, but it must be reduced more than any scholar I have consulted has yet done, to bring this statement within the range of credibility. The legends assign to his figure "nine-and-forty remarkable peculiarities,"[1633] a tenth part of which would have made him more a monster than a man. Dr. Morrison says that the images of him, which he had seen in the northern parts of China, represent him as of a dark, swarthy colour.[1634] It is not so with those common in the south. He was, no doubt, in size and complexion much the same as many of his descendants in the present day. Dr. Edkins and myself enjoyed the services of two of those descendants, who acted as "wheelers" in the wheelbarrows which conveyed us from Chʽü-fau to a town on the Grand Canal more than 250 miles off. They were strong, capable men, both physically and mentally superior to their companions.

But if his disciples had nothing to chronicle of his personal appearance, they have gone very minutely into an account of many of his habits. The tenth book of the Analects is all occupied with his deportment, his eating, and his dress. In public, whether in the village, the temple, or the court, he was the man of rule and ceremony, but "at home he was not formal." Yet if not formal, he was particular. In bed even he did not forget himself;—"he did not lie like a corpse," and "he did not speak." "He required his sleeping dress to be half as long again as his body." "If he happened to be sick, and the prince came to visit him, he had his face set to the east, made his court robes be put over him, and drew his girdle across them."

He was nice in his diet,—"not disliking to have his rice dressed fine, nor to have his minced meat cut small." "Anything at all gone he would not touch." "He must have his meat cut properly, and to every king its proper sauce; but he was not a great eater." "It was only in drink he laid down no limit to himself, but he did not allow himself to be confused by it." "When the villagers were drinking together, on those who carried staffs going out, he went out immediately after." There must always be ginger at the table, and "when eating, he did not converse." "Although his good might be coarse rice and poor soup, he would offer a little of it in sacrifice, with a grave, respectful air."

"On occasion of a sudden clap of thunder, or a violent wind, he would change countenance. He would do the same, and rise up moreover, when he found himself a guest at a loaded board." "At the sight of a person in mourning, he would also change countenance, and if he happened to be in his carriage, he would bend forward with a respectful salutation." "His general way in his carriage was not to turn his head around, nor talk hastily, nor point with his hands." He was charitable. "When any of his friends died, if there were no relations who could be depended on for the necessary offices, he would say, 'I will bury him.'"

The disciples were so careful to record these and other characteristics of their master, it is said, because every act, of movement or of rest, was closely associated with the great principles which it was his object to inculcate. The detail of so many small matters, however, hardly impresses a foreigner so favourably. There rather seems to be a want of freedom about the philosopher.

Section II

His Influence and Opinions

Confucius died, we have seen, complaining that of all the princes of the kingdom there was not one who would adopt his principles and obey his lessons. He had hardly passed from the stage of life, when his merit began to be acknowledged. When the duke Ai heard of his death, he pronounced his eulogy in the words, "Heaven has not left to me the aged man. There is none now to assist me on the throne. Woe is me! Alas! O venerable Ni!"[1635] Tzǔ-kung complained of the inconsistency of this lamentation from one who could not use the master when he was alive, but the prince was probably sincere in his grief. He caused a temple to be erected, and ordered that sacrifice should be offered to the sage, at the four seasons of the year.[1636]

The sovereigns of the tottering dynasty of Chou had not the intelligence, nor were they in a position, to do honour to the departed philosopher, but the facts detailed in the first chapter of these prolegomena, in connection with the attempt of the founder of the Chʽin dynasty to destroy the literary monuments of antiquity, show how the authority of COnfucius had come by that time to prevail through the nation. The founder of the Han dynasty, in passing through Lu, BC 195, visited his toub and offered the three victims in sacrifice to him. Other sovereigns since then have often made pilgrimages to the spot. The most famous temple in the empire now rises near the place of the grave. The second and greatest of the rulers of the present dynasty, in the twenty-third year of his reign, the Kʽang-hsi period, there set the example of kneeling thrice, and each time laying his forehead thrice in the dust, before the image of the sage.

In the year of our Lord 1, began the practice of conferring honorary designations on Confucius by imperial authority. The emperor Pʽing[1637] then styled him—"The duke Ni, all-complete and illustrious."[1638] This was changed, in AD 492, to—"The venerable Ni, the accomplished sage."[1639] Other titles have supplanted this. Shun-chih,[1640] the first of the Man-chou dynasty, adopted, in his second year, AD 1645, the style,—"Kʽung, the ancient teacher, accomplished and illustrious, all-complete, the perfect sage;"[1641] but twelve years later, a shorter title was introduced,—"Kʽung, the ancient teacher, the perfect sage."[1642] Since that year no further alteration has been made.

At first, the worship of Confucius was confined to the country of Lu, but in AD 57 it was enacted that sacrifices should be offered to him in the imperial college, and in all the colleges of the principal territorial divisions throughout the empire. In those sacrifices he was for some centuries associated with the duke of Chou, the legislator to whom Confucius made frequent reference, but in AD 609 separate temples were assigned to them, and in 628 our sage displaced the older worthy altogether. About the same time began the custom, which continues to the present day, of erecting temples to him,—separate structures, in the connection with all the colleges, or examination-halls, of the country.

The sage is not alone in hose temples. In a hall behind the principal one occupied by himself are the tablets—in some cases, the images—of several of his ancestors, and other worthies; while associated with himself are his principal disciples, and many who in subsequent times have signalized themselves as expounders and exemplifiers of his doctrines. On the first day of every month, offerings of fruits and vegetables are set forth, and on the fifteenth there is a solemn burning of incense. But twice a year, in the middle months of spring and autumn, when the first tingday[1643] of the month comes round, the worship of Confucius is performed with peculiar solemnity. At the imperial college the emperor himself is required to attend in state, and is in fact the principal performer. After all the preliminary arrangements have been made, and the emperor has twice knelt and six times bowed his head to the earth, the presence of COnfucius's spirit is invoked in the words, "Great art thou, O perfect sage! Thy virtue is full; thy doctrine is complete. Among mortal men there has not been thine equal. All kings honour thee. Thy statutes and laws have come gloriously down. Thou art the pattern in this imperial school. Reverently have the sacrificial vessels been set out. Full of awe, we sound our drums and bells."[1644]

The spirit is supposed now to be present, and the service proceeds through various offerings, when the first of which has been set forth, an officer reads the following,[1645] which is the prayer on the occasion:—"On this… month of this… year, I, A.B., the emperor, offer a sacrifice to the philosopher Kʽung, the ancient teacher, the perfect sage, and say,—O teacher, in virtue equal to Heaven and earth, whose doctrines embrace the past time and the present, thou didst digest and transmit the six classics, and didst hand down lessons for all generations! Now in this second month of spring (or autumn), in reverent observance of the old statutes, with victims, silks, spirits, and fruits, I carefully offer sacrifice to thee. With thee are associated the philosopher Yen, continuator of thee; the philosopher Tsêng, exhibitor of thy fundamental principles; the philosopher Tzǔ-ssǔ, transmitter of thee; and the philosopher Mêng, second to thee. May'st thou enjoy the offerings!"

I need not go on to enlarge on the homage which the emperors of China render to Confucius. It could not be more complete. He was unreasonably neglected when alive. He is now unreasonably venerated when dead.

The rulers of China are not singular in this matter, but in entire sympathy with the mass of their people. It is the distinction of this empire that education has been highly prized in it from the earliest times. It was so before the era of Confucius, and we may be sure that the system met with his approbation. One of his remarkable sayings was,—"To lead an uninstructed people to war is to throw them away."[1646] When he pronounced this judgment, he was not thinking of military training, but of education in the duties of life and citizenship. A people so taught, he thought, would be morally fitted to fight for their government. Mencius, when lecturing to the rule of Tʽêng on the proper way of governing a kingdom, told him that he must provide the means of education for all, the poor as well as the rich. "Establish," said he, "hsing, hsü, hsio, and hsiao,—all those educational institutions,—for the instruction of the people."[1647]

At the present day, education is widely diffused throughout China. In few other countries is the schoolmaster more abroad, and in all schools it is Confucius who is taught. The plan of competitive examinations, and the selection for civil offices only from those who have been successful candidates,—good so far as the competition is concerned, but injurious from the restricted range of subjects with which an acquaintance is required,—have obtained for more than twelve centuries. The classical works are the text books. It is from them almost exclusively that the themes proposed to determine the knowledge and ability of the students are chosen. The whole of the magistracy of China is thus versed in all that is recorded of the sage, and in the ancient literature which he preserved. His thoughts are familiar to every man in authority, and his character is more or less reproduced in him.

The official civilians of China, numerous as they are, are but a fraction of its students, and the students, or those who make literature a profession, are again but a fraction of those who attend school for a shorter or longer period. Yet so far as the studies have gone, they have been occupied with the Confucian writings. In the schoolrooms there is a tablet or inscription on the wall, sacred to the sage, and every pupil is required, on coming to school on the mourning of the first and fifteenth of every month, to bow before it, the first thing, as an act of reverence.[1648] Thus all in China who receive the slightest tincture of learning do so at the fountain of Confucius. They learn of him and do homage to him at once. I have repeatedly quoted the statement that during his lifetime he had three thousand disciples. Hundreds of millions are his disciples now. It is hardly necessary to make any allowance in this statement for the followers of Taoism and Buddhism, for, as Sir John Davis has observed, "whatever the other opinions or faith or a Chinese may be, he takes good care to treat Confucius with respect."[1649] For two thousand years he has reigned supreme, the undisputed teacher of this most populous land.

This position and influence of Confucius are to be ascribed, I conceive, chiefly to two causes:—his being the preserver, namely of the monuments of antiquity, and the exemplifier and expounder of the maxims of the golder age of China; and the devotion to him of his immediate disciples and their early followers. The national and the personal are thus blended in him, each in its highest degree of excellence. He was a Chinese of the Chinese; he is also represented as, and all now believe him to have been, the beau ideal of humanity in its best and noblest estate.

It may be well to bring forward here Confucius's own estimate of himself and of his doctrines. It was serve to illustrate the statements just made. The following are some of his sayings:—"The sage and the man of perfect virtue;—how dare I rank myself with them? It may simply be said of me, that I strive to become such without satiety, and teach others without weariness." "In letters I am perhaps equal to other men; but the character of the superior man, carrying out in his conduct what he professes, is what I have not yet attained to." "The leaving virtue without proper cultivation; the not thoroughly discussing what is learned; not being able to move towards righteousness of which a knowledge is grained; and not being able to change what is not good;—these are the things which occasion me solicitude." "I am not one who was born in the possession of knowledge; I am one who is fond of antiquity and earnest in seeking it there." "A transmitter and not a maker, believing in and loving the ancients, I venture to compare myself with our old Pʽêng."[1650]

Confucius cannot be thought to speak of himself these declarations more highly than the ought to do. Rather we may recognise in them the expressions of a genuine humility. He was conscious that personally he came short in many things, but he toiled after the character, which he saw, or facies that he saw, in the ancient sages whom he acknowledged; and the lessons of government and morals which he laboured to diffuse were those which had already been inculcated and exhibited by them. Emphatically he was "a transmitter and not a maker." It is not to be understood that he was not fully satisfied of the truth of the principles which he had learned. He held them with the full approval and consent of his own understanding. He believed that if they were acted on, they would remedy the evils of this time. There was nothing to prevent rules like Yao and Shun and the great Yü from again arising, and a condition of happy tranquillity being realised throughout the kingdom under their sway.

If in anything he thought himself "superior and alone," having attributes which others could not claim, it was in his possessing a divine commission as the conservator of ancient truth and rules. He does not speak very definitely on this point. It is noted that "the appointments of heaven was one of the subjects on which he rarely touched."[1651] His most remarkable utterance was that which I have already given in the sketch of his life:—"When he was put in fear in Kʽuang, he said, 'After the death of King Wên, was not the cause of truth lodged here in me? If heaven had wished to let his cause of truth perish, then I, a future mortal, should not have got such a relation to that cause. While heaven does not let the cause of truth perish, what can the people of Kʽuang do to me?'"[1652] Confucius, then, did feel that he was in the world for a special purpose. But it was not to announce any new truths, or to initiate any new economy. It was to prevent what had previously been known from being lost. He followed in the wake of Yao and Shun, of Tʽang, and king Wên. Distant from the last by a long interval of time, he would have said that he had learned the principles on which they all happily governed the country, and in their name he would lift up a standard against the prevailing lawlessness of his age.

The language employed with reference to Confucius by his disciples and their early followers presents a striking contrast with his own. I have already, in writing of the scope and value of The Doctrine of the Mean, called attention to the extravagant eulogies of his grandson Tzǔ-ssǔ. He only followed the example which had been set by those among whom the philosopher went in and out. We have the language of Yen Yüan, his favourite, which is comparatively moderate, and simply expresses the genuine admiration of a devoted pupil.[1653] Tzǔ-kung on several occasions spoke in a different style. Having heard that one of the chiefs of Lu had said that he himself—Tzǔ-kung—was superior to Confucius, he observed, "Let me use the comparison of a house and its encompassing wall. My wall only reaches to the shoulders. One may peep over it, and see whatever is valuable in the apartments. The wall of my master is several fathoms high. If one do not find the door and enter by it, he cannot see the rich ancestral temple with its beauties, nor all the officers in their rich array. But I may assume that they are few who find the door. The remark of the chief was only what might have been expected."[1654]

Another time, the same individual having spoken revilingly of COnfucius, Tzǔ-kung said, "It is of no one doing so. Chung-ni cannot be reviled. The talents and virtue of other men are hillocks and mounds which may be stepped over. Chung-ni is the sun or moon, which it is not possible to step over. Although a man may wish to cut himself off from the sage, what harm can he do to the sun and moon? He only shows that he does not know his own capacity."[1655]

In conversation with a fellow-disciple, Tzǔ-king took a still higher flight. Being charged by Tzǔ-chʽin with being too modest, for that Confucius was not really superior to him, he replied, "For one word a man is often deemed to be wise, and for one word he is often deemed to be foolish. We ought to be careful indeed in what we say. Our master cannot be attained to, just in the same way as the heavens cannot be gone up to by the steps of a stair. Were our master in the position of the prince of a state, or the chief of a family, we should find verified the description which has been given of a sage's rule:—He would plant the people, and forthwith they would be established; he would lead them on, and forthwith they would follow him; he would make them happy, and forthwith multitudes would resort to his dominions; he would stimulate them, and forthwith they would be harmonious. While he lived, he would be glorious. When he died, he would be bitterly lamented. How is it possible for him to be attained to?"[1656]

From these representations of Tzǔ-kung, it was not a difficult step for Tzǔ-ssǔ to take in exalting Confucius not only to the level of the ancient sages, but as "the equal of heaven." And Mencius took up the theme. Being questioned by Kung-sun Chʽau, one of his disciples, about two acknowledged sages, Po-yi and Yi Yin, whether they were to be placed in the same rank with Confucius, he replied, "No. Since there were living men until now, there never was another Confucius;" and then he proceeded to fortify his opinion by the concurring testimony of Tsai Wo, Tzǔ-kung, and Yu Jo, who all had wisdom, he thought, sufficient to know their master. Tsai Wo's opinion was, "According to my view of our master, he is far superior to Yao and Shun." Tzǔ-kung said, "By viewing the ceremonial ordinances of a prince, we know the character of his government. By hearing his music, we know the character of his virtue. From the distance of a hundred ages after, I can arrange, according to their merits, the kings of those hundred ages;—not one of them can escape me. From the birth of mankind till now, there has never been another like our master." Yu Jo said, "Is it only among men that it is so? There is the chʽi-lin among quadrupeds; the fung-huang among birds; the Tʽai mountain among mounds and anthills; and rivers and seas among rain-pools. Though different in degree, they are the same in kind. SO the sages among mankind are also the same in kind. But they stand out from their fellows, and rise above the level; and from the birth of mankind till now, there never has been one so complete as Confucius."[1657] I will not indulge in farther illustration. The judgement of the sage's disciples, of Tzǔ-ssǔ, and of Mencius, has been unchallenged by the mass of the scholars of China. Doubtless it pleases them to bow down at the shrine of the sage, for their profession of literature is thereby glorified. A reflection of the honour done to him falls upon themselves. And the powers that be, and the multitudes of the people, fall in with the judgment. COnfucius is thus, in the empire of China, the one man by whom all possible personal excellence was exemplified, and by whom all possible lessons of social virtue and political wisdom are taught.

The reader will be prepared by the preceding account not to expect to find any light thrown by Confucius on the great problems of the human condition and destiny. He did not speculate on the creation of things or the end of them. He was not troubled to account for the origin of man, nor did he seek to know about his hereafter. He meddled neither with physics nor metaphysics.[1658] The testimony of the Analects about the subjects of his teaching is the following:—"His frequent themes of discourse were the Book of Poetry, the Book of History, and the maintenance of the rules of propriety." "He taught letters, ethics, denotion of soul, and truthfulness." "Extraordinary things; feats of strength; states of disorder; and spiritual beings, he did not like to talk about."[1659]

Confucius is not to be blamed for his silence on the subjects here indicated. His ignorance of them was to a great extent his misfortune. He had not learned them. No report of them had come to him by the ear; no vision of them by the eye. And to his practical mind the toiling of thought amid uncertainties seemed worse than useless.

The question has, indeed, been raised, whether he did not make changes in the ancient creed of China,[1660] but I cannot believe that he did so consciously and designedly. Had his idiosyncrasy been different, we might have had expositions of the ancient views on some points, the effect of which they are not left, and it may be doubted so far, whether COnfucius was not unfaithful to his guides. But that he suppressed or added, in order to bring in articles of belief originating from himself, is a thing not to be charged against him.

I will mention two important subjects in regard to which there is a conviction in my mind that he came short of the faith of the older sages. The first is the doctrine of God. This name is common in the Shih-ching and the Shu-ching. Ti or Shang-ti appears there as a personal being, ruling in heaven and on earth, the author of man's moral nature, the governor among the nations, by whom kings reign and princes degree justice, the rewarder of the good, and the punisher of the bad. Confucius preferred to speak of heaven. Instances have already been given of this. Two others may be cited:—"He who offends against the heaven has none to whom he can pray?"[1661] "Alas!" said he, "there is no one that knows me." Tzǔ-kung said, "What do you mean by thus saying that no one knows you?" He replied, "I do not murmur against heaven. I do not grumble against men. My studies lie low, and my penetration rises high. But there is heaven;—that knows me!"[1662] Not once throughout the Analects does he use the personal name. I would say that he was unreligious rather than irreligious; yet by the coldness of his temperament and intellect in his matter, his influence is unfavourable to the development of ardent religious feeling among the Chinese people generally; and he prepared the way for the speculations of the literati of medieval and modern times,k which have exposed them to the charge of atheism.

Secondly, along with the worship of God there existed in China, from the earliest historical times, the worship of other spiritual beings,—especially, and to every individual, the worship of departed ancestors. Confucius recognised this as an institution to be devoutly observed. "He sacrificed to the dead as if they were present; he sacrificed to the spirits as if the spirits were present. He said, 'I consider my not being present at the sacrifice as if I did not sacrifice.'"[1663] The custom must have originated from a belief in the continued existence of the dead. We cannot suppose that they who instituted it thought that with the cessation of this life on earth there was a cessation also of all conscious being. But Confucius never spoke explicitly on this subject. He tried to evade it. "Chi Lu asked about serving the spirits of the dead, and the master said, 'While you are not able to serve men, how can you serve their spirits?' The disciple added, 'I venture to ask about death,' and he was answered, 'While you do not known life, how can you know about death.'"[1664] Still more striking is a conversation with another disciple, recoded in the Narratives of the School. Tzǔ-kung asked him, saying, "Do the dead have knowledge (of our services, that is), or are they without knowledge?" The master replied, "If I were to say that the dead have such knowledge, I am afraid that filial sons and dutiful grandsons would injure their substance in paying the last offices to the departed; and if I were to say that the dead have not such knowledge, I am afraid lest unfilial sons should leave their parents unburied. You need not wish, Tzʽǔ, to know whether the dead have knowledge or not. There is no present urgency about the point. Hereafter you will know it yourself."[1665] Surely this was not the teaching proper to a sage. He said on one occasion that he had no concealments from his disciples.[1666] Why did he not candidly tell his real thoughts on so interesting a subject? I incline to think that he doubted more than he believed. If the case were not so, it would be difficult to account for the answer which he returned to a question as to what constituted wisdom:—"To give one's self earnestly," said he, "to the duties due to men, and, while respecting spiritual beings, to keep aloof from them, may be called wisdom."[1667] At any rate, as by his frequent references to heaven, instead of following the phraseology of the older sages, he gave occasion to many of his professed followers to identify God with a principle of reason and the course of nature; so, in the point now in hand, he had led them to deny, like the Sadducees of old, the existence of any spirit at all, and to tell us that their sacrifices to the dead are but an outward form, the mode of expression which the principle of filial piety requires them to adopt when its objects have departed this life.

It will not be supposed that I wish to advocate or to defend the practice of sacrificing to the dead. My object has been to point out how Confucius recognised it, without acknowledging the faith from which it must have originated, and how he enforced it as a matter of form or ceremony. It thus connects itself with the most serious charge that be brought against him,—the charge of insincerity. Among the four things which it is said he taught, "truthfulness" is specified,[1668] and many sayings might be quoted from him, in which "sincerity" is celebrated as highly and demanded as stringently as ever it has been by any Christian moralist; yet he was not altogether the truthful and true man to whom we accord our highest approbation. There was the case of Mêng Chih-fan, who boldly brought up the rear of the defeated troops of Lu, and attributed this occupying the place of honour to the backwardness of his horse. The action was gallant, but the apology for it was weak and unnecessary. And yet Confucius saw nothing in the whole but matter for praise.[1669] He could excuse himself from seeing an unwelcome visitor on the ground that he was sick, when there was nothing the matter with him.[1670] These were small matters, but what shall we say to the incident which I have given in the sketch of his life,—his deliberately breaking the oath which he had sworn, simply on the ground that it had been forced from him?[1671] I should be glad if I could find evidence on which to deny the truth of that occurrence. But it rests on the same authority as most other statements about him, and it is accepted as a fact by the people of scholars of China. It must have had, and it must still have, a very injurious influence upon them. Foreigners charge a habit of deceitfulness upon the nation and its government;—on the justice or injustice of this charge I say nothing. For every word of falsehood and every act of insincerity, the guilty party must bear his own burden, but we cannot but regret the example of Confucius in this particular. It is with the Chinese and their sage, as it was with the Jews of old and their teachers. He that leads them has caused them to err, and destroyed the way of their paths.[1672]

But was not insincerity a natural result of the un-religion of Confucius? There are certain virtues which demand a true piety in order to their flourishing in the heart of man. Natural affection, the feeling of loyalty, and enlightened policy, may do much to build up and preserve a family and a state, but it requires more to maintain the love of truth, and make a lie, spoken or acted, to be shrunk from with shame. It requires in fact the living recognition of a God of truth, and all the sanctions of revealed religion. Unfortunately the Chinese have not had these, and the example of him to whom they bow down as the best and wisest of men, does not set them against dissimulation.

I go on to a brief discussion of Confucius's views on government, or what we may call his principles of political science. It could not be in his long intercourse with his disciples but that he should enunciate many maxims bearing on character and morals generally, but he never rested in the improvement of the individual. "The kingdom, the world, brought to a state of happy tranquillity."[1673] was the grand object which he delighted to think of; that it might be brought about as easily as "one can look upon the palm of his hand," was the dream which it pleased him to indulge.[1674] He held that there was in men an adaptation and readiness to be governed, which only needed to be taken advantage of in the proper way. There must be the right administrators, but given those, and "the growth of government would be rapid, just as vegetation is rapid in the earth; yea, their government would display itself like an easily-growing rush."[1675] The same sentiment was common from the lips of Mencius. Enforcing it one day, when conversing with one of the petty rulers of his time, he said in his peculiar style, "Does your majesty understand the way of the growing grain? During the seventh and eighth months, when drought prevails, the plants become dry. Then the clouds collect densely in the heavens; they send down torrents of rain, and the grain erects itself as if by a shoot. When it does so, who can keep it back?"[1676] Such, he contended, would be the response of the mass of the people to any true "shepherd of men." It may be deemed unnecessary that I should specify this point, for it is a truth applicable to the people of all nations. Speaking generally, government is by no device or cunning craftiness; human nature demands it. But in no other family of mankind is the characteristic so largely developed as in the Chinese. The love of order and quiet, and a willingness to submit to "the powers that be," eminently distinguish them. Foreign writers have often taken notice of this, and have attributed it to the influence of Confucius's doctrines as inculcating subordination; but it existed previous to his time. The character of the people moulded his system, more than it was moulded by it.

This readiness to be governed arose, according to Confucius, from "the duties of universal obligation, or those between sovereign and minister, between father and son, between husband and wife, between elder brother and younger, and those belonging to the intercourse of friends."[1677] Men as they are born into the world, and grow up in it, find themselves existing in those relations. They are the appointment of Heaven. And each relation has its reciprocal obligations, the recognition of which is proper to the heaven-conferred nature. It only needs that the sacredness of the relations be maintained, and the duties belonging to them faithfully discharged, and the "happy tranquillity" will prevail all under heaven. As to the institutions of government, the laws and arrangements by which, as through a thousand channels, it should go forth to carry plenty and prosperity through the length and breadth of the country, it did not belong to Confucius, "the throneless king," to set them forth minutely. And indeed they were existing in the records of "the ancient sovereigns." Nothing new was needed. It was only requisite to pursue the old paths, and raise up the old standards. "The government of Wên and Wu", he said, "is displayed in the records,—the tablets of wood and bamboo. Let there be the men, and the government will flourish; but without the men, the government decays and ceases."[1678] To the same effect was the reply which he gave to Yen Hui when asked by him how the government of a state should be administered. It seems very wide of the mark, until we read it in the light of the sage's veneration for ancient ordinances, and his opinion of their sufficiency. "Follow," he said, "the seasons of Hsia. Ride in the state-carriages of Yin. Wear the ceremonial cap of Chou. Let the music be the Shao with its pantomimes. Banish the songs of Chêng, and keep far from specious talkers."[1679]

Confucius's idea then of a happy, well-governed state did not go beyond the flourishing of the five relations of society which have been mentioned; and we have not any condensed exhibition from him of their nature, or of the duties belonging to the several parties in them. Of the two first he spoke frequently, but all that he has said on the others would go into small compass. Mencius has said that "between father and son there should be affection; between sovereign and minister righteousness; between husband and wife attention to their separate functions; between old and young, a proper order; and between friends, fidelity."[1680] Confucius, I apprehend, would hardly have accepted this account. It does not bring out sufficiently the authority which he claimed for the father and the sovereign, and the obedience which he exacted from the child and the minister. With regard to the relation of husband and wife, he was in no respect superior to the preceding sages who had enunciated their views of "propriety" on the subject. We have a somewhat detailed exposition of his opinions in the Narratives of the School.—"Man," said he, "is the representative of heaven, and is supreme over all things. Woman yields obedience to the instructions of man, and helps to carry out his principles.[1681] On this account she can determine nothing of herself, and is subject to the rule of the three obediences. When young, she must obey her father and elder brother; when married, she must obey her husband; when her husband is dead, she must obey her son. She may not think of marrying a second time. No instructions or orders must issue from the harem. Woman's business is simply the preparation and supplying of drink and food. Beyond the threshold of her apartments she should not be known for evil or for good. She may not cross the boundaries of the state to attend a funeral. She may take no step on her own motion, and may come to no conclusion on her own deliberation There are five women who are not to be taken in marriage:—the daughter of a rebellious house; the daughter of a disorderly house; the daughter of a house which has produced criminals for more than one generation; the daughter of a leprous house; and the daughter who has lost her father and elder brother. A wife may be divorced for seven reasons, which, however, may be overruled by three considerations. The grounds for divorce are disobedience to her husband's parents; not giving birth to a son; dissolute conduct; jealousy—(of her husband's attentions, that is, to the other inmates of his harem); talkativeness; and thieving. The three considerations which may overrule these grounds are—first, if, while she was taken from a home, she has now no home to return to; second, if she have passed with her husband through the three years' mourning for his parents; third, if the husband have become rich from being poor. All these regulations were adopted by the sages in harmony with the natures of man and woman, and to give importance to the ordinance of marriage."[1682]

With these ideas of the relations of society, Confucius dwelt much on the necessity of personal correctness of character on the part of those in authority, in order to secure the right fulfilment of the duties implied in them. This is one grand peculiarity of his teaching. I have adverted to tit in the review of The Great Learning, but it deserves some further exhibition, and there are three conversations with the chief Chi Kʽang in which it is very expressly set forth. "Chi Kʽang asked about government, and Confucius replied, 'To govern means to rectify. If you lead on the people with correctness, who will dare not to be correct?'" "Chi Kʽang, distressed about the number of thieves in the state, inquired of Confucius about how to do away with them. Confucius said, 'If you, sir, were not covetous, though you should reward them to do it, they would not steal.'" "Chi Kʽang asked about government, saying, 'What do you say to killing the unprincipled for the good of the principled?' Confucius replied, 'Sir, in carrying on your government, why should you use killing at all? Let your evinced desired be for what is good, and the people will be good. The relation between superiors and inferiors is like that between the wind and the grass. The grass must bend, when the wid blows across it.'"[1683]

Example is not so powerful as Confucius in these and many other passages represented it, but its influence is very great. Its virtue is recognised in the family, and it is demanded in the church of Christ. "A bishop"—and I quote the term with the simple meaning of overseer—"must be blameless." It seems to me, however, that in the progress of society in the west we have come to think less of the power of example in many departments of state than we ought to do. It is thought of too little in the army and the navy. We laugh at the "self-denying ordinance," and the "new model" of 1644, but there lay beneath them the principle which Confucius so broadly propounded,—the importance of personal virtue in all who are in authority. Now that Great Britain is the governing power over the masses of India, and that we are coming more and more into contact with tens of thousands of the Chinese, this maxim of our sage is deserving of serious consideration from all who bear rule, and especially from those on whom devolves the conduct of affairs. His words on the susceptibility of the people to be acted on by those above them ought not to prove as water split on the ground.

But to return to Confucius.—As he thus lays it down that the mainspring of the well-being of society is the personal character of the rule, we look anxiously for what directions he has given for the cultivation of that. But here he is very defective. "Self-adjustment and purification," he said, "with careful regulation of his dress, and the not making a movement contrary to the rules of propriety;—this is the way for ruler to cultivate his person."[1684] This is laying too much stress on what is external; but even to attain to this is beyond unassisted human strength. Confucius, however, never recognised a disturbance of the moral elements in the constitution of man. The people would move, according to him, to the virtue of their ruler as the grass bends to the wind, and that virtue would come to the ruler at his call. Many were the lamentations which he uttered over the degeneracy of his times; frequent were the confessions which he made of his own shortcomings. It seems strange that it never came distinctly before him, that there is a power of evil in the prince and the peasant, which no efforts of their own and no instructions of sages are effectual to subdue.

The government which Confucius taught was a despotism, but of a modified character. He allowed no "jus divinum," independent of personal virtue and a benevolent rule. He has not explicitly stated, indeed, wherein lies the ground of the great relation of the governor and the governed, but his views on the subject were, we may assume, in accordance with the language of the Shu-ching:—"Heaven and earth are the parents of all things, and of all things men are the most intelligent. The man among them most distinguished for intelligence becomes chief ruler, and ought to prove himself the parent of the people."[1685] And again, "Heaven, protecting the inferior people, has constituted for them rulers and teachers, who should be able to be assisting to God, extending favour and producing tranquillity throughout all parts of the kingdom."[1686] The moment the ruler ceases to be a minister of God for good, and does not administer a government that is beneficial to the people, he forfeits the title by which he holds the throne, and perseverance in oppression will surely lead to his overthrow. Mencius inculcated this principle with a frequency and boldness which are remarkable. It was one of the things about which Confucius did not like to talk. Still he held it. It is conspicuous in the last chapter of The Great Learning. Its tendency has been to check the violence of oppression, and maintain the self-respect of the people, all along the course of Chinese history.

I must bring these observation on Confucius's views of government to a close, and I do so with two remarks. First they are adapted to a primitive, unsophisticated state of society. He is a good counsellor for the father of a family, the chief of a clan, and even the head of a small principality. But his views want the comprehension which would make them of much service in a great dominion. Within three centuries after his death, the government of Chinese passed into a new phase. The founder of the Chʽin dynasty conceived the grand idea of abolishing all its feudal kingdoms, and centralizing their administration in himself. He effected the revolution, and succeeding dynasties adopted his system, and gradually moulded it into the forms and proportions which are now existing. There has been a tendency to advance, and Confucius has all along been trying to carry the nation back. Principles have been needed, and not "proprieties." The consequence is that China has increased beyond its ancient dimensions, while there has been no corresponding development of thought. Its body politic has the size of a giant, while it still retains the mind of a child. It hoary age is in danger of becoming but senility.

Second, Confucius makes no provision for the intercourse of his country with other and independent nations. He knew indeed of none such. China was to him "the middle kingdom,"[1687] "the multitude of great states,"[1688] "all under heaven."/[1689] Beyond it were only rude and barbarous tribes. He does not speak of them bitterly, as many Chinese have done since his time. In one place he contrasts their condition favourably with the prevailing anarchy of the kingdom, saying "The rude tribes of the east and north have their princes, and are not like the states of our great land which are without them."[1690] Another time, disgusted with the want of appreciation which he experienced, he was expressing his intention to go and live among the nine wild tribes of the east. Someone said, "They are rude. How can you do such a ting?" His reply was, "If a superior man dwelt among them, what rudeness would there be?"[1691] But had he been a ruler-sage, he would not only have influenced them by his instructions, but brought them to acknowledge and submit to his sway, as the great Yü did.[1692] The only passage of COnfucius's teachings from which any rule can be gathered for dealing with foreigners, is that in the Doctrine of the Mean, where "indulgent treatment of men from a distance" is laid down as one of the nine standard rules for the government of the country. [1693] But "the men from a distance" are understood to be pin and lü[1694] simply,—"guests," that is, or officers of one state seeking employment in another, or at the royal court; and "visitors," or travelling merchants. Of independent nations the ancient classics have not any knowledge, nor has Confucius. So long as merchants from Europe and other parts of the world could have been content to appear in China as suppliants, seeking the privilege of trade, so long the government would have ranked them with the barbarous hordes of antiquity, and given them the benefit of the maxim about "indulgent treatment," according to its own understanding of it. But when their governments interfered, and claimed to treat with that of China on terms of equality, and that their subjects should be spoken to and of as being of the same clay with the Chinese themselves, an outrage was committed on tradition and prejudice, which it was necessary to resent with vehemence.

I do not charge the contemptuous arrogance of the Chinese government and people upon Confucius; what I deplore, is that he left no principles on record to check the development of such a spirit. His simple views of society and government were in a measure sufficient for the people while they dwelt apart from the rest of mankind. His practical lessons were better than if they had been left, which but for him they probably would have been, to fall a prey to the influences of Taoism and Buddhism, but they could only subsist while they were left alone. Of the earth earthy, China was sure to go to pieces when it came to collision with a Christianly-civilized power. Its sage had left it no preservative or restorative elements against such a case.

It is a rude awakening from its complacency of centuries which China has now received. Its ancient landmarks are swept away. Opinions will differ as to the justice or injustice of the grounds on which it has been assailed, and I do not feel called to judge or to pronounce here concerning them. In the progress of events, it could hardly be but that the collision should come; and when it did come it could not be but that China should be broken and scattered. Disorganization will go on to destroy it more and more, and yet there is hope for the people, with their veneration for the relations of society, with their devotion to learning, and with their habits of industry and sobriety;—there is hope for them, if they will look away from all their ancient sages, and turn to Him, who sends them, along with the dissolution of their ancient state, the knowledge of Himself, the only living and true God, and of Jesus Christ whom He hath sent.

I have little more to add on the opinions of Confucius. Many of his saying are pithy, and display much knowledge of character; but as they are contained in the body of the work, I will not occupy the space here with a selection of those which have struck myself as most worthy of notice. The

fourth book

of the Analects, which is on the subject of jên, or perfect virtue, has several utterances which are remarkable.

Thornton observes:—"It may excite surprise, and probably incredulity, to state that the golden rule of our Saviour, 'Do unto others as you would that they should do unto you,' which Mr. Locke designates as 'the most unshaken rule of morality, and foundation of all social virtue,' had been inculcated by COnfucius, almost in the same words, four centuries before."[1695] I have taken notice of this fact in reviewing both The Great Learning and The Doctrine of the Mean. I would be far from grudging a tribute of admiration to Confucius for it. The maxim occurs also twice in the Analects./ In

book XV xxiii

, Tzǔ-kung asks if there be one word which may serve as a rule of practice for all one's life, and is answered, "Is not reciprocity such a word? What you do not want done to yourself do not do to others." The same disciple appears in

book V xi

, telling Confucius that he was practising the lesson. He says, "What I do not wish men to do to me, I also wish not to do to men;" but the master tells him, "Tzʽǔ, you have not attained to that." It would appear from this reply, that he was aware of the difficulty of obeying the precept; and it is not found, in its condensed expression at least, in the older classics. The merit of it is Confucius's own.

When a comparison, however, is drawn between it and the rule laid down by Christ, it is proper to call attention to the positive form of the latter,—"All things whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you, do ye even so to them." The lesson of the gospel commands men to do what they feel to be right and good. It requires them to commence a course of such conduct, without regard to the conduct of others to themselves. The lesson of COnfucius only forbids men to do what they feel to be wrong and hurtful. So far as the point of priority is concerned, moreover, Christ adds, "This is the law and the prophets." The maxim was to be found substantially in the earlier revelations of God. Still it must be allowed that Confucius was well aware of the importance of taking the initiative in discharging all the relations of society. See his words as quoted from The Doctrine of the Mean

above

.

But the worth of the two maxims depends on the intention of the enuciators in regard to their application. Confucius, it seems to me, did not think of the reciprocity coming into action beyond the circle of his five relations of society. Possibly, he might have required its observance in dealings even with the rude tribes, which were the only specimens of mankind besides his own country men of which he knew anything, for on one occasion, when asked about perfect virtue, he replied, "It is, in retirement, to be sedately grave; in the management of business, to be reverently attentive; in intercourse with others, to be strictly sincere. Though a man go among the rude uncultivated tribes, these qualities may not be neglected."[1696] Still, Confucius delivered his rule to his countrymen only, and only for their guidance in their relations of which I have had so much occasion to speak. The rule of Christ is for man as man, having to do with other men, all with himself on the same platform, as the children and subjects of the one God and Father in heaven.

How far short Confucius came of the standard of Christian benevolence, may be seen from his remarks when asked what was to be thought of the principle that injury should be recompensed with kindness. He replied, "With what then will you recompense kindness? Recompense injury with justice, and recompense kindness with kindness."[1697] The same deliverance is given in one of the books of the Li Chi, where he adds that "he who recompenses injury with kindness is a man who is careful of his person."[1698] Chêng Hsüan, the commentator of the second century, says that such a course would be "incorrect in point of propriety."[1699] The "propriety" was a great stumbling-block in the way of Confucius. His morality was the result of the balancing of this intellect, fettered by the decisions of men of old, and not the gushings of a loving heart, responsive to the promptings of heaven, and in sympathy with earring and feeble humanity.

This subject leads me on to the last of the opinions of COnfucius which I shall make the subject of remark in this place. A commentator observes, with reference to the inquiry about recompensing injury with kindness, that the questioner was asking only about trivial matters, which might be dealt with in the way he mentioned, while great offences, such as those against a sovereign or a father, could not be dealt with by such an inversion of the principles of justice.[1700] In the second book of the Li Chi there is the following passage:—"With the slayer of his father, a man may not live under the same heaven; against the slayer of his brother, a man must never have to go home to fetch a weapon; with the slayer of his friend, a man may not live in the same state."[1701] The lex talionis here laid down in its fullest extent. The Chou Li tells us of a provision made against the evil consequences of the principle, by the appointment of a minister called "the reconciler."[1702] The provision is very inferior to the cities of refuge which were set apart by Moses for the manslayer to flee to from the fury of the avenger. Such as it was, however, it existed, and it is remarkable that Confucius, when consulted on the subject, took no notice of it, but affirmed the duty of blood-revenge in the strongest and most unrestricted terms. HIs disciple Tzǔ-hsia asked him, "What course is to be pursued in the case of the murder of a father or mother?" He replied, "The son must sleep upon a matting of grass, with his shield for his pillow; he must decline to take office; he must not live under the same heaven with the slayer. When he meets him in the marketplace or the court, he must have his weapon ready to strike him" "And what is the course on the murder of a brother?" "The surviving brother must not take office in the same state with the slayer; yet if he go on his prince's service to the state where the slayer is, though he meet him, he must not fight with him." "And what is the course on the murder of an uncle or an cousin?" "In this case the nephew or cousin is not the principal. If the principal on whom the revenge devolves can take it, he has only to stand behind with his weapon in his hand, and support him."[1703]

Sir John Davis has rightly called attention to this as one of the objectionable principles of COnfucius. [1704] The bad effects of it are evident even in the present day. Revenge is sweet to the Chinese. I have spoken of their readiness to submit to government, and wish to live in peace, yet they do not like to resign even to government the "inquisition for blood." Where the ruling authority is feeble, as it is at present, individuals and clans take the law into their own hands, and whole districts are kept in a state of constant feud and warfare.

But I must now leave the sage. I hope I have not done him injustice; the more I have studied his character and opinions, the more highly have I come to regard him. He was a very great man, and his influence has been on the whole a great benefit to the Chinese, while his teachings suggest important lessons to ourselves who profess to belong to the school of Christ.

Section III

His Immediate Disciples

Ssǔ-ma Chʽien makes Confucius say:—"The disciples who received my instructions, and could themselves comprehend them, were seventy-seven individuals. THey were all scholars of extraordinary ability.[1705] The common saying is, that the disciples of the sage were three thousand, whille among them there were seventy-two worthies. I propose to give here a list of all those whose names have come down to us, as being his followers. Of the greater number it will be seen that we know nothing more than their names and surnames. My principal authorities will be the Historical Records, the Narratives of the School, The Sacrificial Canon for the Sage's Temple, with Plates, and the chapter on "The Disciples of Confucius" prefixed to the Four Books, Text and Commentary, with Proofs and Illustrations. In giving a few notices of the better-known individuals, I will endeavour to avoid what may be gathered from the Analects.

Yen Hui, by designation Tzǔ-yüan (顔回，字子淵). He was a native of Lu, the favourite of his master, whose junior he was by thirty years, and whose disciple he became when he was quite a youth. "After I got Hui," Confucius remarked, "the disciples came closer to me." We are told that once, when he found himself on the Nêng hill with Hui, Tzǔ-lu, and Tzǔ-kung, Confucius asked them to tell him their different aims, and he would choose between them. Tzǔ-lu began, and when he had done, the master said, "It marks your bravery." Tzǔ-kung followed, on whose words the judgment was, "They show your discriminating eloquence." At last came Yen Yüan, who said, "I should like to find an intelligent king and sage ruler whom I might assist. I would diffuse among the people instructions on the five great points, and lead them on by the rules of propriety and music, so that they should not care to fortify their cities by walls and moats, but would fuse their swords and spears into implements of agriculture. They should send forth their flocks without fear into the plains and forests. There should be no sunderings of families, no widows or widowers. For a thousand years there would be no calamity of war. Yu would have no opportunity to display his bravery, or Tzʽǔ to display his oratory." The master pronounced, "How admirable is this virtue!"

When Hui was twenty-nine, his hair was all white, and in three years more he died. He was sacrificed to, along with Confucius, by the first emperor of the Han dynasty. The title which he now has in the sacrificial canon,—"Continuator of the sage," was conferred in the ninth year of the emperor, or, to speak more correctly, of the period, Chia-ching, AD 1530. Almost all the present sacrificial titles of the worthies in the temple were fixed at that time. Hui's place is the first of the four assessors, on the east of the sage.[1706]

Min Sun, styled Tzǔ-chʽien (閔損，字子騫). He was a native of Lu, fifteen years younger than Confucius, according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, but fifty year younger, according to the Narratives of the School, which latter authority is followed in The Annals of the Empire. When he first came to Confucius, we are told, he had a starved look,[1707] which was by-and-by exchanged for one of fullness and satisfaction.[1708] Tzǔ-kung asked him how the change had come about. He replied, "I came from the midst of my reeds and sedges into the school of the master. He trained my mind to filial piety, and set before me the examples of the ancient kings. I felt a pleasure in his instructions; but when I went abroad, and saw the people in authority, with their umbrellas and banners, and all the pomp and circumstance of their trains, I also felt pleasure in that show. These two things assaulted each other in my breast. I could not determine which to prefer, and so I wore that look of distress. But now the lessons of our master have penetrated deeply into my mind. My progress also has been helped by the example of you my fellow-disciples. I now know what I should follow and what I should avoid, and all the pomp of power is no more to me than the dust of the ground. It is on this account that I have that look of fullness and satisfaction." Tzǔ-chʽien was high in Confucius's esteem. He was distinguished for his purity and filial affection. His place in the temple is the first, east, among "the wise ones," immediately after the four assessors. He was first sacrificed to along with Confucius, as is to be understood of the other "wise ones," excepting in the case of Yu Jo, in the eighth year of the style Kʽai-yüan of the sixth emperor of the Tʽang dynasty, AD 720. His title, the same as that of all but the assessors, is—"The ancient worthy, the philosopher Min."

Jan Kêng, styled Po-niu (冉耕，字白 [al. 百] 牛). He was a native of Lu, and Confucius's junior only by seven years. When Confucius became minister of crime, he appointed Po-niu to the office, which he had himself formerly held, of commandant of Chung-tu. His tablet is now fourth among "the wise ones," on the wise.

Jan Yung, styled Chung-kung (冉雍，字仲弓). He was of the same clan as Jan Kêng, and twenty-nine years younger than Confucius. He had a bad father, but the master declared that was not to be counted to him, to detract from his admitted excellence. His place is among "the wise ones," the second, east.

Jan Chʽiu, styled Tzǔ-yu (冉求，字子有). He was related to the two former, and of the same age as Chung-kung. He was noted among the disciples for his versatile ability and many acquirements. Tzǔ-kung said of him, "Respectful to the old, and kind to the young; attentive to guests and visitors; fond of learning and skilled in many arts; diligent in his examination of things:—these are what belong to Jan Chʽiu." It has been noted in the life of Confucius that it was by the influence of Tzǔ-yu that he was finally restored to Lu. He occupies the third place, west, among "the wise ones."

Chung Yu, styled Tzǔ-lu and Chi-lu (仲由，字子路，又字季路). Hw e was a native of Pʽien (卞) in Lu, and only nine years younger than Confucius. At their first interview, the master asked him what he was fond of, and he replied, "My long sword." Confucius said, "If to your present ability there were added the results of learning, you would be a very superior man." "Of what advantage would learning be to me?" asked Tzǔ-ku. "There is a bamboo on the southern hill, which is straight itself without being bent. If you cut it down and use it, you can send it through a rhinoceros's hid;—what is the use of learning?" "Yes," said the master; "but if you feather it and point it with steel, will it not penetrate more deeply?" Tzǔ-lu bowed twice, and said, "I will reverently receive your instructions." Confucius was wont to say, "From the time that I got Yu, bad words no more came to my ears." For some time Tzǔ-lu was chief magistrate of the district of Pʽu (蒲), where his administration commanded the warm commendations of the master. He died finally in Wei, as has been related

above

. His tablet is now the fourth, east, from those of the assessors.

Tsai Yü, styled Tzǔ-wo (宰予，字子我). He was a native of Lu, but nothing is mentioned of his age. He had "a sharp mouth," according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien. Once, when he was at the court of Chʽu on some commission, the king Chao offered him an easy carriage adorned with ivory for his master. Yü replied, "My master is a man who would rejoice in a government where right principles were carried out, and can find his joy in himself when that is not the case. Now right principles and virtue are as it were in a state of slumber. His wish is to rouse and put them in motion. Could he find a prince really anxious to rule according to them, he would walk on foot to his court, and be glad to do so. Why need he receive such a valuable gift as this from so great a distance?" Confucius commended this reply; but where he is mentioned in the Analects, Tzǔ-wo does not appear to great advantage. He took service in the state of Chʽi, and was chief magistrate of Lin-tzǔ, where he joined with Tʽien Chʽang in some disorderly movement,[1709] which led to the destruction of his kindred, and made Confucius ashamed of him. His tablet is now the second, west, among "the wise ones."

Tuan-mu Tzʽǔ, styled Tzǔ-kung (端木賜，字子貢 [al. 子贛]), whose place is now third, east, from the assessors. He was a native of Wei (衞), and thirty-one years younger than Confucius. He had great quickness of natural ability, and appears in the Analects as one of the most forward talkers among the disciples. Confucius used to say, "From the time that I got Tzʽǔ, scholars from a distance came daily resorting to me." Several instances of the language which he used to express his admiration of the master have been given in the last section. Here is another:—The duke Ching of Chʽi asked Tzǔ-kung how Chung-ni was to be ranked as a sage. "I do not know," was the reply. "I have all my life had the heaven over my head, but I do not know its height, and the earth under my feet, but I do not know its thickness. In my serving of COnfucius, I am like a thirsty man who goes with his pitcher to the river, and there he drinks his fill, without knowing the river's depth." He took leave of COnfucius to become commandant of Hsin-yang (信陽宰), when the master said to him, "In dealing with your subordinates, there is nothing like moderation. Hold fast these two things, and do not swerve from them. To conceal men's excellence is to obscure the worthy; and to proclaim people's wickedness is the part of a mean man. To speak evil of those whom you have not sought the opportunity to instruct is not the way of friendship and harmony." Subsequently Tzǔ-kung was high in office both in Lu and Wei, and finally died in Chʽi. We saw how he was in attendance on Confucius at the time of the sage's death. Many of the disciples built huts near the master's grave, and mourned for him three years, but Tzǔ-kung remained sorrowing slone for three years more.

Yen Yen, styled Tzǔ-yu (言偃，字子游), now the fourth in the western range of "the wise ones." He was a native of Wu (吳), forty-five years younger than Confucius, and distinguished for his literary acquirements. Being made commandant of Wu-chʽêng, he transformed the character of the people by "proprieties" and music, and was priased by the master. After the death of COnfucius, Chi Kʽang asked Yen how that event had made no sensation like that which was made by the death of Tzǔ-chʽan, when the men laid aside their bowstring rings and girdle ornaments, and the women laid aside their pearls and earrings, and the voice of weeping was heard in the lanes for three months. Yen replied, "The influences of Tzǔ-chʽan and my master might be compared to those of overflowing water and the fattening rain. Wherever the water in its overflow reaches, men take knowledge of it, while the fattening rain falls unobserved."

Pu Shang, styled Tzǔ-hsia (卜商，字子夏). It is not certain to what state he belonged, his birth being assigned to Wei (衞), to Wei (魏), and to Wên (温). He was forty-five years younger than Confucius, and lived to a great age, for we find him, BC 406, at the court of the prince Wên of Wei (魏), to whom he gave copies of some of the classical books. He is represented as a scholar extensively read and exact, but without great comprehension of mind. What is called Mao's Shih-ching (毛詩) is said to contain the views of Tzǔ-hsia. Kung-yang Kao and Ku-liang Chʽih are also said to have studied the Chʽun Chʽiu with him. On the occasion of the death of his son he wept himself blind. His place is the fifth, east, among "the wise ones."

Chuan-sun Shih, styled Tzǔ-chang (顓孫師，字子張), has his tablet, corresponding to that of the preceding, on the west. He was a native of Chʽên (陳), and forty-eight years younger than COnfucius. Tzǔ-kung said, "Not to boast of his admirable merit; not to signify joy on account of noble station; neither insolent nor indolent; showing no pride to the dependent:—these are the characteristics of Chuan-sun Shih." When he was sick, he called (his son) Shên-hsiang to him, and said, "We speak of his end in the case of a superior man, and of his death in the case of a mean man. May I think that it is going to be the former with me today?"

Tsêng Shên [or Tsʽan], styled Tzǔ-yü (曾參，字子輿 [al. 子與]). He was a native of south Wuchang, and forty-six years younger than Confucius. In his sixteenth year he was sent by his father into Chʽu, where Confucius then was, to learn under the sage. Excepting perhaps Yen Hui, there is not a name of greater note in the Confucian school. Tzǔ-kung said of him, "There is no subject which he has not studied. His appearance is respectful. His virtue is solid. His words command credence. Before great men he draws himself up in the pride of self-respect. His eyebrows are those of longevity." He was noted for his filial piety, and after the death of his parents, he could not read the rites of mourning without being led to think of them, and moved to tears. He was a voluminous writer. Ten books of his composition are siad to be contained in the Rites of the elder Tai (大戴禮). The Classic of Filial Piety he is said to have made under the eye of Confucius. He was first associated with the sacrifices to Confucius in AD 668, but in 1267 he was advanced to be one of the sage's four assessors. His title—"Exhibitor of the fundamental principles of the sage," dates from the period of Chia-ching, as mentioned in speaking of Yen Hui.

Tan-tʽai Mieh-ming, styled Tzǔ-yü (澹臺滅明，字子羽). He was a native of Wuchang, thirty-nine years younger than Confucius, according to the Historical Records, but forty-nine, according to the Narratives of the School. He was excessively ugly, and Confucius thought meanly of his talents in consequence, on his first application to him. After completing his studies, he travelled to the south as far as the Yangtze. Traces of his presence in that part of the country are stilled pointed out in the department of Suzhou. He was followed by about three hundred disciples, to whom he laid down rules for their guidance in their intercourse with the princes. When Confucius heard of his success, he confessed how he had been led by his bad looks to misjudge him. He, with nearly all the disciples whose names follow, first had a place assigned to him in the sacrifices to Confucius in AD 739. The place of his tablet is the second, east in the outer court, beyond that of the "assessors" and "wise ones."

Corresponding to the preceding, on the west, is the tablet of Fu Pu-chʽi, styled Tzǔ-tsien (宓 [al. 密 and 虙, all = 伏] 不齊，字子賤). He was a native of Lu, and, according to different accounts, thirty, forty, and forty-nine years younger than Confucius. He was commandant of Tan-fu (單父宰), and hardly needed to put forth any personal effort. Wu-ma Chʽi had been in the same office, and had succeeded by dint of the greatest industry and toil. He asked Pu-chʽ how he managed so easily for himself, and was answered, "I employ men; you employ men's strength." People pronounced Fu to be a superior man. He was also a writer, and his works are mentioned in Liu Hsin's catalogue.

Next to that of Mieh-ming is the tablet of Yüan Hsien, styled Tzǔ-ssǔ (原憲，字子思), a native of Sung, or, according to Chêng Hsüan, of Lu, and younger than Confucius by thirty-six years. He was noted for his purity and modesty, and for his happiness in the principles of the master amid deep poverty. After the death of COnfucius, he lived in obscurity in Wei. In the notes to

Ana. VI iii

, I have referred to an interview which he had with Tzǔ-kung.

Kung-yeh Chʽang al. [Chih], styled Tzǔ-chʽang [al. Tzǔ-chih] (公冶長 [al. 芝], 字子長 [al. 子之]), has his tablet next to that of Pu-chʽi. He was son-in-law to Confucius. His nativity is assigned both to Lu and to Chʽi.

Nan-kung Kuo, styled Tzǔ-yung (南宮括 [al. 适 and, in the Narratives of the School, 縚 (Tʽao)], 字子容), has the place at the east next to Yüan Hsien. It is a question much debated whether he was the same with Nan-kung Chêng-shu, who accompanied Confucius to the court of Chou, or not. On occasion of a fire breaking out in the palace of duke Ai, while others were intent on securing the contents of the treasury, Nan-kung directed his efforts to save the library, and to him was owing the preservation of the copy of the Chou Li which was in Lu, and other ancient monuments.

Kung-hsi Ai, styled Chi-tzʽǔ [al. Chi-chʽên] (公晳哀，字季次 [al. 季沉]). His tablet follows that of Kung-yeh. He was a native of Lu, or of Chʽi. Confucius commended him for refusing to take office with any of the families which were encroaching on the authority of the princes of the states, and for choosing to endure the severest poverty rather than sacrifices a tittle of his principles.

Tsêng Tien, styled Hsi (曾蒧 [al. 點], 字晳). He was the father of Tsêng Shên. His place in the temples is the hall to Confucius's ancestors, where his tablet is the first, west.

Yen Wu-yao, styled Lu (顔無繇，字路). He was the father of Yen Hui, younger than Confucius by six years. His sacrificial place is the first, east, in the same hall as the last.

Following the tablet of /Nan-kung Kuo is that of Shang Chü, styled Tzǔ-mu (商瞿，字子木). To him, it is said, we are indebted for the preservation of the Yi-ching, which he received from Confucius. Its transmission step by step, from Chü down to the Han dynasty, is minutely set forth.

Next to Kung-hsi Ai is the place of Kao Chʽai, styled Tzǔ-kao and Chi-kao (高柴，字子羔 [al. 季羔; for 羔 moreover, we find 皋, and 睪]), a native of Chʽi, according to the Narratives of the School, but of Wei, according to Ssǔ-ma Chʽien and Chêng Hsüan. He was thirty (some say forty) years younger than Confucius, dwarfish and ugly, but of great worth and ability. At one time he was criminal judge of Wei, and in the execution of his office condemned a prisoner to lose his feet. Afterwards that same man saved his life, when he was flying from the state. Confucius praised Chʽai for being able to administer stern justice with such a spirit of benevolence as to disarm resentment.

Shang Chü is followed by Chʽi-tiao Kʽai [prop. Chʽi], styled Tzǔ-kʽai, Tzǔ-jo, and Tzǔ-hsiu (漆雕開 [pr. 啟], 字子開, 子若, and 子脩), a native of Tsʽai (蔡), or, according to Chêng Hsüan, of Lu. We only know him as a reader of the Shu-ching, and refusing to go into office.

Kung-po Liao, styled Tzǔ-chou (公伯僚，字子周). He appears in the

Analects, XIV xxxiii

, slandering Tzǔ-lu. It is doubtful whether he should have a place among the disciples.

Ssǔ-ma Kêng, styled Tzǔ-niu (司馬耕，字子牛), follows Chʽi-tiao Kʽai; also styled 黎耕. He was a great talker, a native of Sung, and a brother of Huan Tʽui, to escape from whom seems to have been the labour of his life.

The place next Kao Chʽai is occupied by Fan Hsü, styled Tzǔ-chʽih (樊須，字子遲), a native of Chʽi, or, according to others, of Lu, and whose age is given as thrity-six and forty-six years younger than Confucius. When young, he distinguished himself in a military command under the Chi family.

Yu Jo, styled Tzǔ-jo (有若，字子若). He was a native of Lu, and his age is stated very variously. He was noted among the disciples for his great memory and fondness for antiquity. After the death of COnfucius, the rest of the disciples, because of some likeness in Jo's speech to the master, wished to render the same observances to him which they had done to Confucius, but on Tsêng Shên's demurring to the thing, they abandoned the purpose. The tablet of Tzǔ-jo is now the sixth, east, among "the wise ones," to which place it was promoted in the third year of Chʽien-lung of the present dynasty. This was done in compliance with a memorial from the president of one of the boards, who said he was moved by a dream to make the request. We amy suppose that his real motives were—a wish to do justice to the merits of Tzǔ-jo, and to restore the symmetry of the tablets in the "hall of the great and complete one," which had been disturbed by the introduction of tablet of Chi Hsi in the preceding reign.

Kung-hsi Chʽih, styled Tzǔ-hua (公西赤，字子華), a native of Lu, younger than Confucius by forty-two years, whose place is the fourth, west, in the outer court. He was noted for his knowledge of ceremonies, and the other disciples devolved on him all the arrangements about the funeral of the master.

Wu-ma Shih [or Chʽi], styled Tzǔ-chʽi (巫馬施 [al. 期], 字子期 [al. 子旗]), a native of Chʽên, or, according to Chʽên, or, according to Chêng Hsüan, of Lu, thirty years younger than Confucius. His tablet is on the east, next to that of Ssǔ-ma Kêng. It is related that on one occasion, when Confucius was about to set out with a company of the disciples on a walk or journey, he told them to take umbrellas. They met with a heavy shower, and Wu-ma asked him, saying, "There were no clouds in the morning; but after the sun had risen, you told us to take umbrellas. How did you know that it would rain?" Confucius said, "The moon last evening was in the constellation Pi, and is it not said in the Shih-ching, 'When the moon is in Pi, there will be heavy rain?' It was thus I knew it."

Liang Chan [al. Li], styled Shu-yü (梁鱣 [al. 鯉] 字叔魚), occupies the eighth place, west, among the tablets of the outer court. He was a man of Chʽi, and his age is stated as twenty-nine and thirty-nine years younger than Confucius. The following story is told in connection with him.—When he was thirty, being disappointed that he had no son, he was minded to put away his wife. "Do not do so," said Shang Chü to him. "I was thirty-eight before I had a son, and my mother was then about to take another wife for me, when the master proposed sending me to Chʽi. My mother was unwilling that I should go, but Confucius said, 'Don't be anxious. Chü will have five sons after he is forty.' It has turned out so, and I apprehend it is your fault, and not your wife's, that you have no son yet." Chan took this advice, and in the second year after, he had a son.

Yen Hsing [al. Hsin, Liu, and Wei], styled Tzǔ-liu (顔幸 [al. 辛, 柳, and 韋], 字子柳), occupies the place, east, after Wu-ma Shih. He was a native of Lu, and forty-six years younger than Confucius.

Liang Chan is followed on the west Jan Ju, styled Tzǔ-lu [al. Tzǔ-tsêng and Tzǔ-yü] (冉孺 [al. 儒] 宇子魯 [al. 子曾 and 子魚]), a native of Lu, and fifty years younger than Confucius.

Yen Hsing is followed on the east by Tsʽao Hsü, styled Tzǔ-hsün (曹卹，字子循), a native of Tsʽai, fifty years younger than Confucius.

Next on the west Po Chʽien, styled Tzǔ-hsi, or, in the current copies of the Narratives of the School, Tzǔ-hsi (伯虔，字子皙 [al. 子析] or 子楷), a native of Lu, fifty years younger than Confucius.

Following Tzǔ-hsün is Kung-sun Lung [al. Chʽung], styled Tzǔ-shih (公孫龍 [al. 寵], 字子石), whose birth is assigned by different writers to Wei, Chʽu, and Chao (趙). He was fifty-three years younger than Confucius. We have the following account:—"Tzǔ-kung asked Tzǔ-shih, saying, 'Have you not learned the Book of Poetry?' Tzǔ-shih replied, 'What leisure have I to do so? My parents require me to be filial; my brothers require me to be submissive; and my friends require me to be sincere. What leisure have I for anything else?' 'Come to my master,' said Tzǔ-kung, 'and learn of him.'"

Ssǔ-ma Chʽien here observes:—"Of the thirty-five disciples which preceded, we have some details. Their age and other particulars are found in the books and records. It is not so, however, in regard to the fifty-two which follow."

Jan Chi, styled Tzǔ-chʽan [al. Chi-chʽan and Tzǔ-ta] (冉季，字子產 [al. 季產 and 子達]), a native of Lu, whose place is the 11th, west, next to Po Chʽien.

Kung-tsu Kou-tzǔ or simply Tzǔ, styled Tzǔ-chih (公祖勾茲 [or simply 茲], 字子之), a native of Lu. His tablet is the 23rd, east, in the outer court.

Chʽin Tsu, styled Tzǔ-nan (泰祖，字子南), a native of Chʽin. His tablet precedes that of the last, two places.

Chʽi-tiao Chʽih, styled Tzǔ-lien (漆雕哆 [al 侈], 字子斂), a native of Lu. His tablet is the 13th, west.

Yen Kao, styled Tzǔ-chiao (顔高字子驕). According to the Narratives of the School, he was the same was Yen Kʽo (刻, or 尅), who drove the carriage when Confucius rode in Wei after the duke and Nan-tzǔ. But this seems doubtful. Other authorities make his name Chʽan (產), and style him Tzǔ-tsing (子精). His tablet is the 13th, east.

Chʽi-tiao Tʽu-fu [al. Tsʽung], styled Tzǔ-yu, Tzǔ-chʽi, and Tzǔ-wên (漆雕徒父 [al. 從], 字子有 or 子友 [al. 子期 and 子文]), a native of /Lu, whose tablet precedes that of Chʽi-tiao Chʽih.

Jang Ssǔ-chʽih, styled Tzǔ-tʽu, or Tzǔ-tsʽung (壤 [al. 穰] 駟赤，字子徒 [al. 子從]), a native Chʽin. Some consider Jang-ssǔ (壤駟) to be a double surname. His tabelt comes after that of no. 40.

Shang Chai, styled Tzǔ-chi and Tzǔ-hsiu (商澤，字子季 [al. 子秀]), a native of Lu. His tablet is immediately after that of Fan Hsü, no. 26.

Shih Tso [al. Chih and Tzǔ]-shu, styled Tzǔ-ming (石作 [al. 之 and 子], 蜀，字子明). Some take Shih-tso (石作) as a double surname. His tablet follows that of no. 42.

Jên Pu-chʽi, styled Hsüan (任不齊，字選), a native of Chʽu, whose tablet is next to that of no. 28.

Kung-liang Ju, styled Tzǔ-chêng (公良孺 [al. 儒], 字子正), a native of Chʽin, follows the preceding in the temples. The Sacrificial Canon says:—Tzǔ-chêng was a man of worth and bravery. When Confucius was surrounded and stopped in Pʽu, Tzǔ-chêng fought so desperately, that the people of Pʽu were afraid, and let the master go, on his swearing that he would not proceed to Wei."

Hou [al. Shih] Chʽu [al. Chʽien], styled Tzǔ-li [al. Li-chih] (后 [al 石] 處 [al. 虔], 字子里 [al. 里之]), a native of Chʽi, having his tablet the 17th, east.

Chʽin Jan, styled Kʽai (秦冉，字開), a native of Tsʽai. He is not given in the list of the Narratives of the School, and on this account his tabelt was put out of the temples in the ninth year of Chia-tsing. It was restored, however, in the second year of Yung-chêng, AD 1724, and is the 33rd, east, in the outer court.

Kung-hsia Shou, styled Shêng [and Tzǔ-shêng] (公夏首 [al. 守], 字乘 [and 子乘]), a native of Lu, whose tablet is next to that of No 44.

Hsi Yung-tien [or simply Tien], styled Tzǔ-hsi [al. Tzǔ-chien and Tzǔ-chʽieh] (奚容箴 [or 點], 字子皙 [al. 子偕 and 子楷]), a native of Wei, having his tablet the 18th, east.

Kung Chien-ting [al. Kung Yu], styled Tzǔ-chung (公肩 [al. 堅] 定 [al. 公有], 字子仲 [al. 中 and 忠]). His nativity is assigned to Lu, to Wei, and to Tsin (晉). He follows no. 46.

Yen Tsu [al. Hsiang], styled Hsiang and Tzǔ-hsiang (顔祖 [al. 相], 字襄, and 子襄), a native of Lu, with his tablet following that of no. 50.

Chiao Tan [al. Wu], styled Tzǔ-chia (鄡單 [al. 郻], 字子家), a native of Lu. His place is next to that of no. 51.

Chü [al. Kou] Tsing-chʽiang [and simply Tsing], styled Tzǔ-chʽiang [al. Tzǔ-chieh and Tzǔ-mêng] (句 [al. 勾 and 鈎] 井疆 [and simply 井], 字子疆 [al. 子界 and 子孟]), a native of Wei, following no. 52.

Han [al. Tasi]-fu Hei, styled Tzǔ-hei [al. Tzǔ-so and Tzǔ-su] (罕 [al. 宰] 父黑，字子黑 [al. 子索 and 子素]), a native of Lu, whose tablet is next to that of no. 53.

Chʽin Shang, styled Tzǔ-pʽei [al. Pʽei-tzǔ and Pu-tzǔ] (秦商，字子丕 [al. 丕兹 and 不兹]), a native of Lu, or, according to Chêng Hsüang, of Chʽu. He was forty years younger than Confucius. One authority, however, says he was only four years younger, and that his father and Confucius's father were both celebrated for their strength. His tablet is the 12th, east.

Shin Tang, styled Chou (申黨字周). In the Narratives of the School there is a Shin Chi, styled Tzǔ-chou (申績，字子周). The name is given by other as Tʽang (堂 and 儻) and Tsu (續), with the designation Tzǔ-tsu (子續). These are probably the same person mentioned in the Analects as Shin Chʽang (申棖). Prior to the Ming dynasty they were sacrificed to as two, but in AD 1530, the name Tang was expunged from the sacrificial list, and only that of Chʽang left. His tablet is the 31st, east.

Yen Chih-pʽo, styled Tzǔ-shu [or simply Shu] (顔之僕，字子叔 [or simply 叔]), a native of Lu, who occupies the 29th place, east.

Yung Chʽi, styled Tzǔ-chʽi [al. Tzǔ-yen] (榮旂 [or 祈], 字子旗 or 子祺 [al. 子顔]), a native of Lu, whose tablet is the 20th, west.

Hsien Chʽêng, styled Tzǔ-chʽi [al. Tzǔ-hung] (縣成，字子祺 [al. 子橫]), a native of Lu. His place is the 22nd, east.

Tso Jên-ying or [simply Ying], styled Hsing and Tzǔ-hsing (左人郢 [or simply 郢], 字行 and 子行), a native of Lu. His tablet follows that of no. 59.

Yen Chi, styled An [al. Tzǔ-ssǔ] (燕伋 [or 級], 字思 [al. 子思]), a native of Chʽin. His tablet is the 24th, east.

Chêng Kuo, styled Tzǔ-tʽu (鄭國，字子徒), a native of Lu. This is understood to be the same with the Hsieh Pang, styled (Tzǔ-tsʽung 薛邦，字子從), of the Narratives of the School. His tablet follows no. 61.

Chʽin Fei, styled (Tzǔ-chih 秦非，字子之), a native of Lu, having his tablet the 31st, west.

Shih Chih-chʽang, styled Tzǔ-hêng [al. chʽang] (施之常，字子恆 [al. 常]), a native of Lu. His tablet is the 30th, east.

Yen Kʽuai, styled Tzǔ-shêng (顔噲，字子聲), a native of Lu. His tablet is the next to that of no. 64.

Pu Shu-shêng styled Tzǔ-chʽê (步叔乘 [in the Narratives of the School we have an old form of 乘], 字子車), a native of Chʽi. Sometimes for Pu (步) we find Shao (少). His tablet is the 30th, west.

Yüan Kʽang, styled Tzǔ-chi (原亢，字子籍), a native of Lu. Ssǔ-ma Chʽien calls him Yüan Kʽang-chi, not mentioning any designation. The Narratives of the School makes him Yüan Kʽang (抗), styled Chi. His tablet is the 23rd, west.

Yüeh Kʽo [al. Hsin], styled Tzǔ-shêng (樂欬 [al. 欣], 字子聲), a native or Lu. His tablet is the 25th, east.

Lien Chieh, styled Yung and Tzǔ-yung [al. Tzǔ-tsʽao] (廉絜，字庸 and 子庸 [al. 子曹]), a native of Wei or of Chʽi. HIs tablet is next to that of no. 68.

Shu-chung Hui [al. Kʽuai], styled Tzǔ-chʽi (叔仲會 [al. 噲], 字子期), a native Lu, or, according to Chêng Hsüan, of Tsin. He was younger than Confucius by fifty-four years. It is said that he and another youth, called Kʽung Hsüan (孔璇), attended by turns with their pencils, and acted as a amanuenses to the sage, and when Mêng Wu-po expressed a doubt of their competency, Confucius declared his satisfaction with them. He follows Lien Chieh in the temples.

Yen Ho, styled Jan (顔何，字冉), a native of Lu. The present copies of the Narratives of the School do not contain this name, and in AD 1588 Jan was displaced from his place in the temples. His tablet, however, has been restored during the present dynasty. It is the 33rd, west.

Ti Hei, styled Chê [al. Tzǔ-chê and Chê-chih] (狄黑，字皙 [al. 子皙 and 皙之]), a native of Wei, or of Lu. His tablet is the 26th, east.

Kuei [al. Pang] Sun, styled Tzǔ-lien [al. Tzǔ-yin] (邽 [al. 邦] 巽，字子斂 [al. 子飲]), a native of Lu. His tablet is the 27th, west.

Kʽung Chung, styled Tzǔ-mieh (孔忠，字子蔑). This was the son, it is said, of Confucius's elder brother, the cripple Mêng-pi. His tablet is next to that of no. 73. His sacrificial title is "the ancient worthy, the philosopher Mieh."

Kung-hsi Yü-ju [al. Yü], styled Tzǔ-shang (公西輿如 [al. 輿], 字子上), a native of Lu. His place is the 26th, west.

Kung-hsi Tien, styled Tzǔ-shang (公西葴 [or 點], 字子上 [al. 子尚]), a native of Lu. His tablet is the 28th, east.

Chʽin Chang [al. Lao], styled Tzǔ-kʽai (琴張 [al. 牢], 字子開), a native of Wei. His tablet is the 29th, west.

Chʽên Kʽang, styled Tzǔ-kʽang [al. Tzǔ-chʽin] (陳亢，字子亢 [al. 子禽]), a native of Chʽên. See

notes

on Ana. I x.

Hsien Tan [al. Tan-fu and Fêng], styled Tzǔ-hsiang (縣亶 [al. 亶父 and 豐], 字子象), a native of Lu. Some suppose that this is the same as no. 53. The advisers of the present dynasty in such matters, however, have considered them to be different, and in 1724, a tablet was assigned to Hsien Tan, the 34th, west.

The three preceding names were given in the Narratives of the School.

The research of scholars has added about twenty others.

Lin Fang, styled Tzǔ-chʽiu (林放，字子邱), a native of Lu. The only thing known of him is from the

Ana. III iv

. His tablet was displaced under the Ming, but has been restored by the present dynasty. It is the first, west.

Chü Yüan, styled Po-yü (蘧瑗，伯玉), an officer of Wei, and, as appears from the Analects and Mencius, an intimate friend of Confucius. Still his tablet has shared the same changes as that of Lin Fang. It is not the first, east.

Shên Chʽang (申棖). See no. 57.

Shên Tʽang (申堂). See no. 57.

Mu Pʽi (牧皮), mentioned by Mencius, VII pt. II xxxvii 4. His entrance into the temple has been under the present dynasty. His tablet is the 34th, east.

Tso Chʽiu-ming or Tso-chʽiu Ming (左丘明) has the 32nd place, east. His title was fixed in AD 1530 to be—"the ancient scholar," but in 1642 it was raised to that of "ancient worthy." To him we owe the most distinguished of the annotated editions of the Chʽun Chʽiu. But whether he really was a disciple of COnfucius, and in personal communication with him, is much debated.

The above are the only names and surnames of those of the disciples who now share in the sacrifices to the sage. Those who wish to exhaust the subject, mention in addition, on the authority of Tso Chʽiu-ming, Chung-sun Ho-chi (仲孫何忌), a son of Mêng Hsi (see the

prolegomena chapter 3 section 1

), and Chung-sun Shuo (仲孫説), also a son of Mêng Hsi, supposed by many to be the same with no. 17; Ju Pei (孺悲), mentioned in the

Analects, XVIII xx

, and in the Li Chi, XVIII sect. II ii 22; Kung-wang Chi-chʽiu (公罔之裘) and Hsü Tien (序點), mentioned in the Li Chi, XLIII 7; Pin-mou Chia (賓牟賈), mentioned in the Li Chi, XVII iii 15; Kʽung Hsüan (孔璇) and Hui Shu-lan (惠叔蘭), on the authority of the Narrative of the School; Chʽang Chi (常季), mentioned by Zhuangzi; Chü Yü (鞫語), mentioned by Yen-tzǔ (晏子); Lien Yü (廉瑀) and Lu Chün (魯峻), on the authority of 文翁石室; and finally Tzǔ-fu Ho (子服何), the Tzǔ-fu Ching-po (子服景伯) of the

Analects, XIV xxxviii

.

Section I

Chinese Works, with Brief Notices

十三經註疏, The Thirteen Ching, with Commentary and Explanations. This is the great repertory of ancient lore upon the classics. On the Analects, it contains the "Collection of Explanations of the Lun Yü," by Ho Yen and others (see the

prolegomena chapter 2 section 3

), and "The Correct Meaning," or "Paraphrase of Hsing Ping" (see the

prolegomena chapter 2 section 3

).

新刻批點四書讀本, A New Edition of the Four Books, Punctuated and Annotated, for Reading. This work was published in the seventh year of Tao-kuang (1837) by a Kao Lin (高琳). It is the finest edition of the four books which I have seen, in point of typographical execution. It is indeed a volume for reading. It contains the ordinary Collected Comments of Chu Hsi on the Analects, and his Chapters and Sentences of the Great Learning and Doctrine of the Mean. The editor's own notes are at the top and bottom of the page, in rubric

四書朱子本義匯參, The Proper Meaning of the Four Books as Determined by Chu Hsi, Compared with, and Illustrated from, Other Commentators. This is a most voluminous work, published in the tenth year of Chʽien-lung, AD 1745, by Wang Pu-chʽing (王步青), a member of the Han-lin College.

四書經註集證, The Four Books, Text and Commentary, with Proofs and Illustrations. The copy of this work which I have was edited by a Wang Tʽing-chi (汪廷機), in the third year of Chia-ching, AD 1798. It may be called a commentary on the commentary. The research in all matters of geography, history, biography, natural history, etc., is immense.

四書諸儒輯要, A Collection of the Most Important Comments of Scholars on the Four Books. By Li Pʽei-lin (李沛霖); published in the fifty-seventh Kʽang-hsi year, AD 1718. This work is about as voluminous as the 匯參, but on a different plan. Every chapter is preceded by a critical discussion of its general meaning, and the logical connection of its several paragraphs. This is followed by the text, and Chu Hsi's standard commentary. We have then a paraphrase, full and generally perspicuous. Next, there is a selection of approved comments, from a great variety of authors; and finally, the reader find a number of critical remarks and ingenious views, differing often from the common interpretation, which are submitted for his examination.

四書翼註論文, A Supplemental Commentary, and Literary Discussions, on the Four Books. By Chang Chên-tʽao [al Tʽi-an] (張甄陶 [al. 惕庵]), a member of the Han-li College, in the early part, apparently, of the reign of Chʽien-lung. The work is on a peculiar plan. The reader is supposed to be acquainted with Chu Hsi's commentary, which is not given; but the author generally supports his views, and defends them against the criticisms of some of the early scholar of this dynasty. His own exercitations are of the nature of essays more than of commentary. It is a book for the student who is somewhat advanced, rather than for the learner. I have often perused it with interest and advantage.

四書遵註合講, The Four Books, According to the Commentary, with Paraphrase. Published in the eighth year of Yung Chêng, AD 1730, by Wêng Fu [al. Kʽeh-fu] (翁復 [al. 克夫]). Every page is divided into two parts. Below, we have the text and Chu Hsi's commentary. Above, we have an analysis of every chapter, followed by a paraphrase of the several paragraphs. To the paraphrase of each paragraph are subjoined critical notes, digested from a great variety of scholars, but without the mention of their names. A list of 116 is given who are thus laid under contribution. In addition, there are maps and illustrative figures at the commencement; and to each book there are prefixed biographical notices, explanations of peculiar allusions, etc.

新增四書補註附考備旨, The Four Books, with a Complete Digest of Supplements to the Commentary, and Additional Suggestions. A New Edition, with Additions. By Tu Ting-chi (杜定基). Published in AD 1779. The original of this work was by Têng Lin (鄧林), a scholar of the Ming dynasty. It is perhaps the best of all editions of the four books for a learner. Each page is divided into three parts. Below, is the text divided into sentences and members of sentences, which are followed by short glosses. The text is followed by the usual commentary, and that by a paraphrase, to which are subjoined the supplements and suggestions. The middle division contains a critical analysis of the chapters and paragraphs; and above, there are the necessary biographical and other notes.

四書味根錄, The Four Books, with the Relish of the Radical Meaning. This is a new work, published in 1852. It is the production of Chin Chʽêng, styled Chʽiu-tʽan (金澂，字秋潭), an officer and scholar, who, returning, apparently to Canton province, from the north in 1836, occupied his retirement with reviewing his literary studies of former years, and employed his sons to transcribe his notes. The writer is fully up in all the commentaries on the classics, and pays particular attention to the labours of the scholars of the present dynasty. To the Analects, for instance, there is prefixed Chang Yung's History of Confucius, with criticisms on it by the author himself. Each chapter is preceded by a critical analysis. Then follows the text with the standard commentary, carefully divided into sentences, often with glosses, original and selected, between them. The the commentary there succeeds a paraphrase, which is not copied by the author from those of his predecessors. After the paraphrase we have explanations (解). The book is beautifully printed, and in small type, so that it is really a multum in parvo, with considerable freshness.

日講四書義解, A Paraphrase for Daily Lessons, Explaining the Meaning of the Four Books. This work was produced in 1677, by a department of the members of the Han-li College, in obedience to an imperial rescript. The paraphrase is full, perspicuous, and elegant.

御製周易折中; 書經傳説彚纂; 詩經傳説彚纂; 禮記義疏; 春秋傳説彚纂. These works form together a superb edition of the five ching, published by imperial authority in the Kʽang-hsi and Yung-chêng reigns. They contain the standard views (傳); various opinions (説); critical decisions of the editors (晏); prolegomena; plates or cuts; and other apparatus for the students.

毛西河先生全集, The Collected Writings of Mao Hsi-ho. See

prolegomena, chapter 2 section 3

. The voluminousness of his writings is understated there. Of 經集, or Writings on the Classics, there are 236 sections, while his 文集, or Other Literary Compositions, amount to 257 sections. His treatises on the Great Learning and the Doctrine of the Mean have been especially helpful to me. He is a great opponent of Chu Hsi, and would be a much more effective one, if he possessed the same graces of style as that "prince of literature."

四書拓餘説, A Collection of Supplemental Observations on the Four Books. The preface of the author, Tsʽao Chih-shêng (曹之升), is dated in 1795, the last year of the reign of Chʽien-lung. The work contains what we may call prolegomena on each of the four books, and then excursus on the most difficult and disputed passages. The tone is moderate, and the learning displayed extensive and solid. The views of Chu Hsi are frequently well defended from the assaults of Mao Hsi-ho. I have found the work very instructive.

鄉黨圖考, On the Tenth Book of the Analects, with Plates. This work was published by the author, Chiang Yung (江永), in the twenty-first Chʽien-lung year, AD 1761, when he was seventy-six years old. It is devoted to the illustration of the above portion of the Analects, and is divided into ten sections, the first of which consists of woodcuts and tables. The second contains the "Life of Confucius", of which I have largely avoid myself in the preceding chapter. The whole is a remarkable specimen of the minute care with which Chinese scholars have illustrated the Classical books.

四書釋地; 四書釋地續; 四書釋地又續; 四書釋地三續. We may call these volumes—The Topography of the Four Books; with Three Supplements. The author's name is Yen Zo-chʽü (閻若璩). The first volume was published in 1698, and the second in 1700. I have not been able to find the dates of the publication of the other two, in which there is more biographical and general matter than topographical. The author apologizes for the inappropriateness of their titles by saying that he could not help calling them supplements to the Topography, which was his "first love."

皇清經解, Explanations of the Classics, under the Imperial Tsʽing Dynasty. See the

prolegomena, chapter 2, section 3

. The work, however, was not published, as I have there supposed, by imperial authority, but under the superintendence, and at the expense (aided by other officers), of Yüan Yüan (阮元), governor-general of Guangdong and Guangxi, in the ninth year of the last reign, 1829. The publication of so extensive a work shows a public spirit and zeal for literature among the high officers of China, which should keep foreigners from thinking meanly of them.

孔子家語, Sayings of the Confucian Family. Family is to be taken in the sense of sect or school. In Liu Hsin's Catalogue, in the subdivision devoted to the Lun Yü, we find the entry:—"Sayings of the Confucian Family, Twenty-Seven Books," with a note by Ten Ssǔ-ku of the Tʽang dynasty,—"Not the existing work called the Family Syaings." The original work was among the treasures found in the wall of COnfucius's old house, and was deciphered and edited by Kʽung An-kuo. The present work by Wang Su of the Wei (魏) dynasty, grounded professedly on the older one, the blocks of which had suffered great dilapidation during the intervening centuries. It is allowed also, that, since Su's time, the work has suffered more than any of the acknowledged classics. Yet it is a very valuable fragment of antiquity, and it would be worth while to incorporate it with the Analects. My copy is the edition of Li Yung (李容), published in 1780. I have generally called the work Narratives of the School.

聖廟祀典圖考, Sacrificial Canon of the Sage's Temples, with Plates. This work, published in 1826, by Ku Yüan, styled Hsiang-chou (顧沅，字湘舟), is a very painstaking account of all the names sacrificed to in the temples of Confucius, the dates of their attaining to that honour, etc. There are appended to it Memoirs of Confucius and Mencius, which are not of so much value.

十子全書, The Complete Works of the Ten Tzǔ. See Morrison's Dictionary, under the character 子. I have only had occasion, in connection with this work, to refer to the writings of Zhuangzi (莊子), and Lieh-tzǔ (列子). My copy is an edition of 1804.

歷代名賢列女氏姓譜, A Cyclopaedia of Surnames, or Biographical Dictionary, of the Famous Men and Virtuous Women of the Successive Dynasty. This is a very notable work of its class; published in 1793, by 蕭智漢, and extending through 157 chapters or books.

文獻通考, General Examination of Records and Scholars. This astonishing work, which cost its author, Ma Tuan-lin (馬端臨), twenty years' labour, was first published in 1321. Rémusat says—"This excellent work is a library in itself, and if Chinese literature possessed no other, the language would be worth learning for the sake of reading this alone." It does indeed display all but incredible research into every subject connected with the government, history, literature, religion, etc., of the empire of China. The author's researches are digested in 348 books. I have had occasion to consult principally those on the literary monuments, embraced in the seventy-six books, from 174th to the 249th.

朱彝尊經義考, An Examination of the Commentaries on the Classics, by Chu Yi-tsun. The author was a member of the Han-li College, and the work was first published with an imperial preface by the Chʽien-lung emperor. It is an exhaustive work on the literature of the classics, in 300 chapters or books.

續文獻通考, A Continuation of the General Examination of Records and Scholars. This work, which is in 254 books, and nearly as extensive as the former, was the production of Wang Chʽi (王圻), who dates his preface in 1586, the fourteenth year of Wan-li, the style of the reign of the fourteenth emperor of the Ming dynasty. Wang Chʽi brings down the work of his predecessor to his own times. He also frequently goes over the same ground, and puts things in a clearer light. I have found this to be the case in the chapters on the classical and other books.

二十四史, The Twenty-four Histories. These are the imperially-authorized records of the empire, commencing with the Historical Records, the work of Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, and ending with the History of the Ming Dynasty, which appeared in 1742, the result of the joint labours of 145 officers and scholars of the present dynasty. The extent of the collection may be understood from this, that my copy, bound in English fashion, makes sixty-three volumes, each one larger than this. No nation has a history so thoroughly digested; and on the whole it is trustworthy. In preparing this volume, my necessities have been confined mostly to the works of Ssǔ-ma Chʽien, and his successor, Pan Ku (班固), the historian of the first Han dynasty.

歷代統記表, The Annals of the Nation. Published by imperial authority in 1803, the eighth year of Chʽia-chʽing. This work is invaluable to a student, being, indeed, a collection of chronological tables, where every year, form the rise of the Chou dynasty, BC 1121, has a distinct column to itself, in which, in different compartments, the most important events are noted. Beyond that date, it ascend to the nearly the commencement of the cycles in the sixty-first year of Huang-ti, giving—not every year, but the years of which anything has been mentioned in history. From Huang-ti also, it ascends through the dateless ages up to Pʽan-ku, the first of the mortal sovereigns.

歷代疆域表, The Boundaries of the Nation in the Successive Dynasties. This work by the same author, and published in 1817, does for the boundaries of the empire the same service which the preceding renders to its chronology.

歷代沿革表, The Topography of the Nation in the Successive Dynasties. Another work by the same author, and of the same date as the preceding.

The dictionaries chiefly consulted have been:—

The well-known Shuo Wên (說文解字), by Hsü Shên, styled Shu-chung (許愼，字叔重), published in AD 100; with the supplement (繫傳) by Hsü Chʽieh (徐鍇), of the southern Tʽang dynasty. The characters are arranged in the Shuo Wên under 540 keys or radicals, as they are unfortunately termed.

The Liu Shu Ku (六書故), by Tai Tʽung, styled Chung-ta (戴侗，字仲達), of our thirteenth century. The characters are arranged in it, somewhat after the fashion of the Êrh Ya (

prolegomena, chapter 1, section 1

), under six general divisions, which again are subdivided, according to the affinity of subjects, into various categories.

The Tzǔ Hui (字彚), which appeared in the Wan-li (萬歷) reign of the Ming dynasty (1573–1619). The 540 radicals of the Shuo Wên were reduced in this to 214, at which number they have since continued.

The Kʽang-hsi Tzǔ Tien (康熙字典), or Kʽang-hsi Dictionary, prepared by order of the great Kʽang-hsi emperor in 1716. This is the most common and complete of all Chinese dictionaries for common use.

The Yi Wên Pi Lan (蓺文備覽), A Complete Exhibition of All the Authorized Characters, published in 1787; "furnishing," says Dr. Williams, "good definitions of all common characters, whose ancient forms are explained."

The Pei Wên Yun Fu (佩文韻府), generally known among foreigners as The Kʽang-hsi Thesaurus. It was undertaken by an imperial order, and published in 1711, being probably, as Wylie says, "the most extensive work of a lexicographical character ever produced." It does for the phraseology of Chinese literature all, and more than all, that the Kʽang-hsi Dictionary does for the individual characters. The arrangement of the characters is according to their tones and final sounds. My copy of it, with a supplement published about ten years later, is in forty-five large volumes, with much more letterpress in it than the edition of the Dynastic Histories mentioned

above

.

The Ching Tsi Tsuan Ku Ping Pu Wei (經籍䉵詁并補遺), A Digest of the Meanings in the Classical and Other Books, with Supplement, by, or rather under the superintendence of, Yüan Yüan (see

above

). This has often been found useful. It is arranged according to the tones and rhymes like the characters in the Thesaurus.

Section II

Translations and Other Works

Confucius Sinarum Philosophus; sive Scientia Sinensis Latine Exposita. Studio et Opera Prosperi Intorcetta, Christiani Herdritch, Francisci Rougemont, Philippi Couplet, Patrum Societatis Jesu. Jussus Ludovici Magni. Parisiis, 1837.

The Works of Confucius; Containing the Original Text, with a Translation. Vol. I. By J. Marshman. Serampore, 1809. This is only a fragment of The Works of Confucius.

The Four Books; Translated into English, by Rev. David Collie, of the London Missionary Society. Malacca, 1828.

L'Invariable Milieu; Ouvrage Moral de Tseu-sse, en Chinois et en Manduchou, avec une Version Littérale Latine, une Traduction Françoise, etc. etc. Par M. Abel-Rémusat. A Paris, 1817.

Le Ta Hio, ou La Grande Étude; Traduit en François, avec une Version Latine, etc. Par G. Pauthier. Paris, 1837.

Y-king; Autiquissimus Sinarum Liber, quem ex Latina Interpretatione P. Regis, aliorumque ex Soc. Jesu PP. edidit Julius Mohl. Stuttgartiae et Tubingae, 1839.

Mémoires Concernant L'Histoire, Les Sciences, Les Arts, Les Mœurs, Les Usages, etc., des Chinois. Par Les Missionaires de Pêkin. A Paris, 1776–1814.

Histoire Générale de La Chine; ou Annales de cet Empire. Traduites du Tong-Kien-Kang-Mou. Par le feu Père Joseph-Annie-Marie de Moyriac de Mailla, Jesuite François, Missionaire à Pekin. A Paris, 1776–1785.

Notitia Linguae Sinicae. Auctore P. Prémare. Malaccae, cura Academiae Anglo-Sinensis, 1831.

The Chinese Repository. Canton, China, 20 vols., 1832–1851.

Dictionnaire des Noms, Anciens et Modernes, des Villes et Arrondissements de Premier, Deuxième, et Troisième ordre, compris dans L'Empire Chinoius, etc. Par Édouard Biot, Membre du Conseil de la Société Asiatique. Paris, 1842.

The Chinese. By John Francis Davis, Esq., F.R.S., etc. In two volumes. London, 1836.

China: Its State and Prospects. By W. H. Medhurst, D.D., of the London Missionary Society. London, 1838.

L'Univers: Histoire et Déscription des tous les Peuples. Chine. Par M. G. Pauthier. Paris, 1838.

History of China, from the Earliest Records to the Treaty with Great Britain in 1842. By Thomas Thornton, Esq., member of the Royal Asiatic Society. In two volumes. London, 1844.

The Middle Kingdom: A Survey of the Geography, Government, Education, Social LIfe, Arts, Religion, etc., of the Chinese Empire. By S. Wells Williams, LL.D. In two volumes. New York and London, 1848. The second edition, revised, 1883.

The Religious Condition of the Chinese. By Rev. Joseph Edkins, B.A., of the London Missionary Society. London, 1859.

Christ and Other Masters. By Charles Hardwick, M.A., Christian Advocate in the University of Cambridge. Part III. Religions of China, America, and Oceanica. Cambridge, 1858.

Introduction to the Study of Chinese Characters. By J. Edkins, D.D. London, 1876.

The Structure of Chinese Characters, Under 300 Primary Forms. By John Chalmers, M.A., LL.D. Aberdeen, 1882.

Endnotes

Title of the work.—論語, "Discourses and Dialogues;" that is, the discourses or discussions of Confucius with his disciples and others on various topics, and his replies to their inquiries. Many chapters, however, and one whole book, are the sayings, not of the sage himself, but of some of his disciples. The characters may also be rendered "Digested Conversations," and this appears to be the more ancient signification attached to them, the account being that, after the death of Confucius, his disciples collected together and compared the memoranda of his conversations which they had severally preserved, digesting them into the twenty books which composed the work. Hence the title—論語, "Discussed Sayings," or "Digested Conversations." See

論語註疏解經序

. I have styled the work Confucian Analects, as being more descriptive of its character than any other name I could think of. ↩

Heading of this book.—學而第一. The two first characters in the book, after the introductory—"The Master said," are adopted as its heading. The is similar to the custom of the Jews, who name many books in the Bible from the first word in them. 第一, "The First;" that is, of the twenty books composing the whole work. In some of the books we find a unity or analogy of subjects, which evidently guided the compilers in grouping the chapters together. Others seem devoid of any such principle of combination. The sixteen chapters of this book are occupied, it is said, with the fundamental subjects which ought to engage the attention of the learner, and the great matters of human practice. The word 學, "learn," rightly occupies the forefront in the studies of a nation, of which its educational system has so long been the distinction and glory. ↩

The whole work and achievement of the learning, first perfecting his knowledge, then attracting by his fame like-minded individuals, and finally complete in himself. ↩

子, at the commencement, indicates Confucius. 子, "a son," is also the common designation of males,—especially of virtuous men. We find it, in conversations, used in the same way as our "Sir." When it follows the surname, it is equivalent to our "Mr." or may be rendered "the philosopher," "the scholar," "the officer," etc. Often, however, it is better to leave it untranslated. When it precedes the surname, it indicates the person spoken of was the master of the writer, as 子沈子, "my master, the philosopher 沈." Standing single and alone, as in the text, it denotes Confucius, the philosopher, or, rather, the master. If we render the term by Confucius, as all preceding translators have done, we miss the indication which it gives of the handiwork of his disciples, and the reverence which it bespeaks for him. ↩

不亦...乎 is explained by 豈不, "is it not?" See

四書補注備旨

. To bring out the force of "also" in 亦, some say thus:—"The occasions for pleasure are many, is this also one?" But it is better to consider 亦 as merely redundant;—see Wang Yin-chih's masterly

Treatise on the particles, chap. iii

; it forms chaps. 1208 to 1217 of the 皇清經解. 說, read yüeh, as always when it has the entering tone marked, stands for 悅. What is learned becomes by practice and application one's own, and hence arises complacent pleasure in the mastering mind. 悅, as distinguished from 樂 (lê), in the next paragraph, is the internal, individual feeling of pleasure, and the other, its external manifestation, implying also companionship. ↩

學, in the old commentators, is explained by 誦, "to read chantingly," "to discuss." Chu Hsi interprets it by 效, "to imitate," and makes its results to be 明善而復初, "the understanding of all excellence, and the bringing back original goodness." Subsequent scholars profess, for the most part, great admiration of this explanation. It is an illustration, to my mind, of the way in which Chu Hsi and his followers are continually being wise above what is written in the classical books. 習 is the rapid and frequent motion of the wings of a bird in flying, used for "to repeat," "to practise." 之 is the object of the third pers pronoun, and its antecedent is to be found in the pregnant meaning of 學. ↩

朋, properly "fellow-students;" but, generally, individuals of the same class and character, like-minded. ↩

君子 I translate here—"a man of complete virtue." Literally, it is—"a princely man." See on 子, above. It is a technical term in Chinese moral writers, for which there is no exact correspondency in English, and which cannot be rendered always in the same way. See Morrison's Dictionary, character 子. Its opposite is 小人, "a small, mean man." ↩

人不知, "Men do not know him," but anciently some explained—"men do not know," that is, are stupid under his teaching. The interpretation in the text is, doubtless, the correct one. ↩

Filial piety and fraternal submission are the foundation of all virtuous practice. ↩

Yu, named 若, and styled 子有, and 子若, a native of 魯, was famed among the other disciples of Confucius for his strong memory, and love for the doctrines of antiquity. In something about him he resembled the sage. See

Mencius, III Pt. I iv 13

. 有子 is "Yu, the philosopher," and he and Tsêng Shên are the only two of Confucius's disciples who are mentioned in this style in the "Lun Yü. This has led to an opinion on the part of some, that the work was compiled by the disciples. This may not be sufficiently supported, but I have not found the peculiarity pointed out satisfactorily explained. The tablet of Yu's spirit is now in the same apartment of the sage's temples as that of the same himself, occupying the 6th place in the eastern range of "the wise ones." To this position it was promoted in the 3rd year of Chʽien-lung of the present dynasty. ↩

鮮, 3rd tone, = "few." ↩

A degree of activity enters into the meaning of 爲 in 爲人, = "playing the man," "as men, showing themselves filial," etc. ↩

弟, here = 悌, "to be submissive as a younger brother," is in the 4th tone. With its proper signification, it was anciently in the 3rd tone, an adjective, = "good." ↩

而 = "and yet," different from its simple conjunctive use = "and," in the preceding chapter. ↩

好, a verb "to love," in the 4th tone, differs from the same character in the 3rd tone, an adjective, = "good." ↩

One the idiom—未之有, see

Prémare's Grammar, p. 156

. ↩

君子 has a less intense signification here than in the last chapter. I translate—"The superior man," for want of a better term. ↩

本, "the root," "what is radical," is here said of filial and fraternal duties. ↩

道, "ways" or "courses," of all that is intended by 爲 (=行) 仁, below. ↩

The particles 也者 resume the discourse about 孝弟, and introduce some further description of them. See

Prémare, p. 158

. ↩

仁 is explained here as "the principle of love," "the virtue of the heart." Mencius says—仁也者人也, "仁 is man," in accordance with which, Julien translates it by humanitas. Benevolence often comes near it, but, as has been said before of 君子, we cannot give a uniform rendering of the term. ↩

與, in the 2nd tone, is half interrogative, an answer in the affirmative being implied. ↩

Fair appearances are suspicious. ↩

巧言令色,—see

Shu-Ching, II iii 2

. 巧, "skill in workmanship;" then, "skill," "cleverness," generally, and sometimes with a bad meaning, as here, = "artful," "hypocritical." 令, "a law," "an order," also "good," and here like 巧, with a bad meaning, = "pretending to be good." 色, "the manifestation of the feelings made in the colour of the countenance," is here used for the appearance generally. ↩

How the philosopher Tsêng daily examined himself, to guard against his being guilty of any imposition. ↩

Tsêng, whose name was 參 (Shên), and his designation 子輿, was one of the principal disciples of Confucius. A follower of the sage from his 16th year, though inferior in natural ability to some others, by his filial piety and other moral qualities, he entirely won the Master's esteem, and by persevering attention mastered his doctrines. Confucius, it is said, employed him in the composition of the 考經, or Classics of Filial Piety. The authorship of the 大學, The Great Learning, is also ascribed to him, though incorrectly, as we shall see. Portions, moreover, of his composition are preserved in the Li Chi. His spirit tablet among the sage's four assessors, occupying the first place on the west, has precedence of that of Mencius. ↩

省, read hsing, "to examine." ↩

身, "the body", "one's personality;" 吾身 = myself. ↩

三省 is naturally understood of "three times," but the context and consent of commentators make us assent to the interpretation—"on three points." ↩

爲 is in the 4th tone, = "for." So, frequently, below. ↩

忠 from 中, "middle," "the centre," and 心, "the heart," = loyalty, faithfulness, action with and from the heart. ↩

朋, see

chap. i

. 友, "two hands joined," denoting union. 朋友, = when together, "friends." ↩

傳不習 is very enigmatical. The translation follows Chu Hsi. 何晏 explained quite differently: "whether I have given instruction in what I had not studied and practised?" It does seem more correct to take 傳 actively, "to give instruction," rather than passively, "to receive instruction." See Mao Hsi-ho's

四書改錯, XV article 17

. ↩

Fundamental principles for the government of a large state. ↩

道 is used for 導, "to rule," "to lead," and is marked in the 4th tone, to distinguish it from 道 the noun, which was anciently read with the 3rd tone. It is different from 治, which refers to the actual business of government, while 導 is the duty and purpose thereof, apprehended by the prince. The standpoint of the principles in the prince's mind. ↩

乘, in 4th tone, "a chariot," different from its meaning in the 2nd tone, "to ride." A country of 1000 chariot was one of the largest fiefs of the empire, which could bring such armament into the field. ↩

The last principle,—使民以時, means that the people should not be called from their husbandry at improper seasons, to do service on military expeditions and public works. ↩

Rules for the training of the young:—Duty first and then accomplishments. ↩

弟子, "younger brothers and sons," taken together, = youths, a youth. The 2nd 弟 is for 悌 as in

chap. ii

. ↩

入出, "coming in, going out," = at home, abroad. ↩

汎 is explained by Chu Hsi by 廣, "wide," "widely;" its proper meaning is the rush or overflow of water. ↩

力, "strength," here embracing the idea of leisure. ↩

學文, not literacy studies merely, but all the accomplishments of a gentleman also:—ceremonies, music, archery, horsemanship, writing, and numbers. ↩

Tzŭ-hsia's views of the substance of learning. ↩

Tzŭ-hsia was the designation of 卜商, another of the sage's distinguished disciples, and now placed 5th in the eastern range of "the wise ones." He was greatly famed for his learning, and his views of the Shih-ching and the Chʽun Chʽiu are said to be preserved in the commentaries of 毛, and of 公羊高 and 殼梁赤. He wept himself blind of the death of his son, but lived to a great age, and was much esteemed by the people and princes of the time. With regard to the scope of this chapter, there is some truth in what the commentator Wu, 吳, says,—that Tzŭ-hsia's words maybe wrested to depreciate learning, while those of the Master in the preceding chapter his exactly the due medium. ↩

The 2nd 賢 is a concrete noun. Written in full, it is composed of the characters for a minister, loyal, and a precious shell. It conveys the ideas of talents and worth in the concrete, but it is not easy to render it uniformly by any one term of another language. The 1st 賢 is a verb, = "to treat as a hsien." ↩

色 has a different meaning from that in the 3rd chapter. Here it means "sensual pleasure." Literally rendered, the first sentence would be, "esteeming properly the virtuous, and changing the love of woman," and great fault is found by some, as in

四書改錯, XIII i

, with Chu Hsi's interpretation which have followed; but there is force in what his adherents say, that the passage is not to be understood as if the individual spoken of had ever been given to pleasure, but simply signifies the sincerity of his love for the virtuous. ↩

致, here = 委, "to give to," "to devote." ↩

Principles of self-cultivation. ↩

君子 has here its lightest meaning, = a student, one who wishes to be a Chün-tzŭ. ↩

孔安國, of the Han dynasty, in the 2nd century BC, took 固, in the sense "obscured," "dulled," and interprets—"Let him learn, and he will not fall into error." The received interpretation, as in the transl. is better. ↩

主, as a verb, "to hold to be chief." It is often used thus. ↩

The object of friendship, with Chinese moralists, is to improve one's knowledge and virtue;—hence, this seemingly, but not really, selfish maxim. ↩

The good effect of attention on the part of superiors to the offices to the dead:—An admonition of Tsêng Shên. ↩

終, "the end," = death, and 遠, "distant," have both the force of adjectives = "the dead," and "the departed," or "the long gone." 慎 and 追 mean, "to be careful of," "to follow," but their application is as in the translation. ↩

厚, "thick," in opposition to 薄, "thin;" metaphorically, = good, excellent. The force of 歸, "to return," is to show that this virtue is naturally proper to the people. ↩

Characteristics of Confucius, and their influence on the princes of the time. ↩

Tzŭ-chʽin and Tzu-kʽang (亢) are designations of 陳亢, one of the minor disciples of Confucius. His tablet occupies the 28th place, on the west, in the outer part of the temples. On the death of his brother, his wife and major-domo wished to bury some living persons with him, to serve him in the regions below. Tzŭ-chʽin proposed that the wife and steward themselves submit to the immolation, which made them stop the matter. ↩

Tzŭ-kung, with the double surname 端木 and named 賜, occupies a higher place in the Confucian ranks. He is conspicuous in this work for his readiness and smartness in reply and displayed on several occasions practical and political ability. ↩

夫, "a general designation for males," = man. 夫子,—a common designation for a teacher or master. ↩

是邦, "this country" = any country. ↩

必, "must," = does not fail to. ↩

The antecedent to both the 之 is to the whole clause 聞其政. 與, with no tone marked = "to give to," "with," "to"; 與, as in

chap. ii

. ↩

The force of 其諸 is well enough expressed by the dash in English, the previous 也 indicating a pause in the discourse, which the 其, "it," resumes. See Wang Yin-chih's

Treatise, chap. ix

. ↩

On filial duty. ↩

行 is, in the 4th tone, explained by 行跡, "traces of walking," = conduct. It is to be understood that the way of the father had not been very bad. ↩

An old interpretation, that three years are to be understood of the three years of mourning for the father, is now rightly rejected. The meaning should not be confined to that period. ↩

In ceremonies a natural ease is to be prized, and yet to be subordinate to the end of ceremonies,—The reverential observance of propriety. ↩

禮 is not easily rendered in another language. There underlies it the idea of what is proper. It is 事之宜, "the fitness of things," what reason calls for in the performance of duties towards superior beings, and between man and man. Our term "ceremonies" comes near its meaning here. ↩

道 is here a name for 禮, as indicating the courses or ways to be trodden by men. ↩

In 小大由之, the antecedent to 之 is not 和, but 禮 or 道. ↩

Observe the force of the 亦, "also," in the last clause, and how it affirms the general principles enunciated in the first paragraph. ↩

To save from future repentance, we must be careful in our first steps. ↩

A different view of the scope of this chapter is taken by Ho Yen. It illustrates, according to him, the difference between being sincere and righteousness, between being respectful and propriety, and how a man's conduct may be venerated. The later view commends itself, the only difficulty being with 近於, "near to," which we must accept as a meiosis for 合乎, "agreeing with." 信 = 信約, "a covenant," "agreement." ↩

遠, 4th tone, "to keep away from." ↩

The force of the 亦 =- "he can go on to make them his masters." 宗 being taken as an active verb. ↩

With what mind one aiming to be a Chün-tzŭ pursues his learning. ↩

He may be well, even luxuriously, fed and lodged, but, with his higher aim, these things are not his seeking,—無求. ↩

A nominative to 可謂 must be supposed,—all this, or such a person. ↩

The closing particles, 也已, give emphasis to the preceding sentence, = yes, indeed. ↩

An illustration of the successive steps in self-cultivation. ↩

Tzŭ-kung had been poor, and then did not cringe. He became rich and was not proud. He asked Confucius about the style of character to which he had attained. Confucius allows its worth, but sent him to higher attainments. 而, here, = "and yet." 何如, "what as?" = "what do you say—what is to be thought—of this?" ↩

Observe the force of the 未, "not yet." ↩

The ode quoted is the first of the songs of Wei (衞), praising the prince Wu, who had dealt with himself as an ivory-worker who first cuts the bone, and then files it smooth, on a lapidary whose hammer and chisel are followed by all the appliances for smoothing and polishing. See the

Shih-ching, I v Ode i st. 2

. ↩

In 其斯之謂, the antecedent to 其 is the passage of the ode, and that to 斯 is the reply of Confucius. 之謂, see

Prémare, p. 156

. The clause might be translated—"Is not that passage the saying of this?" Or, "Does not that mean this?" ↩

Intorcetta and his co-adjutors translate here as if 賜 were in the 2nd pers. But the Chinese comm. put it in the 3rd, and correctly. Prémare, on the character 也, says, "Fere semper adjungitur nominibus propriis. Sic in libro Lun Yu, Confucius loquens de suis discipulis, Yeou, Keou, Hosi, vel ipsos alloquens, dicit 由也, 求也, 回也." It is not to be denied that the name before 也 is sometimes in the 2nd pers., but generally it is in the 3rd, and the force of the 也 = quoad. 賜也, quoad Tzʽŭ. ↩

已矣, nearly = 也已, (or 已 without marking the tone), in

chap. xiv

. ↩

The last clause may be given—"Tell him the past, and he knows the future;" but the connection determines the meaning as in the translation. 諸, as in

chap. x

, is a particle, a mere 語助, as it is called, "a helping or supporting word." ↩

Personal attainment should be our chief aim. ↩

Comp.

chap. i 3.

After the negative 不, as in

chapter ii 1

, observe the transposition in 己知, which is more elegant than 知己 would be. 己, "self," the person depending on the context. ↩

We cannot translate "do not be afflicted," because 不 is not used imperatively, like 勿. A nominative to 患 has to be assumed,—我, "I," or 君子, "the superior man." ↩

Heading of this book.—爲政第二. This second Book contains twenty-four chapters, and is named 爲政, "The practice of government." That is the object to which learning, treated of in the last Book, should lead, and here we have the qualities which constitute, and the character of the men who administer, government. ↩

The influence of virtue in a ruler. ↩

德 is explained by 得, and the old commentators say 物得以生謂之德, "what creatures get at their birth is called their virtue;" but this is a mere play on the common sound of different words. Chu Hsi makes it = 行道而有得於心, "the practice of truth and acquisition thereof in the heart." His view of the comparison is that it sets forth the illimitable influence which virtue in a ruler exercises without his using any effort. This is extravagant. This opponents say that virtue is the polar star, and the various departments of government the other stars. This is far-fetched. We must be content to accept the vague utterance without minutely determining its meaning. ↩

北辰 is, not doubt, "the north polar star," anciently believed to coincide exactly with the place of the real pole. ↩

共 in the 3rd tone used for 拱, "to fold the hands in saluting," here = "to turn respectfully towards." ↩

The pure design of the book of poetry. ↩

The number of compositions in the Shih-ching is rather more than the round number here given. 一言 = 一句, "one sentence." 蔽 = 蓋, "to cover," "to embrace." ↩

思無邪, see

Shih-ching, IV ii 1 st. 4

. The sentence there is indicative, and in praise of the duke Hsi, who had no depraved thoughts. The sage would seem to have been intending the design in compiling the Shih. A few individual pieces are calculated to have a different effect. ↩

How rulers should prefer moral appliances. ↩

道, as in

I v

. 之, "them," refers to 民, below. 政, as opposed to 德, = laws and prohibitions. ↩

齊 = "corn earing evenly;" hence, what is level, equal, adjusted, and here with the corresponding verbal force. ↩

民免, "The people will avoid," that is, avoid breaking the laws through fear of the punishment. ↩

格 has the signification of "to come to," and "to correct," from either of which the text may be explained,—"will come to good," or "will correct themselves." Observe the different application of 且 and 而 in

pars. 1 and 2

. 而 = "but;", 且 = "moreover." ↩

Confucius's own account of his gradual progress and attainments. Commentators are perplexed with this chapter. Holding of Confucius that 生而知之, 安而行之, "he was born with knowledge, and did what was right with entire ease," they say that he here conceals his sagehood, and puts himself on the level of common men, to set before them a stimulating example. We may believe that the compilers of the Analects, the sage's immediate disciples, did not think of him so extravagantly as later men have done. It is to be wished, however, that he had been more definite and diffuse in his account of himself. ↩

有, in 4th tone, = "and." The "learning," to which, at 15, Confucius gave himself is to be understood of the subjects of the "Superior Learning." See Chu Hsi's preliminary essay to the Ta Hsüeh. ↩

The "standing firm" probably indicates that he no more needed to bend his will. ↩

The "no doubts" may have been concerning what was proper in all circumstances and events. ↩

"The degrees of Heaven," = the things degreed by Heaven, the constitution of things making what was proper to be so. ↩

"The ear obedient" is the mind receiving as by intuition the truth from the ear. ↩

矩, "an instrument for determining the square." 不踰矩, "without transgressing the square." The expression describing the progress of Confucius at the different periods of his age are often employed as numerical designations of age. ↩

Filial piety must be shown according to the rule of propriety. ↩

Mêng Yi was a great officer of the Sate of Lu, by name Ho-chi (何忌), and the chief of one of the three great families by which in the time of Confucius the authority of that State was grasped. Those families were descended from three brothers, the sons by a concubine of the duke Huan (BC 711–694), who were distinguished at first by the prenomens of 仲, 叔, and 季. To these was subsequently added the character 孫, "grandson," to indicate their princely descent, and 仲孫, 叔孫, and 季孫 became the respective surnames of the families. 仲孫 was changed into 孟孫 by the father of Mêng Yi, on a principle of humility, as he thereby only claimed to be eldest of the inferior sons of their representatives, and avoided the presumption of seeming to be a younger full brother of the reigning duke. 懿, "mild and virtuous," was the posthumous honorary title given to Ho-chi. On 子, see

I i 1

. ↩

Fan, by name 須, and designated 子遲, was a minor disciple of the sage. Confucius repeated his remark to Fan, that he might report the explanation of it to his friend Mêng Yi, or Mêng-sun Yi, and thus prevent him from supposing that all the sage intended was disobedience to parents. Comp. the whole of Confucius's explanation with

I ix

. ↩

The anxiety of parents about their children an argument for filial piety. ↩

This enigmatical sentence has been interpreted in two ways. Chu Hsi takes 唯 (= 惟) not in the sense of "only," but of "thinking anxiously."—"Parents have the sorrow of thinking anxiously about their—i.e. their children's—being unwell. Therefore children should take care of their persons." The old commentators again take 唯 in the sense of "only."—"Let parents have only the sorrow of their children's illness. Let them have no other occasion for sorrow. This will be filial piety." Mêng Wu (the honorary epithet, = "Bold and of straightforward principle") was the son of Mang I, and by name 彘 (Chih). 伯 merely indicates that he was the eldest son. ↩

How there must be reverence in filial duty. ↩

Tzŭ-yu was the designation of 言偃, a native of 吳, and distinguished among the disciples of Confucius for his learning. He is now 4th on the west among "the wise ones." ↩

養 is in the 4th tone, = "to minister support to," the act of an inferior to a superior. ↩

Chu Hsi gives a different turn to the sentiment.—"But dogs and horses likewise manage to get their support." The other and older interpretation is better. 至於, "coming to," = as to, quoad. ↩

別 = "to discriminate," "distinguish." ↩

The duties of filial piety must be performed with a cheerful countenance. ↩

事 followed by 勞 = the "troublesome affairs" in the translation. The use of 弟子 in the phrase here extends filial duty to elders generally,—to the 父兄 as well as to the 父母. We have in translating to supply their respective nominatives to the two 有. ↩

食 read ssŭ, "rice," and then, food generally. ↩

先生饌 = 與先生饌之, "They give them to their elders to eat." 先生 = elders. The phrase, here meaning parents, uncles, and elders generally, is applied by foreign students to their teachers. ↩

曾, aspirated, = 則, "then," a transition particle. To these different interrogatories, the sage, we are told, made answer according to the character of the questioner, as each one needed instruction. ↩

The quiet receptivity of the disciple Hui. ↩

Yen Hui (顔回), styled 子淵, was Confucius's favourite disciple, and is now honoured with the first place east among his four assessors in his temples, and with the title of 復聖顔子, "The second sage, the philosopher Yen." At 29 his hair was entirely white, and at 33 he died, to the excessive grief of the sage. ↩

The subject of 退 is 回, and that of 省 (as in

I iv

) is 吾. 其私, "his privacy," meaning only his way when note with the master. 亦, "also," takes up 如愚,—He was so, and also thus. 回也, see

I xv 3

. ↩

How to determine the characters of men. ↩

以 is explained as = 行, or 行用, "does." The same, though not its common meaning, is the first given to it in the dict. For the noun to which the three 其 refer, we must go down to 人 in the 4th par. ↩

There is a climax in 所以, 所由 ("what from"), and 所安, and a corresponding one in the verbs 視, 觀, and 察. ↩

焉, generally a final particle, in 2nd tone, is here in the 1st, an interrogative, = how? Its interrogative force blends with the exclamatory of 哉 at the end. ↩

To be able to teach others one must from his old stores be continually developing things new. ↩

温 is expressed in the dictionary by 燖, and, with reference to this very passage, it is said, "one's old learning being thoroughly mastered, again constantly to practise it, is called 溫." Modern commentators say that the "new learning is in the old." The idea probably is that of assimilating old acquisitions and new. Compare

中庸, XXVII vi

. ↩

The general aptitude of the Chün-tzŭ. ↩

This is not like our English saying, that "such a man is a machine,"—a blind instrument. A utensil has its particular use. It answers for that and no other. Not so with the superior man, who is ad omnia paratus. ↩

How with the superior man words follow actions. ↩

The reply is literally—"He first acts his words and afterwards follows them." A translator's difficulty is with the latter clause. What is the antecedent to 之? It would seem to be 其言, but in that case there is no room for words at all. Nor is there according to the old commentators. In the interpretation I have given, Chu Hsi foollows the famous Chou Lien-hsi (周濂溪). ↩

The difference between the Chün-tzŭ and the small man. ↩

比, here in 4th tone, = "partial," "partizanly." The sentiment is this:—"With the Chün-tzu, it is in principles not men; with the small man, the reverse." ↩

In learning, reading and thought must be combined. ↩

罔, "a net," used also in the sense of "not," as an adverb, and here as an adjective. The old commentators make 殆, "perilous," simply = "wearisome to the body." ↩

Strange doctrines are not to be studied. ↩

攻, often "to attack," as an enemy, here = "to apply one's self to," "to study." 端, "correct;" then, "beginnings," "first principles;" here = "doctrines." 也已, as in

I xiv

. In Confucius's time Buddhism was not in China, and we can hardly suppose him to intend Taoism. Indeed, we are ignorant to what doctrines he referred, but his maxim is of general application. ↩

There should be no pretence in the profession of knowledge, or the denial of ignorance. ↩

由, by surname 仲, and generally known by his designation of Tzŭ-lu (子路), was one of the most famous disciples of Confucius, and now occupies in the temples the 4th place east in the sage's own hall. He was noted for his courage and forwardness, a man of impulse rather than reflection. Confucius foretold that he would come to an untimely end. He was killed through his own rashness in a revolution in the State of Wei. The tassel of his cap being cut off when he received his death-wound, he quoted a saying—"The superior man must not die without his cap," tied on the tassel, adjusted the cap, and expired. This action—結纓禮全—is much lauded. ↩

Of the six 知, the 1st and 6th are knowledge subjective, the other four are knowledge objective. 爲 = 以爲, "to take to be," 'to consider," "to allow." 女, thus marked with a tone, is used for 汝, "you." ↩

The end in learning should be one's own improvement, and not emolument. ↩

Tzŭ-chang, named 師, with the double surname 顓孫, a native of Chʽen (陳), was not undistinguished in the Confucian school. Tzŭ-kung praised him as a man of merit without boasting, humble in a high position, and not arrogant to the helpless. From this chapter, however, it would appear that inferior motives sometimes ruled him. ↩

學 = "was learning," i.e. at some particular time. 干 = 求, "to seek for." ↩

闕 is explained by 姑舍置, but this meaning of it is not given clearly in the dictionary. Compare its use in

XIII iii 4

. ↩

祿在其中, "Emolument is herein," i.e. it will come without seeking; the individual is on the way to it. The lesson is that we are to do what is right, and not be anxious about temporal concerns. ↩

How a prince by the right employment of his offices may secure the real submission of his subjects. ↩

Ai was the honorary epithet of 蔣, duke of Lu (BC 494–468);—Confucius died in his 16th year. According to the laws of posthumous titles, 哀 denotes "the respectful and benevolent, early cut off." 哀公 = "The to-be-lamented duke." ↩

錯, 4th tone, = 置, "to set aside." 諸 is partly euphonious, but also indicates the plural. 孔子對曰, "The philosopher Kʽung replied." Here, for the first time, the sage is called by his surname, and 對 is used, as indicating the reply of an inferior to a superior. ↩

Example in superiors is more powerful than force. ↩

Kʽang, "easy and pleasant, people-soother," was the honorary epithet of Chi-sun Fei (肥), the head of one of the three great families of Lu; see

chap. v

. His idea is seen in 使, "to cause," the power of force; that of Confucius appears in 則, "then," the power of influence. ↩

In 以勸, 以 is said to = 與, "together with," "mutually." 勸, "to advise," "to teach," has also in the dictionary the meaning—"to rejoice to follow," which is its force here, 爲善, "the practice of goodness," being understood. Wang Yin-chih (on the Particles) says that in this (and similar passages) 以 unites the meaning of 與 and 而; and this is the view which I have myself long held. ↩

Confucius's explanation of his not being in any office. ↩

或謂孔子,—the surname indicates that the questioner was not a disciple. ↩

Confucius had his reason for not being in office at the time, but it was not expedient to tell it. He replied there as in

par. 2

. ↩

See the

Shu-ching, V xxi 1

. But the text is neither correctly applied nor exactly quoted. The old interpreters read in one sentence 孝乎惟孝, "O filial piety! nothing but filial piety!" Chu Hsi, however, pauses at 乎, and commences the quotation with 惟孝. 奚其爲爲政, the 1st 爲 = 以爲, and 其 refers to the thought in the question, that office was necessary to one's being in government. ↩

The necessity to a man of being truthful and sincere. ↩

輗 and 軏 are explained in the dictionary in the same way—"the crossbar at the end of the carriage-pole." Chu Hsi says, "In the light carriage the end of the pole curved upwards, and the cross-bar was suspended from a hook." This would give it more elasticity. ↩

The great principles governing society are unchangeable. ↩

世 may be taken as an age = our "century," or as a generation = thirty years, which is its radical meaning being formed from three tens and one (卅 and 一.) Confucius made no pretension to supernatural powers and all commentators are agreed that the things here asked about were not what we call contingent or indifferent events. He merely says that the great principles of morality and relations of society had continued the same and would ever do so. 也 = 乎. ↩

The Hsia, Yin, and Chou are now spoken of as the 三代, "The three changes," i.e. the three great dynasties. The first sovereign of the Hsia was "The great Yü," BC 2205; of the Yin, Tʽang, BC 1766; and of Chou, Wu, BC 1122. ↩

Neither in sacrifice nor in any other practice may a man do anything but what is right. ↩

人神曰鬼, "The spirit of man (i.e. of the dead) is called 鬼. The 鬼 of which a man may say that they are his, are those only of his ancestors, and to them only he may sacrifice. The ritual of China provides for sacrifices to three classes of objects—天神, 地祇, 人鬼, "spirits of heaven, of the earth, of men." This chapter is not to be extended to all the three. It has reference only to the manes of departed men. ↩

Heading of this book.—八佾第三. The last Book treated of the practice of government, and therein no things, according to Chinese ideas, are more important than ceremonial rites and music. With those topics, therefore, the twenty-six chapters of this Book are occupied, and "eight rows," the principle words in the first chapter, are adopted as its heading. ↩

Confucius's indignation at the usurpation of royal rights. ↩

季氏, by contraction for 季孫氏; see on

II v

. 氏 and 姓 are now used without distinction, meaning "surname," only that the 氏 of a woman is always spoken of , and not her 姓. Originally the 氏 appears to have been used to denote the branch families of one surname. 季氏, "The Chi family," with special reference to its head, "The Chi," as we should say. 謂 is used here, as frequently, in the sense—"to speak of." ↩

佾, "a row of dancers," or pantomimes rather, who kept time in the temple services, in the 庭, the front space before the raised portion in the principal hall, moving or brandishing feathers, flags, or other articles. In his ancestral temple, the king had eight rows, each row consisting of eight men, a duke or prince had six, and a great officer only four. For the Chi, therefore, to use eight rows was a usurpation, for though it may be argued, that to the ducal family of Lu royal rites were conceded, and that the offshoots of it (

II v

) might use the same, still great officers were confined to the ordinances proper to their rank. ↩

Confucius's remark may also be translated, "If this be endured, what may not be endured?" For there is force in the observations of the author of the

四書翼註

, that this par. and the following must be assigned to the sage during the short time that he held high office in Lu. ↩

Again against usurped rights. ↩

三家者. "Those belonging to the three families." They assembled together, as being the descendants of duke Huan (

II v

), in one temple. To this belonged the 庭 in the last chapter, which is called 季氏庭, circumstances having concurred to make the Chi the chief of the three families; see

四書改錯, VIII vii

. For the Yung ode, see

Shih-ching, IV i sec. ii Ode vii.

It was, properly, sung in the royal temples of the Chou dynasty, at the 徹, "the clearing away," of the sacrificial apparatus, and contains the lines quoted by Confucius, quite inappropriate to the circumstances of the three families. ↩

辟,—without an aspirate. 相,—4th tone, "assistant," "assisting." ↩

Ceremonies and music vain without virtue. ↩

仁, see

I ii

. I don't know how to render it here, otherwise than in the translation. Commentators define it—心之全德, "the entire virtue of the heart." As referred to 禮, it indicates the feeling of reverence; as referred to 樂 (yüeh), it indicates harmoniousness. ↩

The object of ceremonies should regulate them:—Against formalism. ↩

Lin Fang, styled 子邱, was a man of Lu, whose tablet is now placed first, on the west, in the outer court of the temples. He is known only by the question in this chapter. According to Chu Hsi, 本 here is not 根本, "the radical idea," "the essence;" but = 初, "the beginning" (opposed to 末), "the first thing to be attended to." ↩

禮, as opposed to 喪 (1st tone), must indicate the festive or fortunate (吉) ceremonies,—capping, marriage, and sacrifices. ↩

易, read yi, 4th tone. Chu Hsi explains it by 治, as in Mencius—易其田疇, "to cleanse and dress the fields," and interprets as in the translation. The old commentators take the meaning—和易, "harmony and ease," i.e. not being overmuch troubled. ↩

The anarchy of Confucius's time. ↩

The 夷 were the barbarous tribes on the east of China, and 狄, those on the north. See

禮記, 王制, III xiv

. The two are here used for the barbarous tribes about China generally. ↩

諸夏 is a name for China because of the multitude of its regions (諸), and its greatness (夏). 華夏, "The Flowery and Great," is still a common designation of it. Chu Hsi takes 如 as simply = 似, and hence the sentiment in the translation. Ho Yen's commentary is to this effect:—"The rude tribes with their prices are still not equal to China with its anarchy." 亡, read as, and = 無. ↩

On the folly of usurped sacrifices. ↩

旅 is said to be the name appropriate to sacrifices to mountains, but we find it applied also to sacrifices to God. The Tʽai mountain is the first of the "five mountains" (五嶽), which are celebrated in Chinese literature, and have always received religious honours. It was in Lu, or rather on the borders between Lu and Chʽi, about two miles north of the present department city of Tʽai-an (泰安), in Shan-tung. According to the ritual of China, sacrifice could only be offered to those mountains by the sovereign, and by the princes in whose States any of them happened to be. For the chief of the Chi family, therefore, to sacrifice to the Tʽai mountain was a great usurpation. ↩

女 as in

II vii

= 汝, and 曾 as in

II viii

= 則, or we may take it as = 經, "Have you said," etc.? 泰山 = 泰山之神, "The spirit of the Tʽai mountain." Lin Fang,—see

chap. iv

from which the reason of this reference to him may be understood. Jan Yu, named (求), and by designation 子有, was one of the disciples of Confucius, and is now third, in the hall, on the west. He entered the service of the Chi family, and was a man of ability and resource. ↩

The superior man avoids all contentious striving. ↩

Here 君子 = 尚德之人, "the man who prefers virtue." 必也射乎, literally, "if he must, shall it be in archery?" ↩

揖譲, according to Chu Hsi, extend over all the verbs, 升, 下, 飲. 下 is marked in the 4th tone, anciently appropriate to it as a verb. 飲, 4th tone, "to give to drink," here = to exact from the vanquished the forfeit cup. In Confucius's time there were three principal exercises of archery:—the great archery, under the eye of the sovereign; the guests' archery, which might be at the royal court or at the visits of the princes among themselves; and the festive archery, for amusement. The regulations for the archers were substantially the same in them all, and served to prove their virtue, instead of giving occasion to quarrelling. There is no end to the controversies among commentators on minor points. ↩

Ceremonies are secondary and merely ornamental. ↩

The sentences quoted by Tzŭ-hsia are, it is supposed, from a 逸詩, one of the poems which Confucius did not admit into the Shih-ching. The two first lines, however, are found in it,

I v

;

III ii

. The disciple's inquiry turns on the meaning of 以爲 in the last line, which he took to mean—"The plain ground is to be regarded as the colouring." ↩

Confucius, in his reply, makes 後 a verb, governing 素, = "comes after the plain ground." ↩

禮後乎;—Tzŭ-hsia's remark is an exclamation rather than a question. 起予者, "He who stirs me up," = "He who brings out my meaning." On the last sentence, see

I xv

.—The above interpretation, especially as to the meaning of 繪事後素, after Chu Hsi, is quite the opposite of that of the old interpreters. Their view is of course strongly supported by the author of

四書改錯, VIII iii

. ↩

The decay of the monuments of antiquity. ↩

Of Hsia and Yin, see

II xxiii

. In the small state of Chʽi (originally what is now the district of the same name in Kʽai-feng department in Ho-nan. But the 文, "literary monuments" of those countries, and their 獻 (= 賢, so in the

Shu-ching, V vii 5, et al.

), "wise men," had become few. Had Confucius therefore delivered all his knowledge about the two dynasties, he would have exposed his truthfulness to suspicion. 徵, in the sense of 證, "to witness," and, at the end, "to appeal to for evidence." The old commentators, however, interpret the whole differently.—Already in the time of Confucius many of the records of antiquity had perished. ↩

The sage's dissatisfaction at the want of propriety in ceremonies. ↩

褅 is the name belonging to different sacrifices, but here indicates the 大祭, "great sacrifice," which could properly be celebrated only by the sovereign. The individual sacrificed to in it was the remotest ancestor from whom the founder of the reigning dynasty traced his descent. As to who were his assessors in the sacrifice and how often it was offered;—these are disputed points. See

Kʽang-hsi's dict., char. 褅

. Compare also

四書改錯, VII viii

, and

四書拓餘説, I xiii

. A royal rite, its use in Lu was wrong (see next chap.), but there was something in the service after the early act of libation inviting the descent of the spirits, which more particularly moved the anger of Confucius. 以往 = 以後, different from 往 in

I xv

. ↩

The profound meaning of the great sacrifice. ↩

This chapter is akin to

II xxi

. Confucius evades replying to his questioner, it being contrary to Chinese propriety to speak in a country of the faults of its government or rulers. ↩

說, "explanation," = meaning. The antecedent to the second 其 is the whole of the preceding clause:—"The relation to the kingdom of him who knew its meaning;—that would be as to look on this." 乎, interjective, more than interrogative. 示 = 視, "to see." 天下, "under heaven," an ambitious designation for the Chinese empire, as ἡ οἰκουμένη and orbis terrae were used by the Greek and Romans. ↩

Confucius's own sincerity in sacrificing. ↩

祭 here is historical and not to be translated in the imperative. We have to supply an objective to the first 祭, viz. 先祖, the dead, his forefathers, as contrasted with 神 in the next clause, = all the "spirits" to which in his official capacity he would have to sacrifice. ↩

Observe 與 in the 4th tone, "to be present at," "to take part in." ↩

That there is no resource against the consequences of violating the right. ↩

Chia was a great officer of Wei (衞), and having the power of the State in his hands insinuated to Confucius that it would be for his advantage to pay court to him. ↩

The 奧, or south-west corner, was from the structure of ancient houses the cosiest nook, and the place of honour. Chu Hsi explains the proverb by reference to the customs of sacrifice. The furnace was comparatively a mean place, but when the spirit of the furnace was sacrificed to, then the rank of the two places was changed for the time, and the proverb quoted was in vogue. But there does not seem much force in this explanation. The door, or well, or any other of the five things in the regular sacrifices, might take the place of the furnace. The old explanation which makes no reference to sacrifice is simpler. Ao might be the more retired and honourable place, but the tsao was the more important for the support and comfort of the household. The prince and his immediate attendants might be more honourable than such a minister as Chia, but more benefit might be got from him. 媚, from woman and eyebrows, = "to ogle," "to flatter." ↩

Confucius's reply was a high tone. Chu Hsi says, 天即理也, "Heaven means principle." But why should Heaven mean principle, if there were not in such a use of the term an instinctive recognition of a supreme government of intelligence and righteousness? We find 天 explained in the 四書拓餘説 by 高高在上者, "The lofty One who is on high." A scholar of great ability and research has written to me contending that we ought to find in this chapter a reference to fire-worship as having been by the time of Confucius introduced from Persia into China; but I have not found sufficient reference to such a introduction at so early a period. The ordinary explanation seems to me more satisfactory;—simple and sufficient. Ho Yen quotes the words of Kʽung An-kuo of our second century on the passage:—"Chia held in his hands the government of the State. Wishing to make Confucius pay court to him, he stirred him up in a gentle way by quoting to him a saying common among the people." ↩

The completeness and elegance of the institutions of the Chou Dynasty. ↩

By the 周 we are specially to understand the founders of the power and polity of the dynasty—the king Wên and Wu, and the duke of Chou. The two past dynasties are the Hsia and the Shang or Yin. 文 = "elegant regulations." ↩

Confucius and the grand temple. ↩

大 (= 太) 廟 was the temple dedicated to the duke of Chou (周公, and where he was sacrificed to with royal rites. The thing is supposed to have taken placed at the beginning of Confucius's official service in Lu, when he went into the temple with other officers to assist at the sacrifice. He had studied all about ceremonies, but he thought it a mark of sincerity and earnestness to make minute inquiries about them on the occasion spoken of. ↩

鄹 was the name of the town of which Confucius's father had been governor, who was known therefore as "the man of Tsou." Confucius would be styled as in the text, only in his early life, or by very ordinary people. ↩

How the ancients made archery a discipline of virtue. ↩

We are not to understand 射不主皮 of all archery among the ancients. The characters are found in the

儀禮, 鄉射, par. 315

of the Chu Shu edition. In the edition of the present dynasty,

V iii, par. 81

. There were trials of archery where the strength was tested. Probably Confucius was speaking of some archery of his times, when the strength which could go through the 皮, "skin," or leather, in the middle of the target, was esteemed more than the skill which could hit it. ↩

How Confucius cleaved to ancient rites. ↩

The king in the last month of the year gave out to the princes a calendar for the first days of the months of the year ensuing. This was kept in their ancestral temples, and on the 1st of every month they offered a sheep and announced the day, requesting sanction for the duties of the month. This idea of requesting sanction is indicated by 告, read kao. The dukes of Lu now neglected their part of this ceremony, but the sheep was still offered:—a meaningless formality, it seemed to Tzŭ-kung. Confucius, however, thought that while any part of the ceremony was retained, there was a better chance of restoring the whole. 去, in the 3rd tone, an active verb, "to put away." It is disputed whether 餼, in the text, means a living sheep, or a sheep killed but not roasted. ↩

愛, in the sense of 愛惜, "to grudge," it is said. But this is hardly necessary. ↩

How princes should be served:—Against the spirit of the times. ↩

The guiding principles in the relation of prince and minister. ↩

定, "Greatly anxious, tranquillizer of the people," was the posthumous epithet of 宋, prince of Lu, BC 509–495. 如之何, "As it what?" 之 referring to the two pointed inquired about. ↩

The praise of the first of the odes. ↩

關雎 is the name of the first ode in the Shih-ching, and may be translated—"The murmuring of the chü." See

Shih-ching, I i i

. ↩

A rash reply of Tsai Wo about the altars to the spirits of the land, and lament of Confucius thereon. ↩

哀公, see

II xix

. Tsai Wo, by name 予, and styled 子我, was an eloquent disciple of the sage, a native of Lu. His place is the second west among "the wise ones." 社, from 示 (Chʽi), "spirit or spirits of the earth," and 土, "the soil," means 土地神主, "the resting-place or altars of the spirits of the land or ground." ↩

Wo simply tells the duke that the founders of the several dynasties planted such and such trees about those altars. The reason was that the soil suited such tress; but as 栗, "the chestnut tree," the tree of the existing dynasty, is used in the sense of 慄, "to be afraid," he suggested a reason for its planting which might lead the duke to severe measures against his people to be carried into effect at the altars. Comp. the

Shu-ching, IV ii 5

, "I will put you to death before the 社." 夏后氏 is the Great Yü, called 后, to distinguish him from his predecessors, the 帝, and 夏氏, to distinguish him from 舜, who was 虞氏, while they were descended from the same ancestor. See

chap. i

, on 氏. 殷人 and 周人, in parallelism with 夏后氏, must mean the founders of these dynasties; why they are simply styled 人, "man," or "men," I have not found clearly explained, though commentators feel it necessary to say something on the point. ↩

This is all directed against Wo's reply. He had spoken, and his words could not be recalled. ↩

Confucius's opinion of Kuan Chung:—Against him. ↩

Kuan Chungz, by name 夷吾, is one of the most famous names in Chinese history. He was chief minister to the duke 桓 of 齊 (BC 683–642), the first and greatest of the five pa (伯 or 霸), leaders of the princes of the nation under the Chou dynasty. In the times of Confucius and Mencius, people thought more of Kuan than those sages, no hero-worshippers, would allow. 器, see

II xii

, but its significance here is difference, and = our measures or capacity. ↩

三歸, in the dictionary, and the commentary of Chu Hsi, was the name of an extravagant tower built by Kuan. There are other views of the phrase, the oldest and the best supported apparently being that it means, "three wives." (A woman's marriage is called 歸.) The San Kuei and having no pluralists among his officers proved that he could not be parsimonious. 焉, the 1st tone, "how." ↩

樹, "a tree," here in the sense of 屏, "a screen," the screen of a prince, usurped by Kuan, who was only entitled to the 簾 of a great officer. ↩

好, the 4th tone, = "a friendly meeting." The 坫, from 土 and 占, was a stand, made originally of earth and turf. Kuan usurped the use of it, as he did of the screen; being as regardless of prescribed forms, as in

par. 2

of expense, and he came far short therefore of the Confucian idea of the Chün-tzŭ. ↩

On the playing of music. ↩

語, the 4th tone, = 告, "to tell," "to instruct." 大 (= 太) 師樂 was the title of the Grand music-master. 樂其可知也, "music, it may be known," but the subject is not of the principles, but the performance of music. Observe the 如. Prémare says, "adjectivis addita sensum auget et exprimit modum." It is our ly or like,—翕如, "blended like." 從, the 4th tone, the same as 縱 = 放, "let go," i.e. proceeding, swelling on. ↩

A stranger's view of the vocation of Confucius. ↩

Yi was a small town on the borders of Wei, referred to a place in the present department of Kʽai-feng, Ho-nan province. ↩

Confucius at the beginning of his wanderings after leaving Lu was retiring from Wei, the prince of which could not employ him. This was the 喪 = 失位. The 1st and 3rd 見 are read hsien, 4th tone, = 通使得見, "to introduce," or "to be introduced." 之 in 君子之至於斯也 has its proper possessive power,—"In the case of a Chün-tzŭ's coming to this." Tsʽung, the 4th tone, "to attend upon." 二三子, "Two or three sons," or "gentlemen," = "my friends." The same idiom occurs elsewhere. The 木鐸 was a metal bell with a wooden tongue, shaken in making announcements, or to call people together. Heaven would employ Confucius to proclaim the truth and right. ↩

The comparative merits of the music of Shun and Wu. ↩

韶 was the name of the music made by Shun, perfect in melody and sentiment. 武 was the music of king Wu, also perfect in melody, but breathing the martial air, indicative of its author. ↩

The disregard of what is essential vitiates all services. ↩

The meaning of the chapter turns upon 何以 = 何有, or 以何者, "wherewith." 寬 is essential to rulers, 敬 to ceremonies, and 哀 to mourning. ↩

Headings of this book.—里仁第四, "Virtue in a neighbourhood, No. 4."—Such is the title of this forth Book, which is mostly occupied with the subject of 仁. To render that term invariably by benevolence, would by no means suit many of the chapters. See

II i 2

. Virtue, as a general term, would answer better. The embodiment of virtue demands an acquaintance with ceremonies and music, treated of in the last Book; and this, it is said, is the reason why the one subject immediately follows the other. ↩

Rule for the selection of a residence. ↩

According to the 周禮, five families made a 鄰, and five 鄰 a 里, which we might style, therefore, a hamlet or village. There are other estimates of the number of its component households. 處, 3rd tone, a verb, "to dwell in." 知, 4th tone, is the same as 智, "wise," "wisdom." So, not unfrequently, below. Friendship, we have seen, is for the aid of virtue (

I viii 3

), and the same should be the object desired in selecting a residence. ↩

Only true virtue adapts a man for the varied conditions of life. ↩

約, "to bind," is used for what binds, as an oath, a covenant; and here, the metaphor being otherwise directed, it denotes a condition of poverty and distress. 利, "gain," "profit," used as a verb, = 貪, "to desire," "to covet." 安仁, "to rest in virtue," being virtuous without effort. 利仁, "to desire virtue," being virtuous because it is the best policy. Observe how 者 following 仁 and 知 makes those terms adjectives or participles. 不可, "may not," = 不能, "cannot." The inability is moral. ↩

Only in the good man are emotions of love and hared right, and to be depended on. ↩

This chapter in incorporated with the

大學傳 X xv

. 好 and 惡 (read wu) are both verbs in the 4th tone. ↩

The virtuous will preserves from all wickedness. ↩

苟 = 誠, not merely—"if," but "if really." Comp. the statement

I John iii 9

, "Whosoever is born of God doth not commit sin." ↩

The devotion of the Chün-tzŭ to virtue. ↩

For the antecedent to 之 in the recurring 得之, we are to look to the following verbs, 處 and 去. We might translate the first 不以道得之, "if they cannot be obtained, etc.," but this would not suit the second case. 其道, "the way," i.e. the proper way. If we supply a nom. to 處 and 去, it must be 君子;—he will not "abide in," nor "go away from," riches and honours. ↩

惡, read wu, the 1st tone, "how." 名, "name," not reputation, but the name of a chün-tzŭ, which he bears. ↩

終食之間, "The space in which a meal can be finished;" meaning a short time. ↩

造次 (interchangeable with 草次) and 顛沛 are well-known expressions, the former for haste and confusion, the latter for change and danger; but it is not easy to trace the attaching of those meanings to the characters. 顛, "to fall down," and 沛, the same, but the former with the face up, the other with the face down. 必於是;—comp. Horace's "Omnis in hoc sum." ↩

A lament because of the rarity of the love of virtue; and encouragement to practice virtue. ↩

The first four 者 belong to the verbs 好 and 惡, and give them the force of participles. In 使不仁者, 者 belongs to 不仁, and 不仁者 = 不仁之事. Commonly, 者 = "he or those who," but sometimes also = "that or those things which." 尚 = 加, "to add to."

Morrison, character 尚

, translates the sentence wrongly—"He who loves virtue and benevolence can have nothing more said in his praise." ↩

蓋 here is 疑辭, "a particle of doubt;" as often. 未之有, a transposition, as in

I ii i

. ↩

A man is not to be utterly condemned because he has faults. Such is the sentiment found in this chapter, in which we may say, however, that Confucius is liable to the charge brought against Tzŭ-hsia,

I vii

. ↩

人之過也 stands absolutely,—"As to the faults of men." 各 = 各人, and 於 = 從,—"Each man follows his class." Observe the force of 過, "what goes beyond." The faults are the excesses of the general tendencies. Compare Goldsmith's line, "And even his failings leant to virtue's side." ↩

The importance of knowing the right way. ↩

One is perplexed to translate 道 here. Chu defines it—事物當然之理, "the principles of what is right in events and things." Better is the explanation in

四書翼註

,—道即率性之道, "道 is the path"—i.e. of action—"which is in accordance with our nature." Man is formed for this, and if he die without coming to the knowledge of it, his death is no better than that of a beast. One would fain recognise in such sentences a vague apprehension of some higher truth than Chinese sages have been able to propound.—"Could I once hear of the prevalence of right principles, I could die the same evening!" Other views of the meaning have been proposed. ↩

The pursuit of truth should raise a man above being ashamed of poverty. ↩

與議,—to be discoursed with i.e. about 道, or "truth," which perhaps is the best translation of the term in places like this. ↩

Righteousness is the rule of the Chün-tzŭ's practice. ↩

君子之云云, "The relation of the Chün-tzŭ to the world, i.e. to all things presenting themselves to him. 適, read ti, is explained by 尊主, "to set the mind exclusively on." We may take the last clause thus:—"his is the according with, and keeping near to (比, the 4th tone, = 從 or 親) righteousness." This gives each character its signification, the 與 blending its meaning with 比. ↩

The different mindings of the superior and the small man. ↩

Huai is here emphatic, = "cherishes and plans about." 土, "earth," "the ground," is here defined—所處之安, "the rest or comforts one dwells amidst." May it not be used somewhat in our sense of earthly?—"thinks of what is earthly." ↩

The consequence of selfish conduct. ↩

放, the 3rd tone, = 依, "to accord with," "to keep along."—"He who acts along the line of gain." ↩

The influence in government of ceremonies observed in their proper spirit. ↩

禮譲字是二是一, i.e. they are a hendiadys. 譲 = 禮之實, "the sincerity and substance of ceremony," the spirit of it. Comp. 和 in

I xii

爲 = 治, "to govern." This meaning is found in the dictionary. ↩

Advising to self-cultivation. ↩

Comp.

I xvi

. Here, as there, 不 not being imperative, we must supply a nominative. 位, "a place," i.e. an official situation. 所以立 is to be completed 所以立乎其位. ↩

Confucius's doctrine that of a pervading unity. This chapter is said to be the most profound in the Lun Yü. ↩

吾道一以貫之;—to myself it occurs to translate, "my doctrines have one thing which goes through them," but such an exposition has not been approved by any Chinese write. 一以貫之 are made to contain the copula and predicate of 吾道; and 之, it is said, "refers to all affairs and all things." The one thing or unity intended by Confucius was the heart, man's nature, of which all the relations and duties of life are only the development and outgoings. ↩

忠 and 恕, which seem to be two things, are both formed from 心, "the heart," 忠 being compounded of 中, "middle," "centre," and 心, and 恕 of 如 "as," and 心. The "centre heart" = I, the ego; and the "as heart" = the I in sympathy with others. 忠 is duty-doing, on a consideration, or from the impulse, of one's own self; 恕 duty-doing, on the principle of reciprocity. The chapter dhows that Confucius only claimed to enforce duties indicated by man's mental constitution. Observe 唯 is 3rd tone, = "yes." Some say that 門人 must mean Tsêng's own disciples, and that, had they been those of Confucius, we should have read 弟子. The criticism cannot be depended on. 而已矣 is a very emphatic "and nothing more." ↩

How righteousness and selfishness distinguish the superior man and the small man. ↩

喻 = 曉, "to understand." 於 is here to be dwelt on, and may be compared with the Hebrew eth. ↩

The lessons to be learned from observing mean of different characters. ↩

Of the final particles 焉 and 也, it is said, 二字頗有抑揚警醒意, "the two characters have something of a repressive, expansive, warning force." Ho Yen's text has a 者 after the second 賢 which is not necessary. ↩

How a son may remonstrate with his parents on their faults. ↩

See the

禮記, XI i 15

. 幾, the 1st tone, "mildly," = the 下氣, 怡色, 柔聲 of the 内則. 不違 is not abandoning his purpose of remonstrance, and not as 包咸 says in the comment given by Ho Yen, 不敢違父母意, "not daring to go against the mind of his parents." 勞 = "toiled and pained," what the 内則 says, 撻之流血, "should they beat him till the blood flows." ↩

A son ought not to go to a distance where he will not able to pay the due services to his parents. ↩

方 = 一定向, "a fixed direction or quarter," whence he may be recalled, if necessary. ↩

A repetition of part of

I xi

. ↩

What effect the age of parents should have on their children. ↩

知, it is said, conveys here 念念不忘意, "the meaning of unforgetting thoughtfulness. ↩

The virtue of the ancients seen in their slowness to speak. ↩

Observe the force of the two 之—"The not coming forth of the words of the ancients was shame about the not coming up to them of their actions." ↩

Advantage of caution. ↩

Collie's version, which I have adopted, is here happy. 約, see

chap. ii

. The "binding" here is of one's self, self-restraint, = "caution." 失之, "loses it," 之 referring to whatever business the cautious may be engaged in. 之, after an active verb, often makes it neuter; at least, a neuter verb renders the expression best in English. ↩

Rule of the Chün-tzŭ about his words and actions. ↩

The virtuous are not left alone:—An encouragement to virtue. ↩

孤, "fatherless;" here = solitary, friendless. 德不孤 = 德無孤立之理, "it is not the nature of virtue to be left to stand along." 鄰, see

chap. i

; here generally used for friends, associates of like mind. ↩

A lesson to counsellors and friends. ↩

數, the 4th tone, read shu, "frequently," understood here in reference to remonstrating or reproving. 斯 = "this," "this leads to," or "thereon is." ↩

Heading of this book.—公冶長第五. Kung-yeh Chʽang, the surname and name of the first individual spoken of in it, heads this Book, which is chiefly occupied with the judgement of the sage on the character of several of his disciples and others. As the decision frequently turns on their being possessed of that jên, or perfect virtue, which is so conspicuous in the last Book, this is the reason, it is said, why the one immediately follows the other. As Tzŭ-kung appears in the Book several times, some have fancied that it was compiled by his disciples. ↩

Confucius in marriage-making was guided by character and not by fortune. ↩

Of Kung-yeh Chʽang, though the son-in-law of Confucius, nothing certain is known, and his tablet is only 3rd on the west, among the οί πολλοί. Silly legends are told of his being put in prison from his bringing suspicion on himself by his knowledge of the language of birds. Chu Hsi approves the interpretation of 縲 as meaning "a black rope," with which criminals were anciently bound (絏) in prison. 妻 and in

chap. 2

, the 3rd tone, "to wive," "to give a wife to one." 子, in both this and the next chapter, = "a daughter." Confucius's brother would be the cripple Mêng-pʽi;—[SEE P.58.] ↩

Nan Jung, another of the disciples, is now 4th, east, in the outer hall. The discussions about who he was, and whether he is to be identified with 南宮适, and several other aliases, are very perplexing. 廢, "to lay, or be laid aside," from office. 戮, "to put to death," has also the lighter meaning of "disgrace." We cannot tell whether Confucius is giving his impression of Jung's character, or referring to events that had taken place. ↩

The Chün-tzŭ formed by intercourse with other Chün-tzŭ. ↩

Tzŭ-chien, by surname 宓 (= 虙, and said to be i.q. 伏), and named 不齊, appears to have been of some note among the disciples of Confucius as an administrator, though his tablet is now only 2nd, west, in the outer hall. See the

Narratives of the School, chap. xxxviii

. What chiefly distinguished him, as appears here, was his cultivation of the friendship of men of ability and virtue. 若人 = 若此人, "a man such as this." See the

註疏 in loc.

The first 斯 is "this man;" the second, "this virtue." The paraphrasts complete the last clause thus:—斯將何所取以成斯德乎, "what friends must this man have chosen to complete this virtue!" ↩

Whereto Tzŭ-kung had attained. See

I x

;

II xiii

. ↩

The 瑚璉 were vessels richly adorned, used to contain grain-offerings in the royal ancestral temples. Under the Hsia dynasty they were called, 璉, and 瑚 under the Yin. See the

Li Chi, XII ii

. While the sage did not grant to Tzʽŭ that he was a Chün-tzŭ (

II xii

), he made him "a vessel of honour," valuable and fit for use on high occasions. ↩

Of Jan Yung:—Readiness with the tongue no part of virtue. ↩

冉雍, styled 仲弓, has his tablet the 2nd, on the east, among "the wise ones." His father was a worthless character (see

VI iv

), but he himself was the opposite. 佞 means "ability," generally; then "ability of speech," often, though not here, with the bad sense of artfulness and flattery. ↩

Confucius would not grant that Yung was 仁, but his not being 佞 was in his favour rather than otherwise. 口給 (read chi: see

dict.

), "smartnesses of speech." 焉 is here "why," rather than "how." The first 焉用仁 is a general statement, not having special reference to Jan Yung. In the

註疏

, 不知其仁焉用佞 is read as one sentence:—"I do not know how the virtuous should also use readiness of speech." ↩

Chʽi-tiao Kʽai's opinion of the qualifications necessary to taking office. ↩

Chʽi-tiao, now 6th, on the east, in the outer hall, was styled 子若. His name originally was 啟, changed into 開 on the accession of the emperor 孝景, BC 156, whose name was also 啟. ↩

The difficulty is with 斯—what does it refer to? and with 信—what is its force? In the chapter about the disciples in the 家語, it is said that Kʽai was reading in the Shu-ching, when Confucius spoke to him about taking office, and he pointed to the book, or some particular passage in it, saying "I am not yet able to rest in the assurance of (信 = 真知確見) this." It may have been so. Obs. the force of the 之 ↩

Confucius proposing to withdraw from the world:—A lesson to Tzŭ-lu ↩

Tzŭ-lu supposed his master really meant to leave the world, and the idea of floating along the coasts pleased his ardent temper. But Confucius only expressed in this way his regret at the backwardness of men to receive his doctrines. 無所取材 is difficult of interpretation. Chu Hsi takes 材 as being for 裁, "to cut out clothes," "to estimate, discriminate," and hence the meaning in the translation. 鄭玄, keeping the meaning of 材, explains—無所取於桴材, = "my meaning is not to be found in the raft." Another old writer makes 材 = 哉, and putting a stop at 勇 explains—"Yu is fond of daring; he cannot go beyond himself to find my meaning." ↩

Of Tzŭ-lu, Tzŭ-yu, and Tzŭ-hua. ↩

孟武伯, see

II vi

. ↩

千乘之國, see

I v

. ↩

賦, properly "revenues," "taxes," but the quota of soldiers contributed being regulated by the amount of the revenue, the term is used here for the forces, or military levies. ↩

求 see

III vi

. ↩

百乘之家, in opposition to 千乘之國, was the secondary fief, the territory appropriated to the highest nobles or officers in a 國 or state, supposed also to comprehend 1000 families 爲之宰, "to be its governor." This is a peculiar idiom, something like the double object in Latin. ↩

Chʽih, surnamed 公西, and styled 子華, having now the 14th place, west, in the outer hall, was famous among the disciples for his knowledge of rules of ceremony, and those especially relating to dress and intercourse. ↩

朝, in 2nd tone. 賓 and 客 may be distinguished, the former indicating neighbouring princes visiting the court; the latter, ministers and officers of the State present as guests. ↩

Superiority of Yen Hui to Tzŭ-kung. ↩

望, "to look to," "to look up to," here = 比, "to compare with." "One" is the beginning of numbers, and "ten" the completion; hence the meaning of 聞一以知十, as in the translation. ↩

與 = 許, "to allow," "to grant to." Ho Yeh gives here the comm. of 包咸 (about AD 50), who interprets strangely,—"I and you are both not equal to him," saying that Confucius thus comforted Tzŭ-kung. ↩

The idleness of Tsai Yü and its reproof. ↩

於予與, "In the case of Yü!" 與 has here the force of an exclamation; so below. 誅, a strong term, to mark the severity of the reproof. ↩

子曰 is superfluous. The characters were probably added by a transcriber. If not, they should head another chapter. Tsai Yü,—the same as Tsai Wo in

III xxi

. ↩

Unbending virtue cannot co-exist with indulgence of the passions. ↩

Shên Chʽêng (there are several aliases, but they are disputed) was one of the minor disciples, of whom little or nothing is known. He was styled 子周, and his place is 31st, east, in the outer ranges. 剛 is to be understood with reference to virtues. 慾 is 情所好, "what the passions love," "lusts." 焉得 are said to = 不是, and not 不能. I have translated accordingly. ↩

The difficulty of attaining to the not wishing to do to others as we wish them not to do to us. It is said—此章見無我之不易及, "this chapter shows that the no I (freedom from selfishness) is not easily reached." ↩

In the

中庸, XIII iii

, it is said—施諸己而不願亦勿施諸人, "what you do not like when done to yourself, do not do to others." The difference between it and the sentence here is said to be that of 恕, "reciprocity;" and 仁, "benevolence," or the highest virtue, apparent in the adverbs 勿 and 無, the one prohibitive, and the other a simple, unconstrained negation. The golden rule of the Gospel is higher than both,—"Do ye unto others as ye would that others should do unto you." 諸 = 於; 加諸, or 加於, "to add upon," "to do to." ↩

The gradual way in which Confucius communicated his doctrines. So the lesson of this chapter is summed up, but there is hardly another more perplexing to a translator. ↩

文章 is the common name for essays, elegant literary compositions. Of course that meaning is out of the question. Whatever is figured and brilliant is 文; whatever is orderly and defined is 章. The comm., accordingly, make 文 to be the deportment and manners of the sage, and 章 his ordinary discourses, but 聞 is an inappropriate term with reference to the former. These things, however, were level to the capacities of the disciples generally, and they had the benefit of them. As to his views about man's nature, as the gift of Heaven, and the way of Heaven generally; these be only communicated to those who were prepared to receive them, and Tzŭ-kung is supposed to have expressed himself thus, after being on some occasion so privileged. ↩

The ardour of Tzŭ-lu in practising the Master's instructions. ↩

The concluding 唯恐有聞 is to be completed 唯恐復有所聞, as in the translation. ↩

An example of the principle on which honorary posthumous titles were conferred. ↩

文, corresponding nearly to our "accomplished," was the posthumous title given to 子圉, an officer of the same surname of the State of Wei, and a contemporary of Confucius. Many of his actions had been of a doubtful character, which made Tzŭ-kung stumble at the application to him of so honourable an epithet. But Confucius shows that, whategver he might otherwise have been, he had those qualities which justified his eing so denominated. The rule for posthumous titles in China has been, and is, very much—"De mortuis nil nisi bonum." ↩

The excellent qualities of Tzŭ-chʽan. ↩

Tzŭ-chʽan, named 公孫僑, was the chief minister of the State of Chêng (鄭), the ablest, perhaps, and most upright of all the statesmen among Confucius's contemporaries. The sage wept when he heard of his death. The old interpreters take 使 in the sense of "employing," but it seems to express more, and = "ordering," "regulating." ↩

How to maintain friendship. ↩

"Familiarity breeds contempt," and with contempt friendship ends. It was not so with Yen Pʽing, another of the worthies of Confucius's time. He was a principal minister of Chʽi (齊), by name 嬰. Pʽing (= "Ruling and averting calamity") was his posthumous title. If we were to render 仲, the name would be "Yen Pʽing, secundus." The antecedent to 之 is 人. ↩

The superstition of Tsang Wên. Tsang Wên (Wên is the honorary epithet, and 仲, see

last chapter

) had been a great officer in Lu, and left a reputation for wisdom, which Confucius did not think was deserved. His full name was 臧孫辰. He was descended from the duke 孝 (BC 794–767), whose son was styled 子臧. This Tsang was taken by his descendants as their surname. Such was one of the ways in which surnames were formed among the Chinese. ↩

蔡, "a large tortoise," so called, because the State of Tsʽai was famous for its tortoises. 居 is sued as an active verb, = 藏. The 節 = 柱頭斗棋, "the capitals of the pillars." The 梲 may be seen in any Chinese house where the whole structure of the roof is displayed, and these small pillars are very conspicuous. The old critics make the keeping such a tortoise an act of usurpation on the part of Tsang Wên. Chu Hsi finds the point of Confucius's words in the keeping it in such a style. ↩

The praise of perfect virtue is not to be lightly accorded. ↩

Ling-yin, lit. "good corrector," was the name given to the chief minister of Chʽu (楚). 尹 is still applied to officers; e.g. the prefect of a department is called 府尹. Tzŭ-wên, surnamed 鬬, and named 穀於菟 ("suckled by a tiger"), had been noted for the things mentioned by Tzŭ-chang, but the sage would not concede that he was therefore 仁. ↩

崔 was a great officer of Chʽi. Yen Pʽing (

chap. xvi

) distinguished himself on the occasion of the murder (BC 547) here referred to. Chʽên Wên was likewise an officer of Chʽi. 之一邦, 之 is a verb, = 往. 乘, 4th tone, as in

I vi

, butr with a different meaning, = "a team of four horses." ↩

Prompt decision good. ↩

Wên was the posthumous title of 季行夫, a faithful and disinterested officer of Lu. 三, 4th tone, "three times," but some say it = 二三, "again and again." Comp. Robert Hall's remark—"In matters of conscience first thoughts are best." ↩

The uncommon but admirable stupidity of Ning Wu ↩

Nine Wu (武, honorary epithet; see

II vi

) was an officer of Wei in the time of Wên (BC 660–635). In the first part of his official life the State was quiet and prosperous, and he "wisely" acquitted himself of his duties. Afterwards came confusion. The prince was driven from the throne, and Ning Yü (俞 was his name) might, like other wise men, have retired from the danger. But he "foolishly," as it seemed, chose to follow the fortunes of his prince, and yet adroitly brought it about in the end, that the prince was reinstated and order restored. ↩

The anxiety of Confucius about the training of his disciples. ↩

The generosity of Po-i and Shu-chʽi and its effects. ↩

These were ancient worthies of the closing period of the Shang dynasty. Compare

Mencius, II i ch. 2, et al.

They were brothers, sons of the king of Ku-chu (孤竹), named respectively 允 and 致. I and Chʽi are their honorary epithets, and 伯 and 叔 only indicate their relation to each other as elder and younger. Po-i Shu-chʽi, however, are in effect their names in the mouths and writings of the Chinese. Ku-chu was a small State, included in the present department of 永平, in Pei-chih-li. Their father left his kingdom to Shu-chʽi, who refused to take the place of his elder brother. Po-i in turn declined the throne; so they both abandoned it, and retired into obscurity. When king Wu was taking his measures against the tyrant Chou, they made their appearance, and remonstrated against his course. Finally, they died of hunger, rather than live under the new dynasty. They were celebrated for their purity, and aversion to men whom they considered bad, but Confucius here bring out their generosity. 怨是用希 = 怨是以希, "Resentments thereby were few." ↩

Small meannesses inconsistent with uprightness. ↩

It is implied that Kao gave the vinegar as from himself. He was a native of Lu, with a reputation better than he deserved to have. ↩

Praise of sincerity, and of Tso Chʽiu-ming. ↩

巧言令色, see

I iii

. 足恭, "excessive respect," 足 being in 4th tone read chü. Some of the old commentators, keeping the usual tone and meaning of 足, interpret the phrase of movements of the "feet" to indicate respect. The discussions about Tso Chʽiu-ming are endless. See

拓餘説, I xxx

. It is sufficient for us to rest in the judgement of the commentator 程, that "he was an ancient of reputation." It is not to be received that he was a disciple of COnfucius, the same whose supplement to the Chʽun Chʽiu chronicles the death of the sage, and carries on the history for many subsequent years. 丘 was the name of COnfucius. The Chinese decline pronouncing it, always substituting Mou (某) "such a one," for it. ↩

The different wishes of Yen Yüan, Tzŭ-lu, and Confucius. ↩

盍各言爾至, "why not each tell your will?" ↩

A student is apt to translate—"I should like to have chariots and horses, etc.," but 共 is the important word in the paragraph, and under the regimen of 願 on to 之, and removing the comma at 共, read 共敝 together, but this construction is not so good. ↩

In Ho Yen's compilation 施勞 is interpreted, "not to impose troublesome affairs on others." Chu Hsi's view is better. ↩

信之 = 與之以信, "To be with them with sincerity."—The Master and the disciples, it is said, agreed in being devoid of selfishness. Hui's however, was seen in a higher style of mind and object than Yu's. In the sage there was an unconsciousness of self, and without any effort he proposed acting in regard to his classification of men just as they ought severally to be acted to. ↩

A lament over men's persistence in error. ↩

The 乎 has an exclamatory force. 訟, "to litigate." 内自訟者, "one who bring himself before the bar of his conscience." The remark affirms a fact, inexplicable on Confucius's view of the nature of man. But perhaps such an exclamation should not be pressed too closely. ↩

The humble claim of Confucius for himself. ↩

邑 (人聚會之稱也) is "the designation of the place where men are collected together," and may be applied from a hamlet upwards to a city. 忠 = 忠厚, "honourable," "substantial." Confucius thus did not claim higher natural and moral qualities than others, but sought to perfect himself by learning. ↩

Heading of this Book.—雍也第六. "There is Yung!" commences the first chapter, and stands as the title of the Book. Its subjects are much akin to those of the preceding Book, and therefore, it is said, they are in juxtaposition. ↩

The characters of Jan Yung and Tzŭ-sang Po-tzŭ, as regards their aptitude for government. ↩

Yung,

V iv

, 可使南面, "might be employed with his face to the south." In China the sovereign sits facing the south. So did the princes of the States in their several courts in Confucius's time. An explanation of the practice is attempted in the

Yi-ching, 説卦, chap. ix

, 離也者明也, 萬物皆相見, 南方之卦也, 聖人南面而聽天下, 向明而治蓋取此也, "The diagram Li conveys the idea of brightness, when all things are exhibited to one another. It is the diagram of the south. The custom of the sages (i.e. monarchs) to sit with their faces to the south, and listen to the representations of all in the kingdom, governing towards the bright region, was taken from this." ↩

Chung-kung was the designation of Jan Yung, see

V iv

. ↩

簡 has here substantially the same meaning as in

V xxi

, = 不煩, "not troubling," i.e. one's self about small matters. With reference to that place, however, the dict., after the old comm., explains it by 大, "great." Of Tzŭ-sang Po-tzŭ we know nothing certain but waht is here stated. Chu Hsi seems to be wrong in approving the identification of him with Tzŭ-sang Hu of

Chuang-tzŭ, VI par. 11

. ↩

居敬, "to dwell in respect," to have the mind imbued with it. 敬 = 敬事 as in

I v

. ↩

The rarity of a true love to learn. Hui's superiority to the other disciples. ↩

In 有顔回者, 者 = "that."—"There was that Yen Hui." ↩

"He did not transfer his anger," i.e.his anger was no tumultuary passion in the mind, but was excited by some specific cause, to which alone it was directed. ↩

短命死矣 = "he died an early death," but 命 conveys also the idea in the translation. The two last clauses are completed thus:—今也, 則亡 (read as, and = 無) 是人, 未聞如是之好學者也. ↩

Discrimination of Confucius in rewarding or salarying officers. ↩

Kung-hsi Chʽih, styled Tzŭ-hua;—see

V vii 3

. 使, in 4th tone, "to commission," or "to be commissioned." Chu Hsi says the commission was a private one from Confucius, but this is not likely. The old interpretation makes it a public one from the court of Lu; see

四書改錯, III ix

. ↩

冉子, "the disciple Jan;" see

III vi

. Jan is here styled 子, like 有子, in

I ii

, but only in narrative, not as introducing any wise utterance. ↩

A fu contained 6 tou (斗) and 4 shêng (升), or 64 shêng. ↩

The yü contained 160 shêng, and the ping 16 hu (斛), or 1600 shêng. A shêng of the present day is about one-fourth less than an English pint. ↩

The 之 in 吾聞之 refers to what follows. ↩

In Ho Yen's edition, another chapter commences here. Yüan Ssŭ, named 憲, is now the 3rd, east, in the outer hall of the temples. He was noted for his pursuit of truth, and carelessness of worldly advantages. After the death of Confucius, he withdrew into retirement in Wei. It is related by Chuang-tzŭ that Tzŭ-kung, high in official station, came one day in great style to visit him. Ssŭ received him in a tattered coat, and Tzŭ-king asking him if he were ill, he replied, "I have heard that to have no money is to be poor, and that to study truth and not be able to find it is to be ill." The answer sent Tzŭ-kung away in confusion. The 900 measures (whatever they were) was the proper allowance for an officer in Ssŭ's station. 爲之宰, see

V vii

, though it is not easy to give the 之 the same reference here as in that passage. ↩

According to ancient statutes, a lin, a li, a hsiang, and a tang, had each their specific number of component families, but the meaning is no more than—"the poor about you." 乎 makes the remark = "may you not, etc." ↩

The vices of a father should not discredit a virtuous son. ↩

The father of Chung-kung (see

V ii

) was a man of bad character, and some would have visited this upon his son, which drew forth Confucius's remark. The rules of the Chou dynasty required that sacrificial victims should be red, and have good horns. An animal with those qualities, though it might spring from one not possessing them, would certainly not be unacceptable on that account to the spirits sacrificed to. I translate 子 by "calf," but it is not implied that the victim was young. 舍, the 3rd tone, = 捨, "to lay aside," "to put away." 其舍諸 = 其舍之乎. ↩

The superiority of Hui to the other disciples. ↩

It is impossible to say whether we should translate here about Hui in the past or present tense. 違 is not 違背, "to oppose," but 違去, "to depart from." 日月至, "come to it," i.e. the line of perfect virtue, "in the course of a day, or a month." 日月 may also be, "for a day or a month." So in the

註疏

. ↩

The qualities of Tzŭ-lu, Tzŭ-kung, and Tzŭ-yu, and their competency to assist in government. ↩

The prince is called 爲政者, "the doer of government;" his ministers and officers are styled 從政者, "the followers of government." 也與 and 何有 are set, the one expression against the other, the former indicating a doubt of the competency of the disciples, the latter affirming their more than competency. ↩

Min Tzŭ-chʽien refuses to serve the Chi family ↩

The tablet of Tzŭ-chʽien(his name was 損) is now the first on the east among "the wise ones" of the temple. He was among the foremost of the disciples. Confucius praises his filial piety, and we see here, how he could stand firm in his virtue, and refuse the proffers of the powerful but unprincipled families of his time. 使 = 使人來召, in the translation, and in 復 (fu, 4th tone) 我者, we must similarly understand 復來召我者. 費, read Pi, was a place belonging to the Chi family. Its name is still preserved in 費縣 in the department of 沂州, in Shan-tung. The Wên stream divided Chʽi and Lu. Tzŭ-chʽien threatens, if he should be troubled again, to retreat to Chʽi, where the Chi family could not reach him. ↩

Lament of Confucius over the mortal sickness of Po-niu. ↩

Po-niu, "elder or uncle Niu," was the denomination of 冉耕, one of the disciples of the sage. In the old interpretation, his sickness is said to have been 惡疾, "an evil disease," by which name leprosy, called 癞, is intended, though that character is now employed for "itch." Suffering from such a disease, Po-niu would not see people, and Confucius took his hand through the window. A different explanation is given by Chu Hsi. He says that sick persons were usually placed on the north side of the apartment; but when the prince visited them, in order that he might appear to them with his face to the south (see

chap. i

), they were moved to the south. On this occasion, Po-niu's friends wanted to receive Confucius after this royal fashion, which he avoided by not entering the house. 亡之 = "It is killing him." 夫, the 2nd tone, generally an initial particle = "now." It is here final, and = "alas!" ↩

The happiness of Hui independent of his poverty. ↩

The 簞 was simply a piece of the stem of a bamboo, and the 瓢 half of a gourd cut into two. 食, see

II viii

. The eulogy turns much on 其 in 其樂, as opposed to 其憂, "his joy," the delight which he had in the doctrines of his master, contrasted with the grief others would have felt under such poverty. ↩

A high aim and perseverance proper to a student. ↩

Confucius would not admit Chʽiu's apology for not attempting more than he did. "Give over in the middle of the way," i.e. they go as long and as far as they can, and are pursuing when they stop. ↩

How learning should be pursued. ↩

君子 and 小人 here = adjectives, qualifying 儒. The 君子, it is said, learns 爲己 for his own real improvement and from duty; the 小人, 爲人, "for men," with a view to their opinion, and for his own material benefit. We should hardly have judged such a counsel necessary for Tzŭ-hsia. ↩

The character of Tan-tʽai Mieh-ming. ↩

The chapter shows, according to Chinese commentators, the advantage to people in authority of their having good men about them. In this way after their usual fashion, they seek for a profound meaning in the remark of Confucius. Tan-tʽai Mieh-ming, who was styled 子羽, has his tablet the 2nd, east, outside the hall. The accounts of him are conflicting. According to one, he was very good-looking, while another says he was so bad-looking that Confucius at first formed an unfavourable opinion of him, an error which he afterwards confessed on Mieh-ming's becoming eminent. He travelled sourthwards with not a few followers, and places near Su-chou and elsewhere retain names indicative of his presence. 焉爾乎, three particles coming together, are said to indicate the slow and deliberate manner in which the sage spoke. 滅明者, compare 顔回者 in

chap. ii

. 室 is said to = 公堂. ↩

The virtue of Mêng Chih-fan in concealing his merit. ↩

But where was his virtue in deviating from the truth? And how could Confucius commend him for doing so? These questions have never troubled the commentators, nor is it wise to bring a railing accusation against the sage for his words here. Mêng Chih-fan, named 側, was an officer of Lu. The defeat referred to was in the eleventh year of duke Ai. To lead the van of an army is called 啟, to bring up the rear is 殿. In retreat the rear is of course the place of honour. ↩

The degeneracy of the age esteeming glibness of tongue and beauty of person. ↩

祝, "to pray," "prayers;" here, in the concrete, the officer charged with the prayers in the ancestral temple. I have coined the word litanist to come as near to the meaning as possible. The Tʽo was an officer of the State of Wei, styled 子魚. Prince Chao had been guilty of incest with his half-sister Nan-tzŭ (see

chap. xxvi

), and afterwards, when she was married to the duke Ling of Wei, he served as an officer there, carrying on his wickedness. He was celebrated for his beauty of person. 而 is a simple connective, = 與, and the 不 is made to belong to both clauses. The old commentators construe differently:—"If a man have not the speech of Tʽo, though he may have the beauty of Chao, etc.," making the degeneracy of the age all turn on its fondness for specious talk. This cannot be right. ↩

A lament over the waywardness of men's conduct. ↩

斯道, "these ways," in a moral sense;—not deep doctrines, but rules of life. ↩

The equal blending of solid excellence and ornamental accomplishments in a complete character. ↩

史, "a historian," an officer of importance in China. The term, however, is to be understood here of "a clerk," one that is of a class sharp and well informed, but insincere. ↩

Life without uprightness in not true life, and cannot be calculated on. ↩

"No more serious warning than this," says one commentator, "was ever addressed to men by Confucius." A distinction is made by Chu Hsi and others between the two 生;—the 1st is 始生, 生存, "preservation in life." 人之生也直, "The being born of man is upright," which may mean either that man at his birth is upright, or that he is born for uprightness. I prefer the latter view. 罔之生也, "The living without it," if we take 罔 = 無, or "to defame it," if 罔 = 誣. We long here as elsewhere for more perspicuity and fuller development of view. Without uprightness the end of man's existence isnot fulfilled, but his preservation in such case is not merely a fortunate accident. ↩

Different stages of attainment. ↩

The four 之 have all one reference, which must be 道 or 理, the subject spoken of. ↩

Teachers must be guided in communicating knowledge by the susceptivity of the learners. ↩

In 以上, 上 is read 2nd tone, a verbal word, and not the prep. "upon," so the 下 in 以下 is also verbal as in

III vii

. The 中人, "or mediocre people," may have all classes of subjects announced to them, I suppose. 語 is in the 4th tone, "to tell to." ↩

Chief elements in wisdom and virtue. ↩

Fan Chʽih,

II v

. ↩

The modern comm. take 民 here as = 人, and 民之義 as = 人道之宜, "what is right according to the principles of humanity." With some hesitation I have assented to this view, though 民 properly means "the multitude," "the people," and the old interpreters explain—"Strive to perfect the righteousness of the people." ↩

We may suppose from the second clause that Fan Chʽih was striving after what was uncommon and super human. For a full exhibition of the phrase 鬼神, see

中庸, XVI

. Here it = "spiritual beings," manes and others. 遠, the 4th tone; 遠之, "keep at a distance from them," not "keep them at a distance." The sage's advice there is—"attend to what are plainly human duties, and do not be superstitious." 先 and 後 are, as frequently, verbs, "put first," "put last." the old interpreters take them differently, but not so well. ↩

Contrasts of the wise and the virtuous. ↩

The two first 樂 are read yao, 4th tone, = 喜好, "to find pleasure in." The wise or knowing are active and restless, like the waters of a stream, ceaselessly flowing and advancing. the virtuous are tranquil and firm, like the stable mountains. The pursuit of knowledge brings joy. The life of the virtuous may be expected to glide calmly on and long. After all, the saying is not very comprehensible. ↩

The condition of the States Chʽi and Lu. ↩

Chʽi and Lu were both within the present Shan-tung. Chʽi lay along the coast on the north, embracing the present department of 青州 and other territory. Lu was on the south, the larger portion of it being formed by the present department of 兗州. At the rise of the Chou dynasty, king Wu invested Lü Shang, a counsellor of king Wu and the commander of his army, with the principality of Chʽi. King Wu at his first interview with Lü Shang addressed him as Tʽai-kung Wang, "Grandfather Hope," the man long looked for in his family. This successor, king Chʽêng, constituted the son of his uncle, the famous duke of Chou, prince of Lu. In Confucius's time, Chʽi had degenerated more than Lu. 道 is 先王盡善盡美之道, "the entirely good and admirable ways of the former kings." ↩

The name without the reality is folly. ↩

This was spoken (see the

註疏

) with reference to the governments of the time, retaining ancient names without ancient principles. The 觚 was a drinking-vessel; others say a wooden tablet. the latter was a later use of the term. It was made with corners as appears from the composition of the character, which is formed from 角, "a horn," "a sharp corner." In Confucius's time the form was changed, while the name was kept.—See the translation in

Williams's Syllabic Dictionary

, under syllable ku. ↩

The benevolent exercise their benevolence with prudence. ↩

Tsai Wo could see no limitation to acting on the impulses of benevolence. We are not to suppose with modern scholars that he wished to show that benevolence was impracticable. 雖 belongs to the whole following clause, especially to the mention of a well. The 仁 of 仁焉 should be 人. This happy correction of the text is due to a contemporary and teacher of Chu Hsi whom he calls Liu Pʽing-chün. 其...也 indicate some doubt in Wo's mind. Observe the hophal force of 逝 and 陷. ↩

The happy effect of learning and propriety combined. ↩

君子 has here its lighter meaning, = "the student of what is right and true." The 之 in 約之 we naturally refer to 文, but comparing

IX x 2

—約我以禮—we may assent to the observation that 我指己身, "me refers to the learner's own person." See note on

IV xxiii

. 畔, "the boundary of a field;" also, "to overstep a boundary." 矣夫, as in

V xxvi

, but the force here is more "ah!" than "alas!" ↩

Confucius vindicates himself for visiting the unworthy Nan-tzŭ. ↩

Nan-tzŭ was the wife of the duke of Wei, and half-sister of the prince Chao, mentioned in

chap. xiv

. Her lewd character was well known, and hence Tzŭ-lu was displeased, thinking an interview with her was disgraceful to the master. Great pains are taken to explain the incident. "Nan-tzŭ," says one, "sought the interview from the stirrings of her natural conscience." "It was a rule," says another, "that stranger officers in a State should visit the prince's wife." "Nan-tzŭ," argues a third, "had all influence with her husband, and Confucius wished to get currency by her means for his doctrine." Whether 矢 is to be understood in the sense of "to swear," = 誓, or "to make a declaration," = 陳, is much debated. Evidently the thing is an oath, or solemn protestation against the suspicions of Tzŭ-lu. 説, as in

I i 1

. ↩

The defective practice of the people in Confucius's time. See the

Chung Yung

. ↩

The true nature and art of virtue. ↩

施, the 4th tone, "to confer benefits." ↩

聖乎,—乎 is said to be "a particle of doubt and uncertainty," but it is rather the interrogative affirmation of opinion. ↩

Tzŭ-kung appears to have thought that great doings were necessary to virtue, and propounds a case which would transcend the achievements of the ancient model sovereigns Yao and Shun. From such extravagant views the Master recalls him ↩

This is the description of 仁者之心體, "the mind of the perfectly virtuous man," as void of all selfishness. ↩

It is to be wished that the idea intended by 能者近取譬 had been more clearly expressed. Still we seem to have here a near approach to a positive enunciation of "the golden rule." ↩

Heading of this Book.—述而第七, "A transmitter, and—Book VII." We have in this Book much information of a personal character about Confucius, both from his own lips and from the descriptions of his disciples. The two preceding Books treat of the disciples and other worthies, and here, in contrast with them, we have the sage himself exhibited. ↩

Confucius disclaims being an originator or maker.↩

述 = 傳舊而已, "simply to hand down the old." Commentators say the the Master's language here is from his extreme humility. But we must hold that it expresses his true sense of his position and work. Who the individual called endearingly "our old Pʽêng was, can hardly be ascertained. Some make 老彭 to be Lao-tzŭ, the founder of the Tao sect, and the other that 彭祖, of whom we read much in

Chuang-tzŭ

. A Pʽêng Hsien appears in the

Li Sao, st. 21

, where Chu Hsi describes him as a worthy of the Yin (or Shang) dynasty, and he supposes him to the the Lao Pʽêng here. ↩

Confucius's humble estimate of himself. ↩

識, here by most scholars read chih, 4th tone, "to remember." 之 refers, it is said, to 理, "principles," the subjects of the silent observation and reflection. 何有於我哉, cannot be,—"what difficulty do these occasion me?" but = 何者能有於我, as in the translation. "The language," says Chu Hsi, "is that of humility upon humility." Some insert, in their explanation, 此外 before 何—"Besides these, what is there in me?" But this is quite arbitrary. The profession may be inconsistent with what we find in other passage, but the in consistency must stand rather than violence be done to the language. Ho Yen gives the singular exposition of 鄭康成 (about AD 150–200)—"Other men have not these things, I only have them." ↩

Confucius's anxiety about his self-cultivation:—Another humble estimate of himself. ↩

Here again commentators find only the expressions of humility, but there can be no reason why we should not admit that Confucius was anxious lest these things, which are only put forth as possibilities, should become in his case actual facts. 講 is in the sense explained in this dictionary by the terms 習 and 究, "practising," "examining." ↩

The manner of Confucius when unoccupied. ↩

The first clause, which is the subject of the other two, is literally—"The Master's dwelling at ease." Observe 燕, in the 4th tone; 夭, in the 1st; 如, as in

III xxiii

. ↩

How this disappointment of Confucius's hopes affected even his dreams. ↩

周公 is now to all intents a proper name, but the characters mean "the duck of Chou." Chou was the name of the seat of the family from which the dynasty so called sprang, and, on the enlargement of this territory, king Wên divided the original seat between his son 旦 (Tan) and the minister 奭 (Shih). Tan was Chou-kung, in wisdom and politics, what his elder brother, the first sovereign, Wu, was in arms. Confucius had longed to bring the principles and institutions of Chou-kung into practice, and in his earlier years, while hope animated him, had often dreamt of the former sage. The original territory of Chou was what is now the district of Qishan (岐山), department of Fengxiang in Shaanxi. ↩

Rules for the full maturing of character. ↩

德 might be translated virtue, but 仁 = "perfect virtue" following, we require another term. ↩

游, "to ramble for amusement," here = "to seek recreation." 藝, see note on 文, in

I vi

. A full enumeration makes "six arts," viz. ceremonies, music, archery, charioteering, the study of characters or language, and figures or arithmetic. The ceremonies were ranged in five classes: lucky or sacrifices; unlucky or those of mourning; military; those of host and guest; and festive. Music required the study of the music of Huang-ti, of Yao, of Shun, of Shun, Tʽang, and of Wu. Archery had a fivefold classification. Charioteering had the same. The study of the characters required the examination of them to determine whether there predominated in their formation resemblance to the object, combination of ideas, indication of properties, a phonetic principles, a principles of contrariety, or metaphorical accommodation. Figures were managed according to nine rules, as the object was the measurement of land, capacity, etc. These six subjects were the business of the highest and most liberal education, but we need not suppose that Confucius had them all in view here. ↩

The readiness of Confucius to impart instruction. ↩

It was the rule anciently that when one party waited on another, he should carry some present or offering with him. Pupils did so when they first waited on their teacher. Of such offerings, one of the lowest was a bundle of strips of 脩, "dried flesh." The wages of a teacher are now called 脩金, "the money of the dried flesh." However small the offering brought to the sage, let him only see the indication of a wish to learn, and he imparted his instructions. 以上 may be translated "upward," i.e. "to such a man and others with larger gifts," 上 being in the 3rd tone; or the character may be understood in the sense of "coming to my instructions." I prefer the former interpretation. ↩

Confucius required a real desire and ability in his disciples. ↩

The last chapter tells of the sage's readiness to teach; this shows that he did not teach where his teaching was likely to prove of no avail. 悱, in the comm. and dict., is explained 口欲言而未能之貌, "the appearance of one with mouth wishing to speak and yet not able to do so." This being the meaning, we might have expected the character to be 啡. 反, "to turn," is explained 還以相證之義, "going round for mutual testimony." 不復 = 不復有所告, "I tell him nothing more." ↩

Confucius's sympathy with mourners. ↩

The weeping is understood to be on occasion of offering his condolences to a mourner, which was "a rule of propriety." ↩

The attainments of Hui like those of Confucius. The excessive boldness of Tzŭ-lu. ↩

In 用之, 舍之, 之 is explained by 我, but we have seen that 之 following active verbs imparts to them a sort of neuter signification. 用之 = "used." 舍之 = "neglected." ↩

A chün, according to the 周禮, consisted of 12,500 men. The royal forces consisted of six such bodies, and those of a great State of three. ↩

暴虎馮河, see Shih-ching, II v 1 st. 6. 懼 does not indicate timidity, but solicitude.—Tzŭ-lu, it would appear, was jealous of the praise conferred on Hui, and, pluming himself on his bravery, put in for a share of the Master's approbation. But he only brought on himself this rebuke. ↩

The uncertainty and folly of the pursuit of riches. ↩

It occurs to a student to understand the first clause—"If it be proper to search for riches," and the third—"I will do it." But the translation is according to the modern commentaries, and the conclusion agrees better with it. In explaining 執鞭之士, some refer us to the attendants who cleared the street with their whips when the prince went abroad, but we need not seek any particular allusion of the kind. Observe 而 = 若, "if," and then 如 = "since." Still we may bring out the meaning from 而 taken in its usual significance of "and." In this construction the previous 富 = "given riches," and 而可求 = "and such as can surely be found."—An objection to the pursuit of wealth may be made on the ground of righteousness, or on that of its uncertainty. It is the latter on which Confucius here rests. ↩

What things Confucius was particularly careful about. ↩

齊, read chai, and = 齋, "to fast," or, rather, denoting the whole religious adjustment, enjoined before the offering of sacrifice, and extending over the ten days previous to the great sacrificial seasons. 齊 means "to equalize" (see

II iii

), and the effect of those previous exercises was 齊不齊以致齊, "to adjust what was not adjusted, so as to produce a perfect adjustment." Sacrifices presented in such a state of mind were sure to e acceptable. Other people, it is said, might be heedless in reference to sacrifice, to war, and to sickness, but not so the sage. ↩

The effect of music on Confucius. ↩

The shao, see

III xxv

. This incident must have happened in the thirty-sixth year of Confucius, when he followed the duke Chao in his flight from Lu to Chʽi. As related in the 史記, Historical Records, before the characters 三月, we have 學之, "he learned it three months," which may relieve us form the necessity of extending the three months over all the time in which he did not know the taste of his food. In Ho Yen's compilation, the 不知 is explained by 忽忘, "he was careless about and forgot." The last clause is also explained there—"I did not think that this music had reached this country of Chʽi." ↩

Confucius did not approve of a son opposing his father. ↩

The eldest so of duke Ling of Wei had planned to kill his mother (? stepmother), the notorious Nan-tzŭ (

VI xxvi

). For this he had to flee the country, and his son, on the death of Ling, became duke (出公), and subsequently oppose his father's attempts to wrest the State from him. This was the matter argued among the disciples,—Was Confucius for (爲, 4th tone) the son, the ruling duke? ↩

In Wei it would not have been according to propriety to speak by name of its ruler, and therefore Tzŭ-kung put the case of Po-i and Shu-chʽi, see

V xxii

. They have given up a throne, and finally their lives, rather than do what they thought wrong, and Confucius fully approving of their conduct, it was plain he could not approve of a son's holding by force what was the rightful inheritance of the father. 求仁而得仁, "They sought for virtue, and they got virtue;" i.e. such was the character of their conduct. ↩

The joy of COnfucius independent of outward circumstances. ↩

飯, in 3rd tone, "a meal;" also, as here, a verb, "to eat." 枕, 4th tone, "to pillow," "to use as a pillow." Critics call attention to 亦, making the sentiment = "My joy is everywhere. It is amid other circumstances. It is also here." 不義云云, = "By unrighteousness I might get riches and honours, but such riches and honours are to me as a floating cloud. It is vain to grasp at them, so uncertain and unsubstantial." ↩

The value which Confucius set upon the study of the Yi. ↩

Chu Hsi supposes that this was spoken when Confucius was about seventy, as he was in his sixty-eighth year when he ceased his wanderings, and settled in Lu to the adjustment and compilation of the Yi and other ching. If the remark be referred to that time, an error may well be found in 五十, for he would hardly be speaking at seventy of having fifty years added to his life. Chu also mentions the report of Liu Pʽing-chün, referred to by him under

V xxiv

, that he had been told of a copy of the Lun Yü, which read 假 for 加, and 卒 for 五十. Amended thus, the meaning would be—"If I had some more years to finish the study of the Yi, etc." Ho Yen interprets the chapter quite differently. Referring to the saying,

II iv 4

, "At fifty, I knew the decree of Heaven," he supposes this to have been spoken when Confucius was forty-seven, and explains—"In a few years more I will be fifty, and have finished the Yi, when I may be without great faults."—One thing remains upon both views:—Confucius never claimed, what his followers do for him, to be a perfect man. ↩

Confucius's most common topics. ↩

書, "The History," i.e. the historical documents which were compiled into the Shu-ching that has come down to us in a mutilated condition. 詩 also, and much more 禮, must not be understood of the now existing Shih-ching and Li Chi. Chu Hsi explains 雅 (3rd tone) by 常, "constantly." The old interpreter Chêng explains it by 正, "correctly,"—"Confucius would speak of the Odes, etc., with attention to the correct enunciation of the characters." This does not seem so good. ↩

Confucius's description of his own character, as being simply a cheerful, earnest learner. ↩

葉 (read shê) was a district of Chʽu (楚), the governor or prefect of which was styled kung, after the usurping fashion of Chʽu. Its name is still preserved in a district of the department of 南陽, in the south of Henan. ↩

云 sometimes finishes a sentence (Prémare, claudit orationem), as here. The 爾 after it 耳, imparting to all the preceding description a meaning indicated by our simply or only. Wang Yin-chih, in his treatise on the particles, gives instances of 云 used as a particle, now initial, now medial, and again final. ↩

Confucius's knowledge not connate, but the result of his study of antiquity. ↩

Here again, according to the commentators, is a wonderful instance of the sage's humility disclaiming what he really had. The comment of a Mr. Yin, subjoined to Chu Hsi's own, is to the effect that the knownledge born with a man is only 義 and 理, while ceremonies, music, names of things, history, etc., must be learned. This would make what we may call connate or innate knowledge the moral sense, and those intuitive principles of reason, on and by which all knowledge is built up. But Confucius could not mean to deny his being possessed of these. "I love antiquity;" i.e. the ancients and all their works. ↩

Subjects avoided by Confucius in his conversation. ↩

亂, "confusion," meaning rebellious disorder, parricide, regicide, and such crimes. Chu Hsi makes 神 here = 鬼神造化之迹, "the mysterious, or spiritual operations apparent in the course of nature." 王肅 (died AD 266), as given by Ho Yen, simply says—鬼神之事, "the affairs of spiritual beings." For an instance of Confucius avoiding such a subject, see

XI xi

. ↩

How a man may find instructors for himself. ↩

三人行, "three men walking;" but it is implied that the speaker is himself one of them. The commentators all take 擇 in the sense of "to distinguish," "to determine."—"I will determine the one who is good, and follow him, etc." I prefer to understand as in the translation. 改之, "change them," i.e. correct them in myself, avoid them. ↩

Confucius calm in danger, through the assurance of having a divine mission. ↩

According to the historical accounts, Confucius was passing through Sung in his way from Wei to Chʽên, and was practising ceremonies with his disciples under a large tree, when they were set upon by emissary of Huan (or Hsiang) Tʽui, a high officer of Sung. These pulled down the tree, and wanted to kill the sage. His disciples urged him to make haste and escape, when he calmed their fears by these words. At the same time, he disguised himself till he had got past Sung. This story may be apocryphal, but the saying remains,—a remarkable one. ↩

Confucius practised no concealment with his disciples. ↩

二三子, see

III xxiv

. 與 is explained by Chu Hsi by 示, "to show," as if the meaning were, "There is not one of my doings in which I am not showing my doctrines to you." But the common signification of 與 may be retained, as in Ho Yen—"which is not given to, shared with, you." To what the concealment has reference we cannot tell. Observe the force of 者 followed by 也 at the end;—"To have none of my actions not shared with you,—that is I, Chʽiu." ↩

The subjects of Confucius's Teachings. ↩

以四教, "took four thing and taught." There were four things which—not four ways in which—Confucius taught. 文 here = our use of letters. 行 = 人倫日用, "what is daily used in the relations of life." 忠 = 無一念之不盡, "not a single thought not exhausted." 信 = 無一事之不實, "not a single thing without its reality." These are the explanations in the

四書備旨

. I confess to apprehend but vaguely the two latter subjects as distinguished from the second. ↩

The paucity of true men in, and the pretentiousness of, Confucius's time. ↩

子曰, par. 2, is supposed by some to be an addition to the text. This being so, we have in the chapter a climax of character:—the man of constancy, or the single-hearted, tasted man; the good man, who on his single-heartedness has built up his virtue; the chün-tzû, the man of virtue in large proportions, and intellectually able besides; and the sage, or highest style of man. 聖, from 耳, 口, and 壬, "ear, mouth, and good," = intuitively apprehensive of truth, and correct in utterance and action. Comp.

Mencius, VII Pt. ii ch. xxv

. ↩

The humanity of Confucius. ↩

綱 is properly the large rope attached to a net, by means of which it may be drawn so as to sweep a stream. 弋, "to shoot with a string tiled to the arrow, by which it may be drawn back again." 射, applied to such shooting, in the 4th tone, is read shih. COnfucius would only destroy what life was necessary for his use, and in taking that he would not take advantage of the inferior creatures. This chapter is said to be descriptive of him in his early life. ↩

Against acting heedlessly. ↩

Pao Hsien, in

Ho Yen

, says that this was spoken with reference to heedless compilers of records. Chu Hsi makes 作之 simply = 作事, "to do things," "to act." The paraphrasts make the latter part descriptive of Confucius—"I hear much, etc." This is not necessary, and the translation had better be as indefinite as the original. ↩

The readiness of Confucius to meet approaches to him though made by the unlikely. ↩

互鄉, the 鄉 appears to be like our local termination ham.—"The people of Hu-ham." Its site is now sought in three different places. ↩

Chu Hsi would have transpose the order of the text, and read 人潔己云云 immediately after 子曰. He also supposes some characters lost in the sentence 唯何甚. This is hardly necessary. 與, as in

V vii 3

, = 許, "to allow," "to concede to." ↩

Virtue is not far to seek. ↩

哉, after 乎, implies the negative answer to be given. ↩

How Confucius acknowledged his error. ↩

Chʽên, one of the States of China in Confucius's time, is to be referred probably to the present department of Chʽên-chou in Henan province. 司敗 was the name given in Chʽên and Chʽu to the minister elsewhere called 司寇, which terms Morrison and Medhurst translate—"criminal judge." But judge does not come up to his functions, which were legislative as well as executive. He was the adviser of his sovereign on all matters relating to crime. See the

周禮, 秋官司寇

. Chao was the honorary epithet of Chʽou (稠), duke of Lu, BC 541–509. He had a reputation for the knowledge and observance of ceremonies, and Confucius answered the minister's question accordingly, the more readily that he was speaking to the officer of another State, and was bound, therefore, to hide any failings that his own sovereign might have had. ↩

With all his knowledge of proprieties, the duke Chao had violated an important rule,—that which forbids the intermarriage of parties of the same surname. The ruling houses of Lu and Wu were branches of the imperial house of Chou, and consequently had the same surname—Chi (姬). To conceal his violation of the rule, Chao called his wife by the surname Tzû (子), as if she had belonged to the ducal house of Sung. 取, the 4th tone = 娶. ↩

Confucius takes the criticism of his questioner very lightly. ↩

The good fellowship of Confucius.↩

On this chapter, see the

四書合講

, which states very distinctly the interpretation which I have followed, making only two singings and not three. 和, 4th tone, here = "to sing in unison with." ↩

Acknowledgment of Confucius in estimating himself.↩

莫 here occasions some difficulty. Ho Yen takes it, as it often is, = 無, and explains, "I am not better than others in letters." In the dictionary, with reference to this passage, it is explained by 强, so that the meaning would be—"By effort, I can equal other men in letters." Chu Hsi makes it 疑辭, a "particle of doubt," = "perhaps." But this is formed for the occasion. 躬行君子, "an in-person-acting chün-tzû." ↩

What Confucius declined to be considered, and what he claimed.↩

若 and 抑 are said to be correlative, in which case they = our "although" and "yet." More naturally, we may join 若 directly with 聖與仁, and take 抑 as = our "but." 云爾, see

chap. xviii 2

. 而矣, added to 云爾, increases its emphasis, = "just this and nothing more." Kung-hsi Hua, see

V vii 4

. ↩

Confucius declines to be prayed for.↩

疾病 together mean "very sick." 有諸;—諸 is interrogative, as we find it frequently in

Mencius

. 誄, "to write a eulogy, and confer the posthumous honorary title;" also, "to eulogise in prayer," i.e. to recite one's excellences as the ground of supplication. Lei is a special from of conposition corresponding to the French éloge, specimens of which are to be found in the

Wên Hsüan (文選)

, of prince Hsiao Tʽung. Wylie,

Notes on Chinese Literature, p. 192

, calls them "obituaries." Tzû-lu must have been referring to some well-known collection of such compositions. In 禱爾, 爾 may be taken as the pronoun. 上下 = heaven and earth, 神 being the appropriate designation of the spirits of the former, and 衹 of the latter.—Chu Hsi says, "Prayer is the expression of repentance and promise of amendment, to supplicate the help of the spirits. If there be not those things, then there is no need for praying. In the case of the sage, he had committed no errors, and admitted of no amendment. In all his conduct he had been in harmony with the spiritual intelligences, and there he said,—my praying has been for a long time." We must demur to some of these expressions; but the declining to be prayed for, and the concluding remark, seem to indicate the satisfaction of Confucius with himself. We wish that our information about him were not so stinted and fragmentary. ↩

Meanness not so bad as insubordination.↩

孫, read sun, like 遜, and with the same meaning. ↩

Contrast in their feelings between the chün-tzû and the mean man.↩

坦, "a level plain," used adverbially with 然, = "lightsomely." This is its force here. 長 = 常時, "constantly." ↩

How various elements modified one another in the character of Confucius.↩

The heading of this book.—泰伯第八, "Tʽai-Po, 'Book VIII.'" As in other cases, the first words of the Book give the name to it. The subjects of the chapter are miscellaneous, but it begins and ends with the character and deeds of ancient sages and worthies, and on this account it follows the seventh chapter, where we have Confucius himself described. ↩

The exceeding virtue of Tʽai-po ↩

Tʽai-po was the eldest son of king Tʽai (太), the grandfather of of Wên, the founder of the Chou dynasty. Tʽai had formed the intention of upsetting the Yin dynasty, of which Tʽai-po disapproved. Tʽai moreover, because of the sage virtues of his grandson Chʽang (昌), who afterwards, became king Wên, wished to hand down his principality to his third son, Chʽang's father. Tʽai-po observing this, and to escape opposing his father's purpose, retired with his second brother among the barbarous tribes of the south, and left their youngest brother in possession of the State. The motives of his conduct Tʽai-po kept to himself, so that the people 不得而稱之, "could not find how to praise him." THere is a difficulty in making out the refusal of the empire three times, there being different accounts of the times and ways in which he did so. Chu Hsi cuts the knot, by making "thrice" = "firmly," in which solution we may acquiesce. There is as great difficulty to find out a declining of the kingdom in Tʽai-po's withdrawing from the petter State of Chou. It may be added that king Wu, the first sovereign of the Chau dynasty, subsequently conferred on Tʽai-po the posthumous title of Chief of Wu (吳), the country to which he had withdrawn, and whose rude inhabitants gathered round him. His second brother succeeded him in the government of them, and hence the ruling house of Wu had the same surname as the royal house of Chou, that namely of Chi (姬);—see

VII xxx

. 也已矣 give emphasis to the preceeding declaration;—compare

I xiv

. ↩

The value of the rules of propriety; and of example in those in high stations. ↩

We must bear in mind that the ceremonies, or rules of propriety, spoken of in these Books, are not mere conventionalities, but the ordinations of man's moral and intelligent nature in the line of what is priper. 絞, "to strange," is here explained by Chu Hsi by 急切. Ho Yen, after Ma Jung (early part of 2nd century), makes it = 絞刺, "sarcasm." ↩

There does not seem any connection between the former paragraph and this, and hence this is by many considered to be a new chapter, and assigned to the philosopher Tsêng. 君子 differs here from its previous usage, having reference more to the 位 or station of the individuals indicated, than to their 德 or virtue. 故舊 = 舊臣舊交, "old ministers and old intimacies." 偷, often a verb, "to steal;" here an adjective, "mean." ↩

The philosopher Tsêng's filial piety seen in his care of his person. ↩

We get our bodies perfect from our parents, and should so perserve them to the last. This is a great branch of filial piety with the Chinese, and this chapter is said to illustrate how Tsêng-tzû (

I iv

) had made this his life-long study. He made the disciples uncover his hands and feet to show them in what preservavtion those members were. 詩云,—see the

Shih-ching, II v I st. 6

. In 而今, we must take 而 = 自. Wang Yin-chih, however, takes the first 而 as = 乃, and adduces other instances of 乃 = 而. Still the usage is remarkable. ↩

The philosopher Tsêng's dying counsels to a man of high rank. ↩

敬 was the honorary epithet of 仲孫捷, a great officer of Lu, and son of Mêng-wu

II vi

. From the conclusion of this chapter, we may suppose that he descended to small matters below his rank. 之 refers to 疾. ↩

言, in 曾子言曰, intimates that Tsêng commenced the conversation. ↩

動, 正, and 出 are all = verbs governing the nouns following. 倍 is read like 背, and with the same meaning, "to rebel against," "to be contrary to," that here opposed being 道, "the truth and right." 籩 was a bamboo dish with a stand, made to hold fruits and seeds at sacrifice; 豆 was like it, and of the same size, only made of wood, and used to contain pickled vegetables and sauces. 君子 is used as in

chap. ii

.—In Ho Yen's compilation, the three clauses, beginning 斯遠, are taken not so well, and = "thus he will not suffer from men's being violent and insulting, etc. etc. ↩

A combination of talents and virtue constituting a chün-tzü. ↩

六尺之孤, "an orphan of six cubits." By a comparison of a passage in the Chou Li and other references, it is established that "of six cubits" is equivalent to "of fifteen years or less," and that for every cubit more or less we should add or deduct five years. See the

經註集證

, where it is also said that the ancient cubit was shorter than the modern, and only = 7.4 in., so that six cubits = 4.4 cubits of the present day. But this estimate of the ancient cubbit is probably still too high. King Wên, it is said, was ten cubits high! 百里之命, see

Mencius, V Pt. ii ch. ii 6

. 與 amounts nearly to a question, and is answered by 也,—"Yes, indeed." ↩

The necessity to the officer of compass and vigour of mind. ↩

士, a learned man, "a scholar;" but in all ages learning has been the qualification for, and passport to, official employment in China, hence it is also a general designation for "an officer." 任, 4th tone, a noun, = "an office," "a burden borne;" with the 2nd tone, it is a verb "to bear." ↩

The effects of poetry, proprieties, and music. ↩

These three short sentences are in form like the four, 志於道, etc. in

VII vi

, but must be interpreted differently. There the first term in each sentence is a verb in the imperative mood; here it is rather in the indicative. There the 於 is to be joined closely to the 1st character and here to the 3rd. There it = our preposition to; here it = by. The terms 詩, 禮, 樂 have all specific reference to the Books so called. ↩

What may, and what may not be attained to with the people ↩

According to Chu Hsi, the first 之 is 理之所以然, "the principle of duty." He also takes 可 and 不可 as = 能 and 不能. If the meaning were so, then the sentiment would be much too broadly expressed. See

四書改錯, XVI xv

. As often in other places, the

翼註

gives the meaning here happily; viz. that a knowledge of the reasons and principles of what they are called to do need not be required from the people,—不可貴之民. ↩

Different causes of insubordination;—a lesson to rulers. ↩

The worthiness of talent without virtue. ↩

"The duke of Chou;"—see

VII v

. 其餘, "the overplus," "the superfluity," referring to the "talents," and indicating that ability is not the 本, or root of character, not what is essential. 也已, as in

chap. i

. ↩

How quickly learning makes men good. ↩

This is the interpretation of Kʽung An-kuo, who takes 穀 in the sense of 善. Chu Hsi takes the term in the sense of 祿, "emolument," and would change 至 into 志, making the whole a lamentation over the rarity of the disinterested pursuit of learning. But we are not at liberty to admit alterations of the text, unless, as received, it be absolutely unintelligible. ↩

The qualification of an officer, who will always act right in accepting and declining office. ↩

This paragraph is taken as descriptive of character, the effects of whose presence we have in the neext, and of its absence in the last. ↩

見 in opposition to 隱, read hsien, in 4th tone. The whole chapter seems to want the warmth of generous principle and feeling. In fact, I doubt whether its parts bear the relation and connection which they are supposed to have. ↩

Every man should mind his own business. ↩

So the sentiment of this chapter is generalized by the paraphrasts, and perhaps correctly. Its letter, however, has doubtless operated to prevent the spread of right notions about political liberty in China. ↩

The praise of the music-master Chih. ↩

Neither Morrison nor Medhurst gives what appears to be the meaning of 亂 in this chapter. The

Kʽang-hsi dictionary

has it—樂之卒章曰亂, "The last part in the musical services is called luan." The programme on those occasions consisted of four parts, in the last of which a number of pieces from the fêng or songs of the States was sung, commencing with the Kuan Chü. The name luan was also given to a sort of refrain, at the end of each song.—The old interpreters explain differently,—"when the music-master Chih first corrected the confusion of the Kuan Chü," etc. ↩

A lamentation over moral errors added to natural defect. ↩

吾不知之, "I do not know them;" that is, say commentators, natural defects of endowment are generally associated with certain redeeming qualities, as hestiness with straightforwardness, etc., but in the parties Confucius had in view, those redeeming qualities were absent. he did not understand them, and could do nothing for them. ↩

With what earnestness and continuousness learning should be pursued. ↩

The lofty character of Shun and Yü. ↩

Shun receive from Yao, BC 2205, and Yü received it from Shun, BC. Th throne came to them not by inheritance. They were called to it through their talents and virtue. And yet the possession of it did not affect them at all. 不與,—"it did not concern them," was as if nothing to them. Ho Yen takes 與 = 求,—"they had the empire without seeking for it." This is not according to usage. ↩

The praise of Yao. ↩

No doubt, Yao, as he appears in Chinese annals, is a fit object of admiration, but if Confucius had had a right knowledge of, and reverence for, Heaven, he could not have spoken as he does here. Grant that it is only the visible heaven overspreading all, to which he compares Yao, even that is sufficiently absurd. 則之, not simply = 法之, "imitated it," but 能與之準, "could equalize with it." ↩

其有成功 = 其所有之成功, "the great achievvements of his government. 文章 (see

V xii

.) = the music, ceremonies, etc., of which he was the author. ↩

The scarcity of men of talent, and praise of the house of Chou. ↩

Shun's five ministers were 禹, Superintendent of Works, 稷, Superintendent of Agriculture; 契 (hsieh), Minister of Instruction; 皋陶, Minister of Justice; and 伯益, Warden of Woods and Marshes. Those five, as being eminent above all their compeers, are mentioned. ↩

See the

Shu-ching V i sect. ii 6

. 亂臣, "governing, i.e. able ministers." In the dictionary, the first meaning given of 亂 is "to regulate," and the second is just the opposite,—"to confound," "confusion." Of the ten ministers, the most distinguished of course was the duke of Chou. One of them, it is said next paragraph, was a woman, but whether she was the mother of king Wên, or his wife, is much disputed. The ten men were:—the duke of Chou, the duke of Shao, Grandfather Hope, the duke of Pi, the duke of Jung, Tʽai-tien, Hung-yao, San-i Shêng, Nan-kung Kʽuo, and the wife or mother of king Wên. ↩

Instead of the usual (The Master said," we have here 孔子曰, "The philosopher Kʽung said." This is accounted for on the ground that the words of king Wu having been quoted immediately before, it would not have been right to crown the sage with his usual title of "the Master." The style of the whole chapter, however, is different from that of any previous one, and we may suspect that it is corrupt. 才難 is a sort of proverb, or common saying, which Confucius quotes and illustrates. 唐虞之際 (Yao is called Tʽang, having ascended the throne from the marquisate of that name, and Yü became a sort of accepted surname or style of Shun) 於斯爲盛 is understood by Chu Hsi as in the translation, while the old writers take exactly the opposite view. The whole is obscure. ↩

This paragraph must be spoken of king Wên. ↩

The praise of Yü. ↩

閒, read chien, 4th tone, "a crevice," "a crack." The form 間 in the text is not so correct. 禹吾無閒然矣, "In Yü, I find no crevice so," i.e. I find nothing in him to which I can point as a flaw. 鬼神 is interpreted of the spirits of heaven and earth, as well as those sacrificed to in the ancestral temple, but the saying that the rich offerings were filial (孝) would seem to restrict the phrase to the latter. The 黻 was an apron made of leather, and coming down over the knees, and the 冕 was a sort of cap or crown, flat on the top, and projecting before and behind, with a long fringe on which gems and pearls were strung, exactly like the Christ-Church cap of Oxford. They were both used in sacrificing. 溝洫, generally the water-channels by which the boundaries of the fields were determined, and provision made for their irrigation, and to carry off the water of floods. The 溝 were four cubits wide and deep, and arranged so as to flow into the 洫, which were double the size. ↩

Heading of this Book.—子罕第九, "The Master seldom, No. 9." The thirty chapters of this Book are much akin to those of the

seventh

. They are mostly occupied with the doctrine, character, and ways of Confucius himself. ↩

Subjects seldom spoken of by Confucius. ↩

利 is mostly taken here in a good sense, not as selfish gain, but as it is defined under the first of the diagrams in the

Yi-ching

,—義之和, "the harmoniousness of all that is righteous;" that is, how what is right is really what is truly profitable. Compare

Mencius, I i 1

. Yet even in this sense COnfucius seldom spoke of it, as he would not have the consideration of the profitable introduced into conduct at all. With his not speaking of 仁 there is a difficulty which I know not how to solve. The

fourth Book

is nearly all occupied with it, and no doubt it was a prominent topic in Confucius's teachings. 命 is not = our fate, unless in the primary meaning of that term,—"Fatum est quod dii fantur." Nor is it decree, or antecedent purpose and determination, but the decree embodied and realised in its object. ↩

Amusement of Confucius at the remark of an ignorant man about him. Commentators, old and new, say theat the chapter shows the exceeding humility of the sage, educed by his being praised, but his observation on the man's remark was evidently ironical. ↩

For want of another word, I render 黨 by "village." According to the statutes of Chou, "five families made a 比, four pi a 閭, and five lü or 500 families a tang." Who the villager was is not receorded, though some would have him to be the same with 項槖, the boy of whom it is said in the

三字經

, 昔仲尼師項槖, "of old Confucius was a scholar of Hsiang Tʽo." The man was able to see that Confucius was very extensively learned, but his idea of fame, common to the age, was that it must be acquired by excellence in some one particular art. In his lips, 孔子 was not more than our "Mr. Kʽung." ↩

Some common practices indifferent and others not. ↩

The cap here spoken of was that prescribed to be worn in the ancestral temple, and made of very fine linen dyed of a deep dark colour. It had fallen into disuse, and was superseded by a simpler one of silk. Rather than be singular, Confucius gave in to a practice, which involved no principle of right, and was economical. ↩

Chu Hsi explains the 拜下, 拜乎上, thus: "In the ceremonial intercourse between ministers and their prince, it was proper for them to bow below the raised hall. This the prince declined, on which they ascended and completed the homage." SSee this illustrated in the

經註集證

, in loc. The prevailing disregard of the first part of the ceremony COnfucius considered inconsistent with the proper distance to be observed between prince and minister, and therefore he would be singular in adhering to the rules. ↩

Frailties from which Confucius was free. ↩

毋, it is said, is not prohibitive here, but simply negative;—to make it appear that it was not by any effort, as 絕 and 毋 more naturally suggest, that Confucius attained to these things. ↩

Confucius assured in a time of danger by his conviction of a divine mission. Compare

VII xxii

, but the adventure to which this chapter refers is placed in the sage's history before the other, not long after he had resigned office, and left Lu. ↩

There are different opinions as to what State Kʽuang belonged to. The most likely is that it was a border town of Chêng, and its site is now to be found in the department of Kaifeng in Henan. It is said the Kʽuang had suffered from 陽虎, an officer of Lu, to whom Confucius bore a resemblance. As he passed by the place, moreover, a disciple, 顔刻, who had been associated with Yang Hu in his measures against Kʽunang, was driving him. These circumstances made the people think that Confucius was their old enemy, so that attacked him, and kept him prisoner for five days. The accounts of his escape vary, some of them being evidently fabulous. The disciples were in fear. 畏 would indicate that Confucius himself was so, but this is denied. ↩

The wên I render by "the cause of truth." More exactly, it is the truth embodied in literature, ceremonies, etc., and its use instead of tao, "truth in its principles," is attributed to Confucius's modesty. 在茲, "in this," referring to himself. ↩

There may be modesty in his use of wên, but he here identifies himself with the line of the great sages, to whom Heaven has intrusted the instruction of men. In all the six centuries between himself and king Wên, he does not admit of such another. 後死者, "he who dies afterwards," = a future mortal. ↩

On the various ability of Confucius:—His sagehood not therein. ↩

According to the

周禮

, the 太宰 was the chief of the six great officers of State, but the use of the designation in Confucius's time was confined to the State of Wu and Sung, and hence the officer in the text must have belonged to one of them. See the

註疏

, in loc. The force of 與 is as appears in the translation. ↩

與 is responded to by Tzû-kung with 固, "certainly," while yet by the use of 將 he gives his answer an air of hesitancy. 縱之, "lets him go," i.e. does not restrict him at all. The officer had found the sagehood of Confucius in his various ability;—by the yu, "moreover," Tzû-kung makes that ability only an additional circumstance. ↩

Confucius explains his possession of various ability, and repudiates its being essential to the sage, or even to the chün-tzû. ↩

Lao was a disciple, by surname Chʽin (琴), and styled Tzû-kʽai (子開), or Tzû-chang (子張). It is supposed that when these conversations were being digested into their present form, someone remembered that Lao had been in the habit of mentioning the remark given, and accordingly it was appended to the chapter. 之云 indicates that it was a frequent saying of Confucius. ↩

Confucius disclaims the knowledge attributed to him, and declares his earnestness in teaching. ↩

The first sentence here was probably an exclamation with reference to some remark upon himself as having extraordinary knowledge. 叩其兩端, "exhibit (叩 = 發動, "to agitate") its two ends," i.e. discuss it from beginning to end. ↩

For want of auspicious omens, Confucius gives up the hope of the triumph of his doctrines. ↩

The fêng is the male of a fabulous bird, which has been called the Chinese phoenix, said to appear when a sage ascends the throne or when right principles are going to triumph in the world. The female is called 凰. In the days of Shun, they gambolled in his hall, and were heard singing on mount Chʽi in the time of king Wên. The river and the map carry us farther back still,—to the time of Fu-hsi, to whom a monster with the head of a dragon, and the body of a horse, rose from the water, being marked on the back so as to give that first of the sages the idea of his diagrams. Confucius indorses these fables. 吾已矣夫,—see

V xxvi

, and observes how 乎 and 夫 are interchanged. ↩

Confucius's sympathy with sorrow, respect for rank, and pity for misfortune. ↩

齊, read tzû, "the lower edge of a garment," and joined with 衰, read tsʽui, "mourning garments," the two characters indicate the mourning of the second degree of intensity, where the edge is unhemmed, but cut even, instead of being ragged, the terms for which are 斬衰. The phrase, however, seems to be for "in mourning" generally. 少, in 4th tone, "young." ↩

Yen Yüan's admiration of his master's doctrines; and his own progress in them. ↩

喟然歎, "sighingly sighed." 仰 and the other verbs here are to be translated in the past tense, as the chapter seems to give an account of the progress of Hui's mind. 忽焉 = 忽然, "suddenly." ↩

誘 = 引進, "to lead forward." 博我云云,—comp.

VI xxv

. ↩

卓爾 = 卓然, an adverb, "uprightly," "loftily." 末, in the sense of 無. 末由 = 無所由以用其力, "I find myself unable to use my strength." 也已, "yea, indeed."—It was this which made him sigh. ↩

Confucius's dislike of pretension, and contentment with his condition. ↩

使, "was causing," or wanted to cause. Confucius's had been a great officer, and enjoyed the services of ministers, as in a petty court. Tzû-lu would have surrounded him in his great sickness with the illusions of his former state, and brought on himself this rebuke. ↩

縱 = 縱然, as a conjunction, "letting it be that," = although. ↩

How the desire for office should be qualified by self-respect. ↩

諸 is interrogative here, as in

VII xxxiv

. There being no nominative to 轀, like the "I" in the translation, we might render, "should it be put," etc. 賈, read chia, 4th tone = 價, "price," "value." The disciple wanted to elicit from Confucius why he declined office so much, and insinuated his question in this way. It seems better to translate yü here by "a gem," or a "precious stone," than by "a piece of jade." ↩

How barbarians can be civilized. This chapter is to be understood, it is said, like

V vi

, not as if Confucius really wished to go among the Yi, but that he thus expressed his regret that his doctrine did not find acceptance in China. ↩

The Yi,—see

III v

. There were nine tribes of varieties (種) of them, the yellow, white, red, etc. ↩

如之何,—the 之 refers to his purpose to go among the Yi. ↩

Confucius's services in correcting the music of this native State and Adjusting The Book of Poetry. ↩

Confucius returned from Wei to Lu in his 69th year, and died five years after. The 雅 (read ya, 3rd tone) and the 頌 are the names of two, or rather three, of the divisions of the

Shih-ching

, the former being the "elegant" or "correct" odes, to be used with music at royal festivals, and the latter the praise songs, celebrating principally the virtues of the founders of different dynasties, to be used in the services of the ancestral temple. ↩

Confucius's very humble estimate of himself. ↩

Comp.

VII ii

, but the things which Confucius here disclaims are of a still lower character than those there mentioned. Very remarkable is the last, as from the sage. The old interpreters treat 何有於我哉, as they do in

VII ii

;—compare

VII xxv

,

xxvii

,

xxxiii

, et al. 公卿 stand together, indicating men of superior rank. If we distinguish between them, the 公 may express the princes, high officers in the royal court, and the 卿, the high officers in the princes' court. ↩

How Confucius was affected by a running stream. ↩

What does the it in the translation refer to? 者 and 如 indicate something in the sage's mind, suggested by the ceaseless movement of the water. Chu Hsi is correct. Comp.

Mencius, IV Pt. ii ch. xviii

. ↩

The rarity of a sincere love of virtue.↩

色 as in

I vii

. ↩

That learners should not cease nor intermit their labours. ↩

This is a fragment, like many other chapters, of some conversation, and the subject thus illustrated must be supplied, after the modern commentator, as in the translation, or, after the old, by "the following of virtues." See the

Shu-ching, V v 9

, where the subject is virtuous consistency. We might expect 平 in 平地 to be a verb, like 爲 in 爲山, but a good sense cannot be made out by taking it so. 雖, = "though only," as many take it in

Vi xxiv

. The lesson of the chapter is—that repeated acquisitions individually small will ultimately amount to much, and that the learner is never to give ever. ↩

Hui the earnest student. ↩

Confucius's fond recollection of Hui as a model student. ↩

This is said to have been spoken after Hui's death. 惜乎 looks as if it were so. The 未, "not yet," would rather make us think differently. ↩

It is the end which crowns the work.↩

How and why a youth should be regarded with respect. ↩

The same person is spoken of throughout the chapter, as is shown by the 亦 in the last sentence. This is not very conclusive, but it brings out a good enough meaning. With Confucius's remark compare that of John Trebonius, Luther's schoolmaster at Eisenach, who used to raise his cap to his pupils on entering the schoolroom, and gave as the reason—"There are among these boys men of whom God will one day make burgomasters, chancellors, doctors, and magistrates. Although you do not yet see them with the badges of their dignity, it is right that you should treat them with respect." 後生, "after born," a youth. See 先生,

II viii

. ↩

The hopelessness of the case of those who assent and approve without reformation or serious thought. ↩

法語之言, "words of law-link admonition." 巽 is the name of the 5th trigram, to which the element of "wind" is attached. Wind enters everywhere, hence the character is interpreted by "entering," and also by "mildness," "yielding." 巽與之言, "words of gentle insinuation." In 繹之爲貴, an antecedent to 之 is readily found in the preceding 言, but in 改之爲貴, such an antecedent can only be found in a roundabout way. This is one of the cases which shows the inapplicability to Chinese composition of our strict syntactical apparatus. 末 as in

chap. x

. ↩

This is a repetition of part of

I viii

. ↩

The will unsubduable. ↩

三軍, see

VII x

. 帥, read shuai, 4th tone, = 將帥, "a general." 匹, "mate." We find in the dictionary—"Husband and wife of the common people are a pair (相匹), and the application of the term being thus fixed, an individual man is called 匹夫, and individual woman 匹婦. ↩

Tzû-lu's brave contentment in poverty, but failure to seek the highest aims. ↩

On the construction of this paragraph, compare

chap. xviii

. The 狐 is the fox. The 貉, read ho, is probably the badger. It is described as nocturnal in its habits, having a soft, warm fur. It sleeps much, and is carnivorous. This last characteristic is not altogether inapplicable to the badger. See the

本草獸部.

↩

See the

Shih-ching I iii Ode viii 4

. ↩

終身, not "all his life," as frequently, but "continually." Tzû-lu was a man of impulse, with many fine points, but not sufficiently reflective. ↩

Men are known in times of adversity. ↩

後彫, "the after-withering," a meiosis for their being evergreens. ↩

The sequences of wisdom, virtue, and bravery. ↩

仁者不憂,—this is one of the sayings about virtue, which is only true when it is combined with trust in God. ↩

How different individuals stop at different stages of progress. ↩

More literally rendered, this chapter would be—"It may be possible with some parties together to study, but it may not yet be possible with them to go on to principles, etc." 權, the weight of a steelyard, then "to weight." It is used here with reference to occurring events,—to weigh them and determine the application of principles to them. In the old commentaries, 權 is used here in opposition to 經, the latter being that which is always, and everywhere right, the former a deviation from that in particular circumstances, to bring things, right. This meaning of the term here is denied. The ancients adopted it probably from their interpretation of the second clause in the next chapter, which they made one with this. ↩

The necessity of refelction. ↩

This is understood to be from one of the pieces of poetry, which were not admitted into the collection of the

Shih

, and no more of it being preserved than what we have here, it is not altogether intelligible. There are long disputes about the 唐棣. Chu Hsi makes it a kind of small plum or cherry tree, whose leaves are constantly quivering, even when there is no wind; and adopting a reading, in a book of the Chin (晉) dynasty, of 翩 for 偏, and changing 翻 into 反, he makes out the meaning in the translation. The old commentators keep the text, and interpret,—"How perversely contrary are the flowers of the Tʽang ti!" saying that those flowers are first open and then shut. This view made them take 權 in the last chapter, as we have noticed. Who or what is meant by 爾 in 爾思, we cannot tell. The two 而 are mere expletives, completing the rhythm. ↩

With this paragraph Chu Hsi compares

VII xxix

—The whole piece is like the

20th of the last Book

, and suggests the thought of its being an addition by another hand to the original compilation. ↩

Heading of the book.—鄉黨第十, "The village, No. 10." This Book is different in its character from all the others in the work. It contains hardly any sayings of Confucius, but is descriptive of his ways and demeanour in a variety of places and circumstances. It is not uninteresting, but, as a whole, it hardly heightens our veneration for the sage. We seem to know him better from it, and perhaps to Western minds, after being viewed in his bedchamber, his undress, and at his meals, he becomes divested of a good deal of his dignity and reputation. There is something remarkable about the style. Only in one passage is its subject styled 子, "The Master." He appears either as 孔子, "The Philosopher Kʽung," or as 君子, "The superior man." A suspicion is thus raised that the chronicler had not the same relation to him as the compilers of the other Books. Anciently, the book formed only one chapter, but it is now arranged under seventeen divisions. Those divisions, for convenience in the translation, I continue to denominate chapters, which is done also in some native editions. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius in his village, in the ancestral temple, and the court. ↩

According to the dictionary, quoting from a record of "the former Han dynasty, the 鄉 contained 2,500 families, and the 黨 only 500;" but the two terms are to be taken here together, indicating the residence of the sage's relatives. his native place in Lu is doubtless intended, rather than the original seat of his family in Sung. 恂恂如 is explained by Wang Su "mild-like," and by Chu Hsi, as in the translation, thinking probably that, with that meaning, it suited the next clause better. ↩

便, read pien, the 2nd tone = 辯, "to debate," "to discriminate accurately." 爾 = 耳. In those two places of high ceremony and of government, it became the sage, it is said, to be precise and particular. Compare

III xv

. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius at court with other great officers, and before the prince. ↩

朝 may be taken here as a verb, literally, = "courting." It was the custom for all the officers to repair at daybreak to the court, and wait for the ruler to give them an audience. 大夫, "Great officer," was a general name, applicable to all the higher officers in a court. At the royal court they were divided into three classes,—"highest," "middle," and "lowest," 上, 中, 下, but the various princes had only the first and third. Of the first order there were properly three, the 卿, or nobles of the State, who were in Lu the chiefs of the "three families." Confucius belonged himself to the lower grade. ↩

踧踖 = "the feet moving uneasily," indicating the respectful anxiety of the mind. 與, 2nd tone, here appears in the phrase 與與如也, in a new sense. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius at the official reception of a visitor. ↩

The visitor is supposed to be the ruler of another State. On the occasion of two princes meeting there was much ceremony. The visitor having arrived, he remained outside the front gate, and the host inside his reception room, which was in the ancestral temple. Messages passed between them by means of a number of officers called 介, on the side of the visitor, and 檳, on teh side of the host, who formed a zigzag line of communication from the one to the other, and passed their questions and answers along, till an understanding about the visit was thus officially effected. 足躩如 probably has the meaning which I have given in the translation. ↩

This shows Confucius's manner when engaged in the transmission of the messages between the prince and his visitor. The prince's nuncio, in immediate communication with himself, with the 上檳, the next was the 承檳, and below were one or more 紹檳. Confucius must have been the chʽêng pin, bowing to the right as he transmitted a message to the shang pin, who was an officer of the higher grade, and to the left as he communicated one from him to the shao pin. ↩

The host having come out to receive his visitor, proceeded in with him, it is said, followed by all their internuncios in a line, and to his manner in this movement this paragraph is generally referred. But the duty of seeing the guest off, the subject of next paragraph, belonged to the shang pin, and could not be performed by Confucius as merely a chʽêng pin. Hence arises a difficulty. Either it is true that Confucius was at one time raised to the rank of teh highest dignitaries of the State, or he was temporarily employed, form his knowledge of ceremonies, after the first act in the reception of visitors, to discharge the duties of one. Assuming this, the 趨進 is to be explained of some of his movements in the reception room. How could he hurry forward when walking in file with the other internuncios? See the

拓餘説, II xxiii

. href="chapter-10-3.xhtml#noteref-656" epub:type="backlink">↩

必復命, "would return the commission," i.e. he had seen the guest off, according to his duty, and reported it. The ways of China, it appears, were much the same anciently as now. A guest turns round and bows repeatedly in leaving, and the host cannot return to his place, till these salutations are ended. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius in the court at an audience. ↩

The royal court consisted of five divisions, each having its peculiar gate. That of a prince of a State consisted only of three, whose gates were named 庫, 雉, and 路. The 公門 is the kʽu, or first of these. The bending his body when passing through, high as the gate was, is supposed to indicate the great reverence which Confucius felt. ↩

不中門 = 不中於門, "He did not stand opposite the middle of the gateway." Each gate had a post in the centre, called 闃, by which it was divided into two halves, appropriated to ingress and egress. The prince only could stand in the centre of either of them, and he only could tread on the threshold or sill. ↩

齊, see

IX ix

. He is now ascending the steps to the 堂, "the dais," or raised platform in the inner apartment, where the prince held his council, or gave entertainments, and from which the family rooms of the palace branched off. ↩

At the early formal audience at daybreak, when the prince came out of the inner apartment, and received the homage of the officers, he occupied a particular spot called 宁 in

par. 3

, but improperly. 進 after 趨 is an addition that has somehow crept into the ordinary text. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius when employed on a friendly embassy. ↩

圭 may be translated "sceptre," in the sense simply of "a badge of authority." It was a piece of jade, conferred by the sovereign on the princes, and differed in size and shape, according to their rank. They took it with them when they attended the king's court, and, according to Chu Hsi and the old interpreters, it was carried also by their representatives as their voucher, on occasions of embassies among themselves. In the

拓餘説, II xxxiii

, however, it is contended, apparently on sufficient grounds, that the sceptre then employed was different from the other. 勝, 1st tone, "to be equal to," "able for." ↩

The preceding paragraph describes Confucius's manner in the friendly court, at his first interview, showing his credentials and delivering his message. That done, he had to deliver the various presents with which he was charged. This was called 享 = 獻. ↩

After all the public presents were delivered, the ambassador had others of his own to give, and his interview for that purpose was called 私覿.—Chu Hsi remarks that there is no record of Confucius ever having been employed on such a mission, and supposes that his chapter and the preceding are simply summaries of the manner in which he used to say duties referred to in them ought to be discharged. ↩

Rules of Confucius in regard to his dress.—The discussions about the colours here mentioned are lengthy and tedious. I am not confident that I have given them all correctly in the translation. ↩

君子, used here to denote Confucius, can hardly have come from the hand of a disciple. 紺 = 深青楊赤色, "a deep azure flushed with carnation." 緅 = 絳色, "a deep red;" it was dipped thrice in a red dye, and then twice in a black. 飾, "for ornament," i.e. for the edgings of the collar and sleeves. The kan, it is said, by Chu Hsi, after Kʽung An-kuo, was worn in fasting, and the tsou in mourning, on which account Confucius would not use them. See this and the account of the colours denied in the

拓餘説, in loc.

↩

There are five colours which go by the name of 正, "correct," viz. 青, 黃, 赤, 白, 黑, "azure, yellow, carnation, white, and black;" others, among with are 紅 and 紫, go by the name of 間, or "intermediate." See the

集證, in loc. Confucius would use only correct colours, and moreover, Chu Hsi adds, red and reddish-blue are liked by women and girls. 䙝服, his dress, when in private. ↩

絺 and 綌 were made from the fibres of a creeping plant, the 葛. See the

Shih-ching, I i Ode ii

. 必表而出之, "he must display and have it outwards." The interpretation of this, as in the translation, after Chu Hsi, though differing from the old commentators, seems to be correct. ↩

The lamb's fur belonged to the court dress, the fawn's was worn on embassies, the fox's on occasions of sacrifice, etc. ↩

Confucius knew how to blend comfort and convenience. ↩

This paragraph it is supposed, belong to the next chapter, in which case it is not the usual sleeping garment of Confucius that is spoken of, but the one he used in fasting. 長, 2nd tone, "over," "overplus." ↩

These are the 䙝裘 of

paragraph 5

. ↩

The appendages of the girdle were, the handkerchief, a small knife, a spike for opening knots, etc. 去, 3rd tone, "to put away." ↩

The 裳 was the lower garment, reaching elow the knees like a kilt or petticoat. For court and sacrificial dress, it was made curtain-like, as wide at top as at bottom. In that worn on other occasions, Confucius saved the cloth in the way described. So, at least, says Kʽung An-kuo. 殺, read shai, 4th tone. ↩

Lamb's fur was worn with black (

par. 4

), but white is the colour of mourning in China, and Confucius would not visit mourners, but in a sympathising colour. ↩

吉月, "the fortunate day of the moon," i.e. the first of the month. This was Confucius's practice, after he had ceased to be in office. ↩

Rules observed by Confucius when fasting. ↩

齊, read chai, 1st tone; see

VII xii. The

6th paragraph

of the last chapter should come in as the 2nd here. ↩

The fasting was not from all food, but only from wine or spirits, and from pot herbs. Observe the difference between 變 and 遷, the former "to change," the latter "to change from," "to remove."—The whole chapter may be compared with Matthew 6:16–18. ↩

Rules of Confucius about this food. ↩

膾, "minced meat," the commentators say, was made of beef, mutton, or fish, uncooked. 100 shing of paddy were reduced to 30, to bring it to the state of 精 rice. ↩

飪 in the dictionary is "overdone," hence 失飪 = "wrong in being overdone." Some, however, make the phrase to mean, "badly cooked," either underdone or overdone. ↩

食 (shih) 氣, "the breath of the rice," or perhaps, "the life-sustaining power of it," bu 氣 can hardly be translated here. 唯 = 惟, "only," showing, it is said, that in other thingshe had a limit, but the use of wine being to make glad, he could not beforehand set a limit to the quantity of it. See, however, the singular note in

IX xv

. ↩

Literally, "he did not take away ginger in eating." ↩

The prince, anciently (and it is still a custom), distributed among the assisting ministers the flesh of his sacrifice. Each would only get a little, and so it could be used at once. ↩

瓜 should be changed into 必, according to Chu Hsi. Ho Yen, however, retains it, and putting a comma after it, joins it with the two preceding specimens of spare diet. The "sacrificing" refers to a custom something like our saying grace. The master took a few grains of rice, or part of the other provisions, and placed them on the ground, among the sacrificial vessels, a tribute to the worthy or worthies who first taught the art of cooking. The Buddhist priests in their monasteries have a custom of this kind, and on public occasions, and when Chʽi-ying gave an entertainment in Hong Kong in 1845, something like it is sometimes observed, but any such ceremony is unknown among the common habits of the people. However poor might be his fare, Confucius always observed. 齊 (chai) = 齋, the grave demeanour appropriate to fasting. ↩

Rule of Confucius about his mat. ↩

Other ways of Confucius in his village. ↩

At sixty, people carried a staff. Confucius here showed his respect for age. 斯 has here an adverbial force, = 即. ↩

There were three 儺 ceremonies eery year, but that in the text was called "the great no," being observed in the winter season, when the officers led all the people of a village about, searching every house to expel demons, and drive away pestilence. It was conducted with great uproar, and little better than a play, but Confucius saw a good old idea in it, and when the mob was in his house, he stood on the eastern steps (the place of a host receiving guests) in full dress. Some make the steps those of his ancestral temple, and his standing there to be to assure the spirits of his shrine. ↩

Traits of COnfucius's intercourse with others. ↩

The two bows were not to the messenger, but intended for the distant friend to whom he was being sent. ↩

康 was the 季康子 of

II xx

et al. Confucius accepted the ift, but thought it necessary to let the donor know he could not, for the present at least, avail himself of it. ↩

How Confucius valued human life. ↩

A rule's 厩was fitted to accommodate 216 horses. See the

集證, in loc.

It may be used indeed for a private stable, but it is more natural to take it here for the 國 or State chiu. This is the view in the

家語

. ↩

Demeanour of Confucius in relation to his prince. ↩

He would not offer the cooked meat to the spirits of his ancestors, not knowing but it might previously have been offered by the prince to the spirits of his. But he reverently tasted it, as if he had been in the prince's presence. He "honoured" the gift of cooked food, "glorified" the undressed, and "was kind" to the living animal. ↩

The 祭 here is that in

chapter viii 10

. Among parties of equal rank, all performed the ceremony, but Confucius, with his prince, held that the prince sacrificed for all. He tasted everything, as if he had been a cook, it being the cook's duty to taste every dish, before the prince partook of it. ↩

首, in the 4th tone, 頭向, "the direction of the head." The head to the east was the proper position for a person in bed; a sick man might for comfort be lying differently, but Confucius would not see the prince but in the correct position, and also in the court dress, so far as he could accomplish it. ↩

He would not wait a moment, but let his carriage follow him. ↩

A repetition of

III xv

, of the questioning being on his first entrance on office very doubtful. ↩